<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><a name="area-chapter"></a>
<chapter name="area-chapter" number="17" title="Areas"><index-entry index="concepts" title="area"></index-entry>

<p>Storage in the Lisp Machine is divided into <arg>areas</arg>.  Each area
contains related objects, of any type.  Areas are intended to give the
user control over the paging behavior of the program, among other
things.  Putting frequently used data and rarely used data in different
areas can cause the frequently used data to occupy fewer pages.  For
example, the system puts the debugging info alists of compiled functions
in a special area so that the other list structure the functions point
to will be more compact.
</p>

<p>Whenever a new object is created the area to be used can
optionally be specified.  For example, instead of using <obj>cons</obj> you can
use <obj>cons-in-area</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-con" key="cons-in-area-fun" title="Function cons-in-area" type="fun"></ref>).  Object-creating functions
which take keyword arguments generally accept a <obj>:area</obj> argument.
You can also control which area is used by binding <obj>default-cons-area</obj>
(see <ref definition-in-file="areas" key="default-cons-area-var" title="Variable default-cons-area" type="var"></ref>); most functions that allocate storage
use the value of this variable, by default, to specify the area to use.
</p>

<p>There is a default `working storage' area that collects those objects
that the user has not chosen to control explicitly. 
</p>

<p indent="1">        Areas also give the user a handle to control the garbage
collector.  Some areas can be declared to be <arg>static</arg>, which means that
they change slowly and the garbage collector should not attempt to
reclaim any space in them.  This can eliminate a lot of useless
copying.  A static area can be explicitly
garbage-collected at infrequent intervals when it is believed that that
might be worthwhile. 
</p>

<p indent="1">        Each area can potentially have a different storage discipline,
a different paging algorithm, and even a different data representation. 
The microcode dispatches on attributes of the area at the
appropriate times.  The structure of the machine makes the performance
cost of these features negligible; information about areas is stored
in extra bits in the memory mapping hardware where it can be quickly
dispatched on by the microcode; these dispatches usually have to be
done anyway to make the garbage collector work and to implement
invisible pointers.  This feature is not currently used by the system,
except for the list/structure distinction described below.
</p>

<p indent="1">        Each area has a name and a number.  The name is a symbol whose
value is the number.  The number is an index into various internal
tables.  Normally the name is treated as a special variable, so the
number is what is given as an argument to a function that takes an area
as an argument.  Thus, areas are not Lisp objects; you cannot
pass an area itself as an argument to a function; you just pass its
number.  There is a maximum number of areas (set at cold-load generation
time); you can only have that many areas before the various internal
tables overflow.  Currently (as this manual is written) the limit is
256 areas, of which 64 already exist when you start.
</p>

<p indent="1">        The storage of an area consists of one or more <arg>regions</arg>.  Each region
is a contiguous section of address space with certain homogeneous properties.
The most important of these is the <arg>data representation type</arg>.  A given region
can only store one type.  The two types that exist now are <arg>list</arg> and <arg>structure</arg>.
A list is anything made out of conses (a closure for instance).  A structure is
anything made out of a block of memory with a header at the front; symbols, strings,
arrays, instances, compiled functions, etc.  Since lists and structures cannot be stored
in the same region, they cannot be on the same page.  It is necessary to know about
this when using areas to increase locality of reference.
</p>

<p>When you create an area, one region is created initially.  When you try
to allocate memory to hold an object in some area, the system tries to
find a region that has the right data representation type to hold this
object, and that has enough room for it to fit.  If there isn't any such
region, it makes a new one (or signals an error; see the <obj>:size</obj> option
to <obj>make-area</obj>, below).  The size of the new region is an attribute of
the area (controllable by the <obj>:region-size</obj> option to <obj>make-area</obj>).
If regions are too large, memory may get taken up by a region and never used.
If regions are too small, the system may run out of regions because regions,
like areas, are defined by internal tables that have a fixed size (set at
cold-load generation time).  Currently (as this manual is written) the limit
is 256 regions, of which about 105 already exist when you start.
(If you're wondering why the limit on regions isn't higher than the limit
on areas, as it clearly ought to be, it's just because both limits have
to be multiples of 256 for internal reasons, and 256 regions seem
to be enough.)
</p>
<a name="Area Functions and Variables"></a>

<section chapter-number="17" name="Area Functions and Variables" number="1" title="Area Functions and Variables"><definition>
<define key="default-cons-area-var" name="default-cons-area" type="var"></define>

<description>The value of this variable is the number of the area in which objects are created
by default.  It is initially the number of <obj>working-storage-area</obj>.
Giving <obj>nil</obj> where an area is required uses the value of <obj>default-cons-area</obj>.
Note that to put objects into an area other than <obj>working-storage-area</obj>
you can either bind this variable or use functions such as
<obj>cons-in-area</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-con" key="cons-in-area-fun" title="Function cons-in-area" type="fun"></ref>) which take the area as an explicit argument.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="background-cons-area-var" name="background-cons-area" type="var"></define>

<description>The value of this variable is the number of a non-temporary area in
which objects created as incidental side effects by system functions
should be created.  This area is used whenever an object is created that
should never be in a temporary area, even if <arg>default-cons-area</arg> is a
temporary area.

By default, this area is <obj>working-storage-area</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="make-area-fun" name="make-area" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;key</standard> name size region-size representation gc read-only pdl room</args>
</define>

<description>Creates a new area, whose name and attributes are specified by the keywords.
You must specify a symbol as a name; the symbol is <obj>setq</obj>'ed to
the area-number of the new area, and that number is also returned,
so that you can use <obj>make-area</obj> as the initialization of a <obj>defvar</obj>.

Here are the meanings of the keywords:

<table><tbody><tr><td><arg>name</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":name make-area"></index-entry>
A symbol that will be the name of the area.  This item is required.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>size</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":size make-area"></index-entry>
The maximum allowed size of the area, in words.  Defaults to infinite.
(Actually, the default is the largest positive fixnum; but the area is
not limited to that size!)
If the number of words allocated to the area reaches this size, attempting
to cons an object in the area will signal an error.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>region-size</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":region-size make-area"></index-entry>
The approximate size, in words, for regions within this area.  The
default is the area size if a <obj>:size</obj> argument was given, otherwise it is a
suitable medium size.  Note that if you specify <obj>:size</obj> and not
<obj>:region-size</obj>, the area will have exactly one region.  When making an
area that will grow very big, it is desirable to make the region size
larger than the default region size to avoid creating very many regions
and possibly overflowing the system's fixed-size region tables.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>representation</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":representation make-area"></index-entry>
The type of object to be contained in the area's initial region.
The argument to this keyword can be <obj>:list</obj>, <obj>:structure</obj>, or a numeric code.
<obj>:structure</obj> is the default.  If you are only going to cons lists in your
area, you should specify <obj>:list</obj> so you don't get a useless structure region.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>gc</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":gc make-area"></index-entry>
The type of garbage-collection to be employed.  The choices are
<obj>:dynamic</obj> (which is the default), <obj>:static</obj>, and <obj>:temporary</obj>.
<obj>:static</obj> means that the area will not be copied by the garbage
collector, and nothing in the area or pointed to by the area will ever
be reclaimed, unless a garbage collection of this area is manually
requested.  <obj>:temporary</obj> is like <obj>:static</obj>, but in addition you are
allowed to use <obj>si:reset-temporary-area</obj> on this area.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>read-only</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":read-only make-area"></index-entry>
With an argument of <obj>t</obj>, causes the area to be made read-only.  Defaults
to <obj>nil</obj>.  If an area is read-only, then any attempt to change anything
in it (altering a data object in the area or creating a new object in the
area) will signal an error unless <obj>sys:%inhibit-read-only</obj>
(see <ref definition-in-file="fd-sub" key="sys:%inhibit-read-only-var" title="Variable sys:%inhibit-read-only" type="var"></ref>) is bound to a non-<obj>nil</obj> value.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>pdl</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":pdl make-area"></index-entry>
With an argument of <obj>t</obj>, makes the area suitable for storing
regular-pdls of stack-groups.  This is a special attribute due to the
pdl-buffer hardware.  Defaults to <obj>nil</obj>.  Areas for which this is <obj>nil</obj>
may <arg>not</arg> be used to store regular-pdls.  Areas for which this is <obj>t</obj>
are relatively slow to access; all references to pages in the area will
take page faults to check whether the referenced location is really in
the pdl-buffer.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>room</arg></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":room make-area"></index-entry>
With an argument of <obj>t</obj>, adds this area to the list of areas that are
displayed by default by the <obj>room</obj> function (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-hac" key="room-fun" title="Function room" type="fun"></ref>).
</td></tr></tbody></table>

<lisp><exdent amount="96"><caption>Example: </caption>(make-area :name 'foo-area
           :gc :dynamic
           :representation :list)
</exdent></lisp></description></definition><definition><define key="describe-area-fun" name="describe-area" type="fun"><args>area</args>
</define>

<description><arg>area</arg> may be the name or the number of an area.  Various
attributes of the area are printed.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="area-list-var" name="area-list" type="var"></define>

<description>The value of <obj>area-list</obj> is a list of the names of all existing areas.
This list shares storage with the internal area name table, so you should
not change it.
</description></definition><definition><define key="%area-number-fun" name="%area-number" type="fun"><args>pointer</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the number of the area to which <arg>pointer</arg> points, or <obj>nil</obj> if
it does not point within any known area.  The data-type of <arg>pointer</arg>
is ignored.
</description></definition><definition><define key="%region-number-fun" name="%region-number" type="fun"><args>pointer</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the number of the region to which <arg>pointer</arg> points, or <obj>nil</obj> if
it does not point within any known region.  The data-type of <arg>pointer</arg>
is ignored.  (This information is generally not very interesting to users;
it is important only inside the system.)
</description></definition><definition><define key="area-name-fun" name="area-name" type="fun"><args>number</args>
</define>

<description>Given an area number, returns the name.  This ``function'' is actually an array.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:reset-temporary-area-fun" name="si:reset-temporary-area" type="fun"><args>area-number</args>
</define>

<description>This very dangerous operation marks all the storage in area
<arg>area-number</arg> as free and available for re-use.  Any data in the area
is lost and pointers to it become meaningless.  In principle,
this operation should only be used if you are sure there are no pointers
into the area.

If the area was not defined as temporary, this function gets an
error.
</description></definition><nopara></nopara>
<p>See also <obj>cons-in-area</obj> (<ref definition-in-file="fd-con" key="cons-in-area-fun" title="Function cons-in-area" type="fun"></ref>), <obj>list-in-area</obj> (<ref definition-in-file="fd-con" key="list-in-area-fun" title="Function list-in-area" type="fun"></ref>),
and <obj>room</obj> (<ref definition-in-file="fd-hac" key="room-fun" title="Function room" type="fun"></ref>).
</p>
</section><a name="Interesting Areas"></a>


<section chapter-number="17" name="Interesting Areas" number="2" title="Interesting Areas"><p>This section lists the names of some of the areas and tells what they are for.
Only the ones of the most interest to a user are listed; there are many others.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="working-storage-area-var" name="working-storage-area" type="const"></define>

<description>This is the normal value of <obj>default-cons-area</obj>.
Most working data are consed in this area.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="permanent-storage-area-var" name="permanent-storage-area" type="const"></define>

<description>This area is to be used for permanent data, which will (almost) never become
garbage.  Unlike <obj>working-storage-area</obj>, the contents of this area
are not continually copied by the garbage collector; it is a static area.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="sys:extra-pdl-area-var" name="sys:extra-pdl-area" type="const"></define>

<description>The `number consing area' in which floating point numbers, ratios and bignums
are normally created.  If a pointer to a number in this area is stored anywhere
outside the machine registers and current stack, a copy of the number is
made in <obj>working-storage-area</obj> and a pointer to the copy is stored instead.
When <obj>sys:extra-pdl-area</obj> gets full, the all numbers pointed to by the
registers and current stack are copied, and then nothing in the area can be
in use any more, so it is marked as empty.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="sys:p-n-string-var" name="sys:p-n-string" type="const"></define>

<description>Print-names of symbols are stored in this area.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="sys:nr-sym-var" name="sys:nr-sym" type="const"></define>

<description>Contains most of the symbols in the Lisp world, except <obj>t</obj> and <obj>nil</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="sys:resident-symbol-area-var" name="sys:resident-symbol-area" type="const"></define>

<description>Contains the symbols <obj>t</obj> and <obj>nil</obj>.  <obj>nil</obj> is known to be at address zero.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="sys:pkg-area-var" name="sys:pkg-area" type="const"></define>

<description>This area contains packages, principally the hash tables with which <obj>intern</obj>
keeps track of symbols.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="macro-compiled-program-var" name="macro-compiled-program" type="const"></define>

<description>Compiled functions (FEFs) are put here by the compiler and by <obj>fasload</obj>.
So are the constants that they refer to.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="sys:property-list-area-var" name="sys:property-list-area" type="const"></define>

<description>This area holds the property lists of symbols.
</description></definition></section><a name="compiler"></a>

<section chapter-number="17" name="compiler" number="3" title="Errors Pertaining to Areas"><definition><define key="sys:area-overflow-condition" name="sys:area-overflow" type="condition"><args>(<obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This is signaled on an attempt to make an area bigger than its declared maximum size.

The condition instance supports the operations <obj>:area-name</obj> and
<obj>:area-maximum-size</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="sys:region-table-overflow-condition" name="sys:region-table-overflow" type="condition"><args>(<obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This is signaled if you run out of regions.
</description></definition><definition><define key="sys:virtual-memory-overflow-condition" name="sys:virtual-memory-overflow" type="condition"><args>(<obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This is signaled if all of virtual memory is part of some region and an
attempt is made to allocate a new region.  There may be free space left
in some regions in other areas, but there is no way to apply it to the
area in which storage is to be allocated. 
</description></definition><definition><define key="sys:cons-in-fixed-area-condition" name="sys:cons-in-fixed-area" type="condition"><args>(<obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This is signaled if an attempt is made add a second region to a fixed
area.  The fixed areas are certain areas, created at system
initialization, that are only allowed a single region, because their
contents must be contiguous in virtual memory.
</description></definition></section></chapter>
</document-part>