<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><a name="code-chapter"></a>
<chapter name="code-chapter" number="32" title="How to Read Assembly Language"><index-entry index="concepts" title="compiled code"></index-entry>

<p>Sometimes it is useful to study the machine language code produced by
the Lisp Machine's compiler, usually in order to analyze an error, or
sometimes to check for a suspected compiler problem.  This chapter
explains how the Lisp Machine's instruction set works and how to
understand what code written in that instruction set is doing.
Fortunately, the translation between Lisp and this instruction set is
very simple; after you get the hang of it, you can move back and forth
between the two representations without much trouble.  The following
text does not assume any special knowledge about the Lisp Machine,
although it sometimes assumes some general computer science background
knowledge.
</p>
<a name="Introduction"></a>


<section chapter-number="32" name="Introduction" number="1" title="Introduction"><p>Nobody looks at machine language code by trying to interpret octal
numbers by hand.  Instead, there is a program called the Disassembler
which converts the numeric representation of the instruction set into a
more readable textual representation.  It is called the Disassembler
because it does the opposite of what an Assembler would do; however,
there isn't actually any assembler that accepts this input format, since
there is never any need to manually write assembly language for the Lisp
Machine.
</p>

<p>The simplest way to invoke the Disassembler is with the Lisp function
<obj>disassemble</obj>.  Here is a simple example.  Suppose we type:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x)
  (assq 'key (get x 'propname)))

(compile 'foo)

(disassemble 'foo)
</lisp>
<p>This defines the function <obj>foo</obj>, compiles it, and invokes the Disassembler
to print out the textual representation of the result of the compilation.
Here is what it looks like:
</p>

<lisp>22 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;'KEY
23 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
24 MOVE D-PDL FEF|7           ;'PROPNAME
25 (MISC) GET D-PDL
26 (MISC) ASSQ D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>The Disassembler is also used by the Error Handler and the Inspector.
When you see stuff like the above while using one of these programs, it
is disassembled code, in the same format as the <obj>disassemble</obj> function
uses.  Inspecting a compiled code object shows the disassembled code.
</p>

<p>Now, what does this mean?  Before we get started, there is just a little
bit of jargon to learn.
</p>

<p>The acronym PDL stands for Push Down List, and means the same thing as
Stack: a last-in first-out memory.  The terms PDL and stack will be used
interchangeably.  The Lisp Machine's architecture is rather typical of
``stack machines''; there is a stack that most instructions deal with, and
it is used to hold values being computed, arguments, and local
variables, as well as flow-of-control information.  An important use of
the stack is to pass arguments to instructions, though not all
instructions take their arguments from the stack.
</p>

<p>The acronym `FEF' stands for Function Entry Frame.  A FEF is a compiled
code object produced by the compiler.  After the <obj>defun</obj> form above
was evaluated, the function cell of the symbol <obj>foo</obj> contained a
lambda expression.  Then we compiled the function <obj>foo</obj>, and the
contents of the function cell were replaced by a FEF.  The
printed representation of the FEF for <obj>foo</obj> looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>#&lt;DTP-FEF-POINTER 11464337 FOO&gt;
</lisp>
<p>The FEF has three parts (this is a simplified explanation): a header
with various fixed-format fields; a part holding constants and invisible
pointers, and the main body, holding the machine language instructions.
The first part of the FEF, the header, is not very interesting and is
not documented here (you can look at it with <obj>describe</obj> but it won't
be easy to understand).  The second part of the FEF holds various
constants referred to by the function; for example, our function <obj>foo</obj>
references two constants (the symbols <obj>key</obj> and <obj>propname</obj>), and so
(pointers to) those symbols are stored in the FEF.  This part of the FEF
also holds invisible pointers to the value cells of all symbols that the
function uses as variables, and invisible pointers to the function cells
of all symbols that the function calls as functions.  The third part of
the FEF holds the machine language code itself.
</p>

<p>Now we can read the disassembled code.  The first instruction looked
like this:
</p>

<lisp>22 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;'KEY
</lisp>
<p>This instruction has several parts.  The <obj>22</obj> is the address of this
instruction.  The Disassembler prints out the address of each
instruction before it prints out the instruction, so that you can
interpret branching instructions when you see them (we haven't seen one
of these yet, but we will later).  The <obj>MOVE</obj> is an opcode: this is a
<obj>MOVE</obj> instruction, which moves a datum from one place to another.  The
<obj>D-PDL</obj> is a destination specification.  The <obj>D</obj> stands for
`Destination', and so <obj>D-PDL</obj> means `Destination-PDL': the destination
of the datum being moved is the PDL.  This means that the
result will be pushed onto the PDL, rather than just moved to the top;
this instruction is pushing a datum onto the stack.  The next field of
the instruction is <obj>FEF|6</obj>.  This is an <arg>address</arg>, and it specifies
where the datum is coming from.  The vertical bar serves to separate the
two parts of the address.  The part before the vertical bar can be
thought of as a <arg>base register</arg>, and the part after the bar can be
thought of as being an offset from that register.  <obj>FEF</obj> as a base
register means the address of the FEF that we are disassembling, and so
this address means the location six words into the FEF.  So what this
instruction does is to take the datum located six words into the FEF,
and push it onto the PDL.  The instruction is followed by a comment
field, which looks like <obj>;'KEY</obj>.  This is not a comment that any person
wrote; the disassembler produces these to explain what is going on.  The
semicolon just serves to start the comment, the way semicolons in Lisp
code do.  In this case, the body of the comment, <obj>'KEY</obj>, is telling us
that the address field (<obj>FEF|6</obj>) is addressing a constant (that is what
the single-quote in <obj>'KEY</obj> means), and that the printed representation
of that constant is <obj>KEY</obj>.  With the help of this comment we finally
get the real story about what this instruction is doing: it is pushing
(a pointer to) the symbol <obj>key</obj> onto the stack.
</p>

<p>The next instruction looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>23 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
</lisp>
<p>This is a lot like the previous instruction; the only difference is that
a different ``base register'' is being used in the address.  The <obj>ARG</obj>
base register is used for addressing your arguments: <obj>ARG|0</obj> means
that the datum being addressed is the zeroth argument.  Again, the
comment field explains what that means: the value of X (which was the
zeroth argument) is being pushed onto the stack.
</p>

<p>The third instruction is just like the first and second ones; it pushes
the symbol <obj>propname</obj> onto the stack.
</p>

<p>The fourth instruction is something new:
</p>

<lisp>25 (MISC) GET D-PDL
</lisp>
<p>The first thing we see here is <obj>(MISC)</obj>.  This means that this is one of
the so-called <arg>miscellaneous</arg> instructions.  There are quite a few of
these instructions.  With some exceptions, each miscellaneous
instruction corresponds to a Lisp function and has the same name as that
Lisp function.  If a Lisp function has a corresponding miscellaneous
instruction, then that function is hand-coded in Lisp Machine microcode.
</p>

<p>Miscellaneous instructions only have a destination field; they don't
have any address field.  The inputs to the instruction come from the
stack: the top <arg>n</arg> elements on the stack are used as inputs to the
instruction and popped off the stack, where <arg>n</arg> is the number of arguments
taken by the function.  The result of the function is stored wherever
the destination field says.  In our case, the function being executed is
<obj>get</obj>, a Lisp function of two arguments.  The top two values will be
popped off the stack and used as the arguments to <obj>get</obj> (the value
pushed first is the first argument, the value pushed second is the
second argument, and so on).  The result of the call to <obj>get</obj> will be
sent to the destination <obj>D-PDL</obj>; that is, it will be pushed onto the stack.
(In case you were wondering about how we handle optional arguments and
multiple-value returns, the answer is very simple: functions that use
either of those features cannot be miscellaneous instructions!  If you
are curious as to what functions are hand-microcoded and thus available
as miscellaneous instructions, you can look at the <obj>defmic</obj> forms in the
file <obj>SYS: SYS; DEFMIC LISP</obj>.)
</p>

<p>The fifth and last instruction is similar to the fourth:
</p>

<lisp>26 (MISC) ASSQ D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>What is new here is the new value of the destination field.  This one is
called <obj>D-RETURN</obj>, and it can be used anywhere destination
fields in general can be used (like in <obj>MOVE</obj> instructions).  Sending
something to ``Destination-Return'' means that this value should be the
returned value of the function, and that we should return from this
function.  This is a bit unusual in instruction sets; rather than having
a ``return'' instruction, we have a destination that, when stored into,
returns from the function.  What this instruction does, then, is to
invoke the Lisp function <obj>assq</obj> on the top two elements of the stack
and return the result of <obj>assq</obj> as the result of this function.
</p>

<p>Now, let's look at the program as a whole and see what it did:
</p>

<lisp>22 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;'KEY
23 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
24 MOVE D-PDL FEF|7           ;'PROPNAME
25 (MISC) GET D-PDL
26 (MISC) ASSQ D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>First it pushes the symbol <obj>key</obj>.  Then it pushes the value of <obj>x</obj>.
Then it pushes the symbol <obj>propname</obj>.  Then it invokes <obj>get</obj>, which
pops the value of <obj>x</obj> and the symbol <obj>propname</obj> off the stack and
uses them as arguments, thus doing the equivalent of evaluating the form
<obj>(get x 'propname)</obj>.  The result is left on the stack; the stack now
contains the result of the <obj>get</obj> on top, and the symbol <obj>key</obj>
underneath that.  Next, it invokes <obj>assq</obj> on these two values, thus
doing the equivalent of evaluating <obj>(assq 'key (get x 'propname))</obj>.
Finally, it returns the value produced by <obj>assq</obj>.  Now, the original
Lisp program we compiled was:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x)
  (assq 'key (get x 'propname)))
</lisp>
<p>We can see that the code produced by the compiler is correct: it will do
the same thing as the function we defined will do.
</p>

<p>In summary, we have seen two kinds of instructions so far: the <obj>MOVE</obj>
instruction, which takes a destination and an address, and two of the
large set of miscellaneous instructions, which take only a destination,
and implicitly get their inputs from the stack.  We have seen two
destinations (<obj>D-PDL</obj> and <obj>D-RETURN</obj>), and two forms of address (<obj>FEF</obj>
addressing and <obj>ARG</obj> addressing).
</p>
</section><a name="A More Advanced Example"></a>


<section chapter-number="32" name="A More Advanced Example" number="2" title="A More Advanced Example"><p>Here is a more complex Lisp function, demonstrating local variables,
function calling, conditional branching, and some other new
instructions.
</p>

<lisp>(defun bar (y)
  (let ((z (car y)))
    (cond ((atom z)
           (setq z (cdr y))
           (foo y))
          (t
           nil))))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>20 CAR D-PDL ARG|0            ;Y
21 POP LOCAL|0                ;Z
22 BR-NOT-ATOM 27
23 CDR D-PDL ARG|0            ;Y
24 POP LOCAL|0                ;Z
25 CALL D-RETURN FEF|6        ;#'FOO
26 MOVE D-LAST ARG|0          ;Y
27 MOVE D-RETURN 'NIL
</lisp>
<p>The first instruction here is a <obj>CAR</obj> instruction.  It has the same
format as <obj>MOVE</obj>: there is a destination and an address.  The <obj>CAR</obj>
instruction reads the datum addressed by the address, takes the car of
it, and stores the result into the destination.   In our example, the
first instruction addresses the zeroth argument, and so it computes
<obj>(car y)</obj>; then it pushes the result onto the stack.
</p>

<p>The next instruction is something new: the <obj>POP</obj> instruction.  It has an
address field, but it uses it as a destination rather than as a source.
The <obj>POP</obj> instruction pops the top value off the stack, and stores that
value into the address specified by the address field.  In our example,
the value on the top of the stack is popped off and stored into address
<obj>LOCAL|0</obj>.  This is a new form of address; it means the zeroth local
variable.  The ordering of the local variables is chosen by the
compiler, and so it is not fully predictable, although it tends to be
by order of appearance in the code; fortunately you never have to look
at these numbers, because the comment field explains what is going on.
In this case, the variable being addressed is <obj>z</obj>.  So this instruction
pops the top value on the stack into the variable <obj>z</obj>.  The first two
instructions work together to take the car of <obj>y</obj> and store it into
<obj>z</obj>, which is indeed the first thing the function <obj>bar</obj> ought to do.
(If you have two local variables with the same name, then the comment
field won't tell you which of the two you're talking about; you'll have
to figure that out yourself.  You can tell two local variables with
the same name apart by looking at the number in the address.)
</p>

<p>The next instruction is a familiar <obj>MOVE</obj> instruction, but it uses a
new destination: <obj>D-IGNORE</obj>.  This means that the datum being
addressed isn't moved anywhere.  If so, then why bother doing this
instruction?  The reason is that there is conceptually a set of
<arg>indicator</arg> bits, as are found in most modern computers such as the
68000, the Vax, as well as in obsolete computers such as the 370.  Every
instruction that moves or produces a datum sets the indicator bits from
that datum so that following instructions can test them.  So the reason
that the <obj>MOVE</obj> instruction is being done is so that someone can test
the indicators set up by the value that was moved, namely the value of
<obj>z</obj>.
</p>

<p>All instructions except the branch instructions set the indicator bits
from the result produced and/or stored by that instruction.
</p>

<p>The next instruction is a conditional branch; it changes the flow of
control, based on the values in the indicator bits, which in this case
reflect the value popped by the <obj>POP</obj> instruction 21.  The branch
instruction is <obj>BR-NOT-ATOM 27</obj>, which means ``Branch, if the quantity
was not an atom, to location 27; otherwise proceed with execution''.  If
<obj>z</obj> was an atom, the Lisp Machine branches to location 27, and
execution proceeds there.  (As you can see by skipping ahead, location
27 just contains a <obj>MOVE</obj> instruction, which will cause the function
to return <obj>nil</obj>.)
</p>

<p>If <obj>z</obj> is not an atom, the program keeps going, and the <obj>CDR</obj>
instruction is next.  This is just like the <obj>CAR</obj> instruction except
that it takes the cdr; this instruction pushes the value of <obj>(cdr y)</obj>
onto the stack.  The next one pops that value off into the variable <obj>z</obj>.
</p>

<p>There are just two more instructions left.  These two instructions are
our first example of how function calling is compiled.  It is the
only really tricky thing in the instruction set.  Here is how it works
in our example:
</p>

<lisp>25 CALL D-RETURN FEF|6        ;#'FOO
26 MOVE D-LAST ARG|0          ;Y
</lisp>
<p>The form being compiled here is <obj>(foo y)</obj>.  This means we are applying
the function which is in the function cell of the symbol <obj>foo</obj>, and
passing it one argument, the value of <obj>y</obj>.  The way function calling
works is in the following three steps.  First of all, there is a <obj>CALL</obj>
instruction that specifies the function object being applied to
arguments.  This creates a new stack frame on the stack, and stores the
function object there.  Secondly, all the arguments being passed except
the last one are pushed onto the stack.  Thirdly and lastly, the last
argument is sent to a special destination, called <obj>D-LAST</obj>,
meaning ``this is the last argument''.  Storing to this destination is
what actually calls the function, <arg>not</arg> the <obj>CALL</obj> instruction itself.
</p>

<p>There are two things you might wonder about this.  First of all, when
the function returns, what happens to the returned value?  Well, this is
what we use the destination field of the <obj>CALL</obj> instruction for.  The
destination of the <obj>CALL</obj> is not stored into at the time the <obj>CALL</obj>
instruction is executed; instead, it is saved on the stack along with
the function operation (in the stack frame created by the <obj>CALL</obj>
instruction).  Then, when the function actually returns, its result is
stored into that destination.
</p>

<p>The other question is what happens when there isn't any last argument;
that is, when there is a call with no arguments at all?  This is handled
by a special instruction called <obj>CALL0</obj>.  The address of <obj>CALL0</obj>
addresses the function object to be called; the call takes place
immediately and the result is stored into the destination specified by
the destination field of the <obj>CALL0</obj> instruction.
</p>

<p>So, let's look at the two-instruction sequence above.  The first
instruction is a <obj>CALL</obj>; the function object it specifies is at <obj>FEF|6</obj>,
which the comment tells us is the contents of the function cell of <obj>foo</obj>
(the FEF contains an invisible pointer to that function cell).  The
destination field of the <obj>CALL</obj> is <obj>D-RETURN</obj>, but we aren't going to
store into it yet; we will save it away in the stack frame and use it
later.  So the function doesn't return at this point, even though it
says <obj>D-RETURN</obj> in the instruction; this is the tricky part.
</p>

<p>Next we have to push all the arguments except the last one.  Well,
there's only one argument, so nothing needs to be done here.  Finally,
we move the last argument (that is, the only argument: the value of <obj>y</obj>)
to <obj>D-LAST</obj>, using the <obj>MOVE</obj> instruction.  Moving to <obj>D-LAST</obj> is what
actually invokes the function, so at this point the function <obj>foo</obj> is
invoked.  When it returns, its result is sent to the destination stored
in the stack frame: <obj>D-RETURN</obj>.  Therefore, the value returned by the
call to <obj>foo</obj> will be returned as the value of the function <obj>bar</obj>.  Sure
enough, this is what the original Lisp code says to do.
</p>

<p>When the compiler pushes arguments to a function call, it sometimes does
it by sending the values to a destination called <obj>D-NEXT</obj> (meaning the
``next'' argument).  This is exactly the same as <obj>D-PDL</obj> when producing
a compiled function.  The distinction is important when the compiler
output is passed to the microcompiler to generate microcode.
</p>

<p>Here is another example to illustrate function calling.  This Lisp
function calls one function on the results of another function.
</p>

<lisp>(defun a (x y)
  (b (c x y) y))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>22 CALL D-RETURN FEF|6        ;#'B
23 CALL D-PDL FEF|7           ;#'C
24 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
25 MOVE D-LAST ARG|1          ;Y
26 MOVE D-LAST ARG|1          ;Y
</lisp>
<p>The first instruction starts off the call to the function <obj>b</obj>.  The
destination field is saved for later: when this function returns, we
will return its result as <obj>a</obj>'s result.  Next, the call to <obj>c</obj> is
started.  Its destination field, too, is saved for later; when <obj>c</obj>
returns, its result should be pushed onto the stack, so that it will be
the next argument to <obj>b</obj>.  Next, the first and second arguments to
<obj>c</obj> are passed; the second one is sent to <obj>D-LAST</obj> and so the
function <obj>c</obj> is called.  Its result, as we said, will be pushed onto
the stack, and thus become the first argument to <obj>b</obj>.  Finally, the
second argument to <obj>b</obj> is passed, by storing in <obj>D-LAST</obj>; <obj>b</obj> gets
called, and its result is sent to <obj>D-RETURN</obj> and is returned from
<obj>a</obj>.
</p>
</section><a name="The Rest of the Instructions"></a>


<section chapter-number="32" name="The Rest of the Instructions" number="3" title="The Rest of the Instructions"><p>Now that we've gotten some of the feel for what is going on, I will
start enumerating the instructions in the instruction set.  The
instructions fall into four classes.  Class I instructions have both a
destination and an address.  Class II instructions have an address, but
no destination.  Class III instructions are the branch instructions,
which contain a branch address rather than a general base-and-offset
address.  Class IV instructions have a destination, but no address;
these are the miscellaneous instructions.
</p>

<p>We have already seen just about all the Class I instructions.  There are
nine of them in all: <obj>MOVE</obj>, <obj>CALL</obj>, <obj>CALL0</obj>, <obj>CAR</obj>, <obj>CDR</obj>, <obj>CAAR</obj>,
<obj>CADR</obj>, <obj>CDAR</obj>, and <obj>CDDR</obj>.  <obj>MOVE</obj> just moves a datum from an address
to a destination; the <obj>CxR</obj> and <obj>CxxR</obj> instructions are the same but
perform the function on the value before sending it to the destination;
<obj>CALL</obj> starts off a call to a function with some arguments; <obj>CALL0</obj>
performs a call to a function with no arguments.
</p>

<p>We've seen most of the possible forms of address.  So far we have seen
the <obj>FEF</obj>, <obj>ARG</obj>, and <obj>LOCAL</obj> base registers.  There are two other
kinds of addresses.  One uses a ``constant'' base register, which
addresses a set of standard constants: <obj>NIL</obj>, <obj>T</obj>, <obj>0</obj>, <obj>1</obj>, and
<obj>2</obj>.  The disassembler doesn't even bother to print out
<obj>CONSTANT|<arg>n</arg></obj>, since the number <arg>n</arg> would not be even slightly
interesting; it just prints out <obj>'NIL</obj> or <obj>'1</obj> or whatever.  The
other kind of address is a special one printed as <obj>PDL-POP</obj>, which
means that to read the value at this address, an object should be popped
off the top of the stack.
</p>

<p>There are more Class II instructions.  The only one we've
seen so far is <obj>POP</obj>, which pops a value off the stack and stores it
into the specified address.  Another, called <obj>MOVEM</obj>
(from the PDP-10 opcode name, meaning MOVE to Memory), stores the
top element of the stack into the specified address, but doesn't pop it
off the stack.
</p>

<p>Seven Class II instructions implement heavily-used
two-argument functions: <obj>+</obj>, <obj>-</obj>, <obj>*</obj>, <obj>/</obj>, <obj>LOGAND</obj>, <obj>LOGXOR</obj>, and
<obj>LOGIOR</obj>.  These instructions take the first argument from the top of
the stack (popping it off) and their second argument from the
specified address, and they push the result on the stack.  Thus the
stack level does not change due to these instructions.
Here is a small function that shows some of these new things:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x y)
  (setq x (logxor y (- x 2))))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>16 MOVE D-PDL ARG|1           ;Y
17 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
20 - '2
21 LOGXOR PDL-POP
22 MOVEM ARG|0                ;X
23 MOVE D-RETURN PDL-POP
</lisp>
<p>Instructions 20 and 21 use two of the new Class II instructions: the <obj>-</obj>
and <obj>LOGXOR</obj> instructions.  Instructions 21 and 23 use the <obj>PDL-POP</obj>
address type, and instruction 20 uses the ``constant'' base register to
get to a fixnum <obj>2</obj>.  Finally, instruction 22 uses the <obj>MOVEM</obj>
instruction; the compiler wants to use the top value of the stack to
store it into the value of <obj>x</obj>, but it doesn't want to pop it off the
stack because it has another use for it: to return it from the function.
</p>

<p>Another four Class II instructions implement some commonly used
predicates: <obj>=</obj>, <obj>&gt;</obj>, <obj>&lt;</obj>, and <obj>EQ</obj>.  The two arguments come from the
top of the stack and the specified address; the stack is popped, the
predicate is applied to the two objects, and the result is left in the
indicators so that a branch instruction can test it, and branch based
on the result of the comparison.  These instructions remove the top
item on the stack and don't put anything back, unlike the previous set,
which put their results back on the stack.
</p>

<p>Next, there are four Class II instructions to read, modify, and write a
quantity in ways that are common in Lisp code.  These instructions are
called <obj>SETE-CDR</obj>, <obj>SETE-CDDR</obj>, <obj>SETE-1+</obj>, and <obj>SETE-1-</obj>.  The <obj>SETE-</obj>
means to set the addressed value to the result of applying the specified
one-argument function to the present value.  For example, <obj>SETE-CDR</obj>
means to read the value addressed, apply <obj>cdr</obj> to it, and store the
result back in the specified address.  This is used when compiling
<obj>(setq x (cdr x))</obj>, which commonly occurs in loops; the other functions
are used frequently in loops, too.
</p>

<p>There are two instructions used to bind special variables.  The first is
<obj>BIND-NIL</obj>, which binds the cell addressed by the address field to
<obj>nil</obj>; the second is <obj>BIND-POP</obj>, which binds the cell to an object
popped off the stack rather than <obj>nil</obj>.  The latter instruction pops a
value off the stack; the former does not use the stack at all.
</p>

<p>There are two instructions to store common values into addressed cells.
<obj>SET-NIL</obj> stores <obj>nil</obj> into the cell specified by the address field;
<obj>SET-ZERO</obj> stores <obj>0</obj>.  Neither instruction uses the stack at all.
</p>

<p>Finally, the <obj>PUSH-E</obj> instruction creates a locative pointer to the cell
addressed by the specified address, and pushes it onto the stack.  This
is used in compiling <obj>(value-cell-location 'z)</obj> where <obj>z</obj> is an
argument or a local variable, rather than a symbol (special variable).
</p>

<p>Those are all of the Class II instructions.  Here is a contrived
example that uses some of the ones we haven't seen, just to show
you what they look like:
</p>

<lisp>(defun weird (x y)
  (cond ((= x y)
         (let ((*foo* nil) (*bar* 5))
           (declare (special *foo* *bar*))
           (setq x (cdr x)))
         nil)
        (t
         (setq x nil)
         (caar (variable-location y)))))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>24 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
25 = ARG|1                    ;Y
26 BR-NIL 35
27 BIND-NIL FEF|6             ;*FOO*
30 PUSH-NUMBER 5
31 BIND-POP FEF|7             ;*BAR*
32 SETE-CDR ARG|0             ;X
33 (MISC) UNBIND 2 bindings 
34 MOVE D-RETURN 'NIL
35 SET-NIL ARG|0              ;X
36 PUSH-E ARG|1               ;Y
37 CAAR D-RETURN PDL-POP
</lisp>
<p>Instruction 25 is an <obj>=</obj> instruction; it numerically compares the top of the
stack, <obj>x</obj>, with the addressed quantity, <obj>y</obj>.  The <obj>x</obj> is
popped off the stack, and the indicators are set to the result of the
equality test.  Instruction 26 checks the indicators, branching to 35 if
the result of the call to <obj>=</obj> was <obj>nil</obj>; that is, the machine will
branch to 35 if the two values were not equal.  Instruction 27 binds
<obj>*foo*</obj> to <obj>nil</obj>; instructions 30 and 31 bind <obj>*bar*</obj> to <obj>5</obj>.
Instruction 30 is a peculiar class IV instruction called <obj>PUSH-NUMBER</obj>
which pushes a constant integer on the stack.  The integer must be in
the range of zero to 511 in order for <obj>PUSH-NUMBER</obj> to be used.
Instruction 32 demonstrates the use of <obj>SETE-CDR</obj> to compile <obj>(setq x
(cdr x))</obj>, and instruction 35 demonstrates the use of <obj>SET-NIL</obj> to
compile <obj>(setq x nil)</obj>.  Instruction 36 demonstrates the use of
<obj>PUSH-E</obj> to compile <obj>(variable-location y)</obj>.
</p>

<p>The Class III instructions are for branching.  These have neither
addresses nor destinations of the usual sort.  Instead, they have
branch-addresses; they say where to branch, if the branch is going to
happen.  There are several instructions, differing in the conditions
under which they branch and whether they pop the stack.
Branch-addresses are stored internally as self-relative addresses, to
make Lisp Machine code relocatable, but the disassembler does the
addition for you and prints out FEF-relative addresses so that you can
easily see where the branch is going to.
</p>

<p>The branch instructions we have seen so far decide whether to branch on
the basis of the <obj>nil</obj>-indicator, that is, whether the last value dealt
with was <obj>nil</obj> or non-<obj>nil</obj>.  <obj>BR-NIL</obj> branches if it was <obj>nil</obj>, and
<obj>BR-NOT-NIL</obj> branches if it was not <obj>nil</obj>.  There are two more
instructions that test the result of the <obj>atom</obj> predicate on the last
value dealt with.  <obj>BR-ATOM</obj> branches if the value was an atom (that is,
if it was anything besides a cons). and <obj>BR-NOT-ATOM</obj> branches if the
value was not an atom (that is, if it was a cons).  The <obj>BR</obj> instruction
is an unconditional branch (it always branches).
</p>

<p>None of the above branching instructions deal with the stack.  There are
two more instructions called <obj>BR-NIL-POP</obj> and <obj>BR-NOT-NIL-POP</obj>, which
are the same as <obj>BR-NIL</obj> and <obj>BR-NOT-NIL</obj> except that if the branch is
not done, the top value on the stack is popped off the stack.  These are
used for compiling <obj>and</obj> and <obj>or</obj> special forms.
</p>

<p>Finally, there are the Class IV instructions, most of which are
miscellaneous hand-microcoded Lisp functions. The file <obj>SYS: SYS;
DEFMIC LISP</obj> has a list of all the miscellaneous instructions.  Most
correspond to Lisp functions, including the subprimitives, although some
of these functions are very low level internals that may not be
documented anywhere (don't be disappointed if you don't understand all
of them).  Please do not look at this file in hopes of finding obscure
functions that you think you can use to speed up your programs; in fact,
the compiler automatically uses these things when it can, and directly
calling weird internal functions will only serve to make your code hard
to read, without making it any faster.  In fact, we don't guarantee that
calling undocumented functions will continue to work in the future.
</p>

<p>The <obj>DEFMIC</obj> file can be useful for determining if a given function is in
microcode, although the only definitive way to tell is to compile some
code that uses it and look at the results, since sometimes the compiler
converts a documented function with one name into an undocumented one
with another name.
</p>
</section><a name="Function Entry"></a>


<section chapter-number="32" name="Function Entry" number="4" title="Function Entry"><p>When a function is first entered in the Lisp Machine, interesting things
can happen because of the features that are invoked by use of the
various lambda-list keywords.  The microcode performs various services when
a function is entered, even before the first instruction of the function
is executed.  These services are called for by various fields of the
header portion of the FEF, including a list called the <arg>Argument
Descriptor List</arg>, or <arg>ADL</arg>.  We won't go into the detailed format of
any of this, as it is complex and the details are not too interesting.
Disassembling a function that makes use of the ADL prints a summary of
what the ADL says to do, before the beginning of the code.
</p>

<p>The function-entry services include the initialization of unsupplied
optional arguments and of <obj>&amp;AUX</obj> variables.  The ADL
has a little instruction set of its own, and if the form that computes
the initial value is something simple, such as a constant or a
variable, then the ADL can handle things itself.  However, if things get
too complicated, instructions are needed, and the compiler generates
some instructions at the front of the function to initialize the
unsupplied variables.  In this case, the ADL specifies several different
starting addresses for the function, depending on which optional arguments
have been supplied and which have been omitted.  If all the optional
arguments are supplied, then the ADL starts the function off after all
the instructions that would have initialized the optional arguments;
since the arguments were supplied, their values should not be set, and
so all these instructions are skipped over.  Here's an example:
</p>

<lisp>(defvar *y*)

(defun foo (&amp;optional (x (car *y*)) (z (* x 3)))
  (cons x z))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>Arg 0 (X) is optional, local,
  initialized by the code up to pc 32.
Arg 1 (Z) is optional, local,
  initialized by the code up to pc 35.

30 CAR D-PDL FEF|6            ;*Y*
31 POP ARG|0                  ;X
32 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
33 * '3
34 POP ARG|1                  ;Z
35 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
36 MOVE D-PDL ARG|1           ;Z
37 (MISC) CONS D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>If no arguments are supplied, the function will be started at
instruction 30; if only one argument is supplied, it will be started at
instruction 32; if both arguments are supplied, it will be started at
instruction 35.
</p>

<p>The thing to keep in mind here is that when there is initialization of
variables, you may see it as code at the beginning of the function, or
you may not, depending upon whether it is too complex for the ADL to handle.
This is true of <obj>&amp;aux</obj> variables as well as unsupplied <obj>&amp;optional</obj>
arguments.
</p>

<p>When there is a <obj>&amp;rest</obj> argument, it is passed to the function as the
zeroth local variable, rather than as any of the arguments.  This is not
really so confusing as it might seem, since a <obj>&amp;rest</obj> argument is not
an argument passed by the caller; rather it is a list of some of the
arguments, created by the function-entry microcode services.  In any case
the comment tells you what is going on.  In fact, one hardly ever
looks much at the address fields in disassembled code, since the
comment tells you the right thing anyway.  Here is a silly example of the
use of a <obj>&amp;rest</obj> argument:
</p>

<lisp>(defun prod (&amp;rest values)
  (apply #'* values))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>20 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;#'*
21 MOVE D-PDL LOCAL|0         ;VALUES
22 (MISC) APPLY D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>As can be seen, <obj>values</obj> is referred to as <obj>LOCAL|0</obj>.
</p>

<p>Another thing the microcode does at function entry is to bind the
values of any arguments or <obj>&amp;aux</obj> variables that are special.
Thus, you won't see any <obj>BIND</obj> instructions for binding them.
</p>
</section><a name="initialization"></a>


<section chapter-number="32" name="initialization" number="5" title="Special Class IV Instructions"><p>We said earlier that most of the Class IV instructions are miscellaneous
hand-microcoded Lisp functions.  However, a few of them are not Lisp
functions at all.  There are two instructions that are printed as
<obj>UNBIND 3 bindings</obj> or <obj>POP 7 values</obj>; the number can be
anything up to 16 (these numbers are printed in decimal).  These
instructions just do what they say, unbinding the last <arg>n</arg> values that
were bound or popping the top <arg>n</arg> values off the stack.
</p>

<p>Another Class IV instruction is <obj>PUSH-NUMBER</obj>.  It pushes a constant
integer, in the range zero to 511.  An example of it appeared on <ref definition-in-file="code" key="push-number-use" type="page"></ref>.
</p>

<p>The array referencing functions--<obj>aref</obj>, <obj>aset</obj>, and <obj>aloc</obj>--take
a variable number of arguments, but they are handled differently
depending on how many there are.  For one-, two-, and three-dimensional
arrays, these functions are turned into internal functions with names
<obj>ar-1</obj>, <obj>as-1</obj>, and <obj>ap-1</obj> (with the number of dimensions
substituted for <obj>1</obj>).  Again, there is no point in using these
functions yourself; it would only make your code harder to understand
but not any faster at all.  When there are more than three dimensions,
the functions <obj>aref</obj>, <obj>aset</obj> and <obj>aloc</obj> are called in the ordinary
manner.
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (y x i j &amp;aux v)
  (setq v (aref x i j))
  (setf (aref y i) v))
</lisp>
<lisp>16 MOVE D-PDL ARG|1           ;X
17 MOVE D-PDL ARG|2           ;I
20 MOVE D-PDL ARG|3           ;J
21 (MISC) AR-2 D-PDL
22 POP LOCAL|0                ;V
23 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;Y
24 MOVE D-PDL ARG|2           ;I
25 MOVE D-PDL LOCAL|0         ;V
26 (MISC) SET-AR-1 D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>Reference to one-dimensional arrays with constant subscripts
use special instructions which have the array index encoded instead
of an address.
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x)
  (+ (aref x 3) (array-leader x 2))
  (setf (aref x 5) t))
</lisp>
<lisp>FOO:
16 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
17 AR-1 (3) D-IGNORE
20 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
21 ARRAY-LEADER (2) D-IGNORE
22 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
23 MOVE D-PDL 'T
24 SET-AR-1 (5) D-RETURN
</lisp>
<p>The <obj>AR-1</obj> instruction is to be distinguished from the <obj>MISC AR-1</obj>
instruction.  <obj>AR-1</obj> pops an array off the stack and encodes the
subscript itself.  The 3 in <obj>(3)</obj> is the subscript.  <obj>ARRAY-LEADER</obj>
is similar but refers to an array leader slot.  <obj>SET-AR-1</obj> pops an
array and then pops a value to store into it at the specified slot.
<obj>SET-AR-1</obj> is analogous.  There also exist <obj>%INSTANCE-REF</obj> and
<obj>SET-%INSTANCE-REF</obj> instructions.
</p>

<p>When you call a function and expect to get more than one value back,
a slightly different kind of function calling is used.  Here is an example
that uses <obj>multiple-value</obj> to get two values back from a function call:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x)
  (let (y z)
    (multiple-value (y z)
      (bar 3))
    (+ x y z)))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>20 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;#'BAR
21 MOVE D-PDL '2
22 (MISC) %CALL-MULT-VALUE D-IGNORE
23 MOVE D-LAST '3
24 POP LOCAL|1                ;Z
25 POP LOCAL|0                ;Y
26 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
27 + LOCAL|0                  ;Y
30 + LOCAL|1                  ;Z
31 MOVE D-RETURN PDL-POP
</lisp>
<p>A <obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE</obj> instruction is used instead of a <obj>CALL</obj>
instruction.  The destination field of <obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE</obj> is unused and
will always be <obj>D-IGNORE</obj>.  <obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE</obj> takes two ``arguments'',
which it finds on the stack; it pops both of them.  The first one is the
function object to be applied; the second is the number of return values
that are expected.  The rest of the call proceeds as usual, but when the
call returns, the returned values are left on the stack.  The number of
objects left on the stack is always the same as the second ``argument'' to
<obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE</obj>.  In our example, the two values returned are left
on the stack, and they are immediately popped off into <obj>z</obj> and <obj>y</obj>.
There is also a <obj>%CALL0-MULT-VALUE</obj> instruction, for the same
reason <obj>CALL0</obj> exists.
</p>

<p>The <obj>multiple-value-bind</obj> form works similarly; here is an
example:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x)
  (multiple-value-bind (y *foo* z)
      (bar 3)
    (declare (special *foo*))
    (+ x y z)))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>22 MOVE D-PDL FEF|7           ;#'BAR
23 MOVE D-PDL '3
24 (MISC) %CALL-MULT-VALUE D-IGNORE
25 MOVE D-LAST '3
26 POP LOCAL|1                ;Z
27 BIND-POP FEF|6             ;*FOO*
30 POP LOCAL|0                ;Y
31 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;X
32 + LOCAL|0                  ;Y
33 + LOCAL|1                  ;Z
34 MOVE D-RETURN PDL-POP
</lisp>
<p>The <obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE</obj> instruction is still used, leaving the results
on the stack; these results are used to bind the variables.
</p>

<p>Calls done with <obj>multiple-value-list</obj> work with the <obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE-LIST</obj>
instruction.  It takes one ``argument'' on the stack: the function object
to apply.  When the function returns, the list of values is left on the
top of the stack.  Here is an example:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (x y)
  (multiple-value-list (bar -7 y x)))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>22 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;#'BAR
23 (MISC) %CALL-MULT-VALUE-LIST D-IGNORE
24 MOVE D-PDL FEF|7           ;'-7
25 MOVE D-PDL ARG|1           ;Y
26 MOVE D-LAST ARG|0          ;X
27 MOVE D-RETURN PDL-POP
</lisp>
<p>Returning of more than one value from a function is handled
by special miscellaneous instructions.  <obj>%RETURN-2</obj> and <obj>%RETURN-3</obj> are
used to return two or three values; these instructions take two
and three arguments, respectively, on the stack and return from the
current function just as storing to <obj>D-RETURN</obj> would.  If there are more
than three return values, they are all pushed, then the number
that there were is pushed, and then the <obj>%RETURN-N</obj> instruction is
executed.  None of these instructions use their destination field.
Note: the <obj>return-list</obj> function is just an ordinary miscellaneous
instruction; it takes the list of values to return as an argument on the
stack and returns those values from the current function.
</p>

<p>The function <obj>apply</obj> is compiled using a special instruction called
<obj>%SPREAD</obj> to iterate over the elements of its last argument, which
should be a list.  <obj>%SPREAD</obj> takes one argument (on the stack), which
is a list of values to be passed as arguments (pushed on the stack).  If
the destination of <obj>%SPREAD</obj> is <obj>D-PDL</obj> (or <obj>D-NEXT</obj>), then the
values are just pushed; if it is <obj>D-LAST</obj>, then after the values are
pushed, the function is invoked.  <obj>apply</obj> with more than two arguments
will always compile using a <obj>%SPREAD</obj> whose destination is <obj>D-LAST</obj>.
Here is an example:
</p>

<lisp>(defun foo (a b &amp;rest c)
  (apply #'format t a c)
  b)
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>FOO:
20 CALL D-IGNORE FEF|6        ;#'FORMAT
21 MOVE D-PDL 'T
22 MOVE D-PDL ARG|0           ;A
23 MOVE D-PDL LOCAL|0         ;C
24 (MISC) %SPREAD D-LAST
25 MOVE D-RETURN ARG|1        ;B
</lisp>
<p>Note that in instruction 23, the address <obj>LOCAL|0</obj> is used to
access the <obj>&amp;rest</obj> argument.
</p>

<p>The <obj>catch</obj> special form is also handled specially by the compiler.
Here is a simple example of <obj>catch</obj>:
</p>

<lisp>(defun a ()
  (catch 'foo (bar)))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>24 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;'30
25 (MISC) %CATCH-OPEN D-RETURN
26 MOVE D-PDL FEF|7           ;'FOO
27 CALL0 D-RETURN FEF|8       ;#'BAR
</lisp>
<p>The <obj>%CATCH-OPEN</obj> instruction is like the <obj>CALL</obj> instruction; it
starts a call to the <obj>catch</obj> function.  It takes one ``argument'' on
the stack, which is the location in the program that should be branched
to if this <obj>catch</obj> is <obj>throw</obj>n to.  In addition to saving that
program location, the instruction saves the state of the stack and
of special-variable binding so that they can be restored in the event
of a <obj>throw</obj>.  So instructions 24 and 25
start a <obj>catch</obj> block, and the rest of the function computes the
two arguments of the <obj>catch</obj>.  Note, however, that <obj>catch</obj>
is not actually called.  The last form inside the <obj>catch</obj>, in this case
<obj>(bar)</obj>, is compiled so as to return its values directly out of the
function <obj>a</obj>.  The only way that the inactive stack frame for <obj>catch</obj>
matters is if a <obj>throw</obj> is done during the execution of <obj>bar</obj>.
This searches for a pending call to <obj>catch</obj> and returns from that frame.
In this case, since the <obj>%CATCH-OPEN</obj> instruction specifies
<obj>D-RETURN</obj>, the values thrown are returned from <obj>a</obj>.
</p>

<p>You may have wondered why instruction 24 is there at all.
If the destination of a <obj>catch</obj> is not <obj>D-RETURN</obj>, it is necessary
for <obj>throw</obj> to resume execution of the function containing the <obj>catch</obj>.
Then it is necessary to specify what instruction to resume at.
For example:
</p>

<lisp>(defun a ()
  (catch 'foo (bar))
  (print t))
</lisp>
<p>The disassembled code looks like this:
</p>

<lisp>26 MOVE D-PDL FEF|6           ;'32
27 (MISC) %CATCH-OPEN D-IGNORE
30 MOVE D-PDL FEF|7           ;'(BAR)
31 MOVE D-LAST FEF|8          ;'FOO
32 CALL D-RETURN FEF|9        ;#'PRINT
33 MOVE D-LAST 'T
</lisp>
<p>The instruction 26 pushes 32, which is the number of instruction
at which execution should resume if there is a <obj>throw</obj>.
</p>

<p>To allow compilation of <obj>(multiple-value (...) (catch ...))</obj>, there
is a special instruction called <obj>%CATCH-OPEN-MULT-VALUE</obj>, which is a
cross between <obj>%CATCH-OPEN</obj> and <obj>%CALL-MULT-VALUE</obj>.
</p>
</section></chapter>
</document-part>