<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><a name="format"></a>


<section chapter-number="23" name="format" number="4" title="Formatted Output"><index-entry index="concepts" title="formatted output"></index-entry>

<p>There are two ways of doing general formatted output.  One is the
function <obj>format</obj>.  The other is the <obj>output</obj> subsystem.
<obj>format</obj> uses a control string written in a special format
specifier language to control the output format.
<obj>format:output</obj> provides Lisp functions to do
output in particular formats.  
</p>

<p>For simple tasks in which only the most basic format specifiers are
needed, <obj>format</obj> is easy to use and has the advantage of brevity.
For more complicated tasks, the format specifier language becomes
obscure and hard to read.  Then <obj>format:output</obj> becomes advantageous
because it works with ordinary Lisp control constructs.
</p>


<subsection name="NIL" title="The Format Function"><definition><define key="format-fun" name="format" type="fun"><args>destination control-string <standard>&amp;rest</standard> args</args>
</define>

<description>Produces formatted output.
<obj>format</obj> outputs the characters of <arg>control-string</arg>, except
that a tilde (`<obj>~</obj>') introduces a directive.  The character after
the tilde, possibly preceded by prefix parameters and modifiers, specifies
what kind of formatting is desired.  Most directives use one or more
elements of <arg>args</arg> to create their output; the typical directive
puts the next element of <arg>args</arg> into the output, formatted in
some special way.

        The output is sent to <arg>destination</arg>.  If <arg>destination</arg> is
<obj>nil</obj>, a string is created which contains the output; this string is
returned as the value of the call to <obj>format</obj>.  In all other cases
<obj>format</obj> returns no interesting value (generally it returns <obj>nil</obj>).
If <arg>destination</arg> is a stream, the output is sent to it.  If
<arg>destination</arg> is <obj>t</obj>, the output is sent to <obj>*standard-output*</obj>.  If
<arg>destination</arg> is a string with an array-leader, such as would be
acceptable to <obj>string-nconc</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-str" key="string-nconc-fun" title="Function string-nconc" type="fun"></ref>), the output is
added to the end of that string.
</description></definition>
<p indent="1">        A directive consists of a tilde, optional prefix parameters
separated by commas, optional colon (`<obj>:</obj>') and atsign (`<obj>@</obj>') modifiers,
and a single character indicating what kind of directive this is.
The alphabetic case of the character is ignored.
The prefix parameters are generally decimal numbers.
Examples of control strings:
</p>

<lisp>&quot;~S&quot;        ; <standard>This is an S directive with no parameters.</standard>
&quot;~3,4:@s&quot;   ; <standard>This is an S directive with two parameters, 3 and 4,</standard>
            ; <standard>   and both the colon and atsign flags.</standard>
&quot;~,4S&quot;      ; <standard>The first prefix parameter is omitted and takes</standard>
            ; <standard>   on its default value, while the second is 4.</standard>
</lisp>
<p><obj>format</obj> includes some extremely complicated and specialized
features.  It is not necessary to understand all or even most of its
features to use <obj>format</obj> efficiently.  The beginner should
skip over anything in the following documentation that is not
immediately useful or clear.  The more sophisticated features are
there for the convenience of programs with complicated formatting
requirements.
</p>

<p indent="1">        Sometimes a prefix parameter is used to specify a character,
for instance the padding character in a right- or left-justifying
operation.  In this case a single quote (&quot;<obj> ' </obj>&quot;) followed by the
desired character may be used as a prefix parameter, so that you don't
have to know the decimal numeric values of characters in the character
set.  For example, you can use <obj>&quot;~5,'0d&quot;</obj> instead of <obj>&quot;~5,48d&quot;</obj> to
print a decimal number in five columns with leading zeros.
</p>

<p>In place of a prefix parameter to a directive, you can put the letter
<obj>V</obj>, which takes an argument from <arg>args</arg> as a parameter to the
directive.  Normally this should be a number but it doesn't really have
to be.  This feature allows variable column-widths and the like.  Also,
you can use the character <obj>#</obj> in place of a parameter; it represents the
number of arguments remaining to be processed.
</p>
<need amount="1800"></need>
<p>Here are some relatively simple examples to give you the general
flavor of how <obj>format</obj> is used.

<lisp>(format nil &quot;foo&quot;) =&gt; &quot;foo&quot;
(setq x 5)
(format nil &quot;The answer is ~D.&quot; x) =&gt; &quot;The answer is 5.&quot;
(format nil &quot;The answer is ~3D.&quot; x) =&gt; &quot;The answer is   5.&quot;
</lisp>
<lisp>(setq y &quot;elephant&quot;)
(format nil &quot;Look at the ~A!&quot; y) =&gt; &quot;Look at the elephant!&quot;
(format nil &quot;The character ~:@C is strange.&quot; #\meta-beta)
      =&gt; &quot;The character Meta-β (Greek-b) is strange.&quot;
</lisp>
<lisp>(setq n 3)
(format nil &quot;~D item~:P found.&quot; n) =&gt; &quot;3 items found.&quot;
(format nil &quot;~R dog~:[s are~; is~] here.&quot; n (= n 1))
      =&gt; &quot;three dogs are here.&quot;
(format nil &quot;~R dog~:*~[~1; is~:;s are~] here.&quot; n)
      =&gt; &quot;three dogs are here.&quot;
(format nil &quot;Here ~[~1;is~:;are~] ~:*~R pupp~:@P.&quot; n)
      =&gt; &quot;Here are three puppies.&quot;
</lisp></p>

<p>The directives will now be described.
<arg>arg</arg> will be used to refer to the next argument from <arg>args</arg>.

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>~A</obj></td><td><arg>arg</arg>, any Lisp object, is printed without escaping (as by <obj>princ</obj>).
<obj>~:A</obj> prints <obj>( )</obj> if <arg>arg</arg> is <obj>nil</obj>; this is useful when printing
something that is always supposed to be a list.
<obj>~<arg>n</arg>A</obj> inserts spaces on the right, if necessary, to make the
column width at least <arg>n</arg>.  The <obj>@</obj> modifier causes the spaces
to be inserted on the left rather than the right.
<obj>~<arg>mincol,colinc,minpad,padchar</arg>A</obj> is the full form of <obj>~A</obj>,
which allows elaborate control of the padding.
The string is padded on the right with at least <arg>minpad</arg> copies
of <arg>padchar</arg>; padding characters are then inserted <arg>colinc</arg> characters
at a time until the total width is at least <arg>mincol</arg>.
The defaults are 0 for <arg>mincol</arg> and <arg>minpad</arg>, 1 for <arg>colinc</arg>,
and space for <arg>padchar</arg>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~S</obj></td><td>This is just like <obj>~A</obj>, but <arg>arg</arg> is printed <arg>with</arg> escaping
(as by <obj>prin1</obj> rather than <obj>princ</obj>).

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~D</obj></td><td><arg>arg</arg>, a number, is printed in base ten.
Unlike <obj>print</obj>, <obj>~D</obj> never puts a decimal point after the number.
<obj>~<arg>n</arg>D</obj> uses a column width of <arg>n</arg>; spaces are inserted on
the left if the number requires less than <arg>n</arg> columns for its digits
and sign.  If the number doesn't fit in <arg>n</arg> columns, additional columns
are used as needed. <obj>~<arg>n</arg>,<arg>m</arg>D</obj> uses <arg>m</arg> as the pad character
instead of space.  If <arg>arg</arg> is not a number, it is printed
in <obj>~A</obj> format and decimal base.
The <obj>@</obj> modifier causes the number's sign to be printed always; the default
is only to print it if the number is negative.
The <obj>:</obj> modifier causes commas to be printed between groups of three digits;
the third prefix parameter may be used to change the character used as the comma.
Thus the most general form of <obj>~D</obj> is
<obj>~<arg>mincol</arg>,<arg>padchar</arg>,<arg>commachar</arg>D</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~O</obj></td><td>This is just like <obj>~D</obj> but prints in octal instead of decimal.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~X</obj></td><td>This is just like <obj>~D</obj> but prints in hex instead of decimal.
Note that <obj>~X</obj> used to have a different meaning: print one or more spaces.
Uses of <obj>~X</obj> intended to have this meaning should be replaced with <obj>~@T</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~B</obj></td><td>This is just like <obj>~D</obj> but prints in binary instead of decimal.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~<arg>w</arg>,<arg>d</arg>,<arg>k</arg>,<arg>ovfl</arg>,<arg>pad</arg> F</obj></td><td><arg>arg</arg> is printed in nonexponential floating point format, as in
`10.5'.  (If the magnitude of <arg>arg</arg> is very large or very small, it is
printed in exponential notation.)  The parameters control the details of
the formatting.

<table><tbody><tr><td><arg>w</arg></td><td>is the total field width desired.  If omitted, this is not constrained.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>d</arg></td><td>is the number of digits to print after the decimal point.
If <arg>d</arg> is omitted, it is chosen to do a good job based on <arg>w</arg>
(if specified) and the value of <arg>arg</arg>.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>k</arg></td><td>is a scale factor.  <arg>arg</arg> is multiplied by <obj>(exp 10. <arg>k</arg>)</obj>
before it is printed.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>ovfl</arg></td><td>is a character to use for overflow.  If <arg>arg</arg>
is too big to print and fit the constraints of field width, etc.,
and <arg>ovfl</arg> is specified then the whole field is filled with <arg>ovfl</arg>.
If <arg>ovfl</arg> is not specified, <arg>arg</arg> is printed using extra width as needed.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>pad</arg></td><td>is a character to use for padding on the left, when the field
width is specified and not that many characters are really needed.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<nopara></nopara>If the <obj>@</obj> modifier is used, a sign is printed even if <arg>arg</arg> is positive.

Rational numbers are converted to floats and then printed.
Anything else is printed with <obj>~<arg>w</arg>D</obj> format.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~<arg>w</arg>,<arg>d</arg>,<arg>e</arg>,<arg>k</arg>,<arg>ovfl</arg>,<arg>pad</arg>,<arg>expt</arg> E</obj></td><td><arg>arg</arg> is printed in exponential notation, as in `.105e+2'.  The parameters control
the details of the formatting.

<table><tbody><tr><td><arg>w</arg></td><td>is the total field width desired.  If omitted, this is not constrained.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>d <standard>and</standard> k</arg></td><td>control the number of mantissa digits and their arrangement around the
decimal point.  <arg>d</arg>+1 digits are printed.  If <arg>k</arg> is positive, all
of them are significant digits, and the decimal point is printed after
the first <arg>k</arg> of them.  If <arg>k</arg> is zero or negative, the first
|<arg>k</arg>|+1 of the <arg>d</arg>+1 digits are leading zeros, and the decimal
point follows the first zero.  (This zero can be omitted if necessary
to fit the number in <arg>w</arg> characters.)  So the number of significant
figures is less than <arg>d</arg> if <arg>k</arg> is negative.

The exponent printed always compensates for any powers of ten
introduced according to <arg>k</arg>, so 10.5 might be printed as
<obj>0.105e+2</obj> or as <obj>1050.0e-2</obj>.

If <arg>d</arg> is omitted, the system chooses enough significant figures
to represent the float accurately.  If <arg>k</arg> is omitted, the default is one.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>e</arg></td><td>is the number of digits to use for the exponent.  If it is not specified,
however many digits are needed are used.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>ovfl</arg></td><td>is the overflow character.
If the exponent doesn't fit in <arg>e</arg> digits or the entire number
does not fit in <arg>w</arg> characters, then if <arg>ovfl</arg> is specified,
the field of <arg>w</arg> characters is filled with <arg>ovfl</arg>.  Otherwise
more characters are used as needed.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>pad</arg></td><td>is a character to use for padding on the left, when the field
width is specified and not that many characters are really needed.
</td></tr><tr><td><arg>expt</arg></td><td>is a character to use to separate the mantissa from the exponent.
The default is <obj>e</obj> or <obj>s</obj> or <obj>f</obj>, whichever would be used
in printing the number normally.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<nopara></nopara>If the <obj>@</obj> modifier is used, a sign is printed even if <arg>arg</arg> is positive.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~<arg>w</arg>,<arg>d</arg>,<arg>e</arg>,<arg>k</arg>,<arg>ovfl</arg>,<arg>pad</arg>,<arg>expt</arg> G</obj></td><td>Prints a floating point number <arg>arg</arg> in either <obj>~F</obj> or <obj>~E</obj>
format.  Fixed format is used if the absolute value of <arg>arg</arg> is less
than <obj>(expt 10. <arg>d</arg>)</obj>, and exponential format otherwise.  (If <arg>d</arg>
is not specified, it defaults based on the value of <arg>arg</arg>.)  If fixed
format is used, <arg>e</arg>+2 blanks are printed at the end (where the
exponent and its separator and sign would go, in exponential format).
These count against the width <arg>w</arg> if that is specified.  Four blanks
are used if <arg>e</arg> is omitted.  The diminished width available, <arg>d</arg>,
<arg>ovfl</arg> and <arg>pad</arg> are used as specified.  The scale factor used in
fixed format is always zero, not <arg>k</arg>.

If exponential format needs to be used, all the parameters are passed to
the <obj>~E</obj> directive to print the number.

Rational numbers are converted to floats and then printed.
Anything else is printed with <obj>~<arg>w</arg>D</obj> format.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~$</obj></td><td><obj>~<arg>rdig</arg>,<arg>ldig</arg>,<arg>field</arg>,<arg>padchar</arg>$</obj> prints
<arg>arg</arg>, a float, with exactly <arg>rdig</arg> digits after the decimal
point.  The default for <arg>rdig</arg> is 2, which is convenient for
printing amounts of money.  At least <arg>ldig</arg> digits are printed
preceding the decimal point; leading zeros are printed if there would
be fewer than <arg>ldig</arg>.  The default for <arg>ldig</arg> is 1.  The number is
right justified in a field <arg>field</arg>
columns long, padded out with <arg>padchar</arg>.  The colon modifier means
that the sign character is to be at the beginning of the field, before
the padding, rather than just to the left of the number.  The atsign modifier
says that the sign character should always be output.

If <arg>arg</arg> is not a number, or is unreasonably large, it is printed
in <obj>~<arg>field</arg>,,,<arg>padchar</arg>@A</obj> format; i.e. it is <obj>princ</obj>'ed
right-justified in the specified field width.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~C</obj></td><td><obj>(character <arg>arg</arg>)</obj> is put in the output.  <arg>arg</arg> is treated as a
keyboard character (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-str" key="%%kbd" type="page"></ref>), thus it may contain extra
control-bits.  These are printed first by representing them with
abbreviated prefixes: `<obj>C-</obj>' for <obj>Control</obj>, `<obj>M-</obj>' for <obj>Meta</obj>, `<obj>H-</obj>' for <obj>Hyper</obj>,
and `<obj>S-</obj>' for <obj>Super</obj>.

With the colon flag (<obj>~:C</obj>), the names of the control bits are spelled out
(e.g. `<obj>Control-Meta-F</obj>') and non-printing characters
are represented by their names (e.g. `<obj>Return</obj>') rather than being output
as themselves.  The printing characters Space and Altmode are also represented
as their names, but all others are printed directly.

With both colon and atsign (<obj>~:@C</obj>), the colon-only format is printed, and then
if the character requires the <obj>Top</obj> or <obj>Greek</obj> (<obj>Front</obj>) shift key(s) to type it,
this fact is mentioned (e.g. `<obj>∀ (Top-U)</obj>').  This is the format
used for telling the user about a key he is expected to type, for instance
in prompt messages.

For all three of these formats, if the character is a mouse character, it
is printed as <obj>Mouse-</obj>, the name of the button, `<example>-</example>', and the number
of clicks.

With just an atsign (<obj>~@C</obj>), the character is printed in such a way that
the Lisp reader can understand it, using `<obj>#\</obj>' or `<obj>#/</obj>', depending
on the escaping character of <obj>*readtable*</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="rdprt" key="escape-characters" type="page"></ref>).

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~%</obj></td><td>Outputs a carriage return.  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>%</obj> outputs <arg>n</arg> carriage returns.
No argument is used.  Simply putting a carriage return in the control string
would work, but <obj>~%</obj> is usually used because it makes the control string
look nicer in the Lisp source program.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~&amp;</obj></td><td>The <obj>:fresh-line</obj> operation is performed on the output stream.
Unless the stream knows that it is already at the front of a line,
this outputs a carriage return.  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>&amp;</obj> does a <obj>:fresh-line</obj> operation
and then outputs <arg>n</arg>-1 carriage returns.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~|</obj></td><td>Outputs a page separator character (<obj>#\page</obj>).  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>|</obj> does this
<arg>n</arg> times.  With a <obj>:</obj> modifier, if the output stream supports the
<obj>:clear-screen</obj> operation this directive clears the screen, otherwise
it outputs page separator character(s) as if no <obj>:</obj> modifier were
present.  <obj>|</obj> is vertical bar, not capital I.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~~</obj></td><td>Outputs a tilde.  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>~</obj> outputs <arg>n</arg> tildes.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~ &lt;CR&gt;</obj></td><td>Tilde immediately followed by a carriage return ignores the carriage return
and any whitespace at the beginning of the next line.  With a <obj>:</obj>, the whitespace
is left in place.  With an <obj>@</obj>, the carriage return is left in place.
This directive is typically used when a format control string is too long
to fit nicely into one line of the program.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~*</obj></td><td><arg>arg</arg> is ignored.  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>*</obj> ignores the next <arg>n</arg> arguments.
<obj>~:*</obj> ``ignores backwards''; that is, it backs up in the list of
arguments so that the argument last processed will be processed again.
<obj>~<arg>n</arg>:*</obj> backs up <arg>n</arg> arguments.  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>@*</obj> is absolute;
it moves to argument <arg>n</arg> (<arg>n</arg> = 0 specifies the first argument).

When within a <obj>~{</obj> construct (see below), the ignoring (in either
direction) is relative to the list of arguments being processed by the
iteration.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~P</obj></td><td>If <arg>arg</arg> is not <obj>1</obj>, a lower-case `s' is printed.  (`<obj>P</obj>' is for `plural'.)
<obj>~:P</obj> does the same thing, after doing a <obj>~:*</obj>; that is, it prints
a lower-case s if the <arg>last</arg> argument was not 1.  <obj>~@P</obj> prints `y'
if the argument is 1, or `ies' if it is not.  <obj>~:@P</obj> does the same thing,
but backs up first.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~T</obj></td><td>Spaces over to a given column.  <obj>~<arg>n</arg>,<arg>m</arg>T</obj> outputs
sufficient spaces to move the cursor to column <arg>n</arg>.  If the cursor
is already past column <arg>n</arg>, it outputs spaces to move it to
column <arg>n</arg>+<arg>mk</arg>, for the smallest integer value <arg>k</arg> possible.
<arg>n</arg> and <arg>m</arg> default to <obj>1</obj>.  Without the colon flag, <arg>n</arg> and
<arg>m</arg> are in units of characters; with it, they are in units of pixels.

Note: this operation works properly <arg>only</arg> on streams that support
the <obj>:read-cursorpos</obj> and <obj>:increment-cursorpos</obj> stream operations
(see <ref definition-in-file="stream" key="read-cursorpos" type="page"></ref>).  On other streams, any <obj>~T</obj> operation
simply outputs two spaces.  When <obj>format</obj> is creating
a string, <obj>~T</obj> works by assuming that the first character in the string
is at the left margin.

<obj>~@T</obj> simply outputs a space.
<obj>~<arg>rel</arg> T</obj> simply outputs <arg>rel</arg> spaces.
<obj>~<arg>rel</arg>, <arg>period</arg> T</obj> outputs <arg>rel</arg> spaces and then
additional spaces until it reaches a column which is a multiple
of <arg>period</arg>.  If the output stream does not support <obj>:read-cursorpos</obj>
then it simply outputs <arg>rel</arg> spaces.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~R</obj></td><td><obj>~R</obj> prints <arg>arg</arg> as a cardinal English number, e.g. four.
<obj>~:R</obj> prints <arg>arg</arg> as an ordinal number, e.g. fourth.
<obj>~@R</obj> prints <arg>arg</arg> as a Roman numeral, e.g. <obj>IV</obj>.
<obj>~:@R</obj> prints <arg>arg</arg> as an old Roman numeral, e.g. <obj>IIII</obj>.

<obj>~<arg>n</arg>R</obj> prints <arg>arg</arg> in radix <arg>n</arg>.
The flags and any remaining parameters are used as for the <obj>~D</obj> directive.
Indeed, <obj>~D</obj> is the same as <obj>~10R</obj>.  The full form here is therefore
<obj>~<arg>radix</arg>,<arg>mincol</arg>,<arg>padchar</arg>,<arg>commachar</arg>R</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~?</obj></td><td>Uses up two arguments, and processes the first one as a format control string
using the second one's elements as arguments.  Thus,

<lisp>(format nil &quot;~? ~D&quot; &quot;~O ~O&quot; '(4 20.) 9)
</lisp>returns <obj>&quot;4 24 9&quot;</obj>.

<obj>~@?</obj> processes the following argument as a format control string,
using all the remaining arguments.  Any arguments it does not use
are left to be processed by the format directives following the <obj>~@?</obj>
in the original control string.

<lisp>(format nil &quot;~@? ~D&quot; &quot;~O ~O&quot; 4 20. 9)
</lisp>likewise returns <obj>&quot;4 24 9&quot;</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~→<arg>str</arg>~←</obj></td><td>Performs the formatting specified by <arg>str</arg>, with indentation on
any new lines.  Each time a <obj>Return</obj> is printed during the processing of <arg>str</arg>,
it is followed by indentation sufficient to line up underneath the place
where the cursor was at the beginning of <arg>str</arg>.  For example,

<lisp>(format t &quot;Foo: ~8T~~A~&quot; <arg>string</arg>)
</lisp>prints <arg>string</arg> with each line starting at column 8.  If <arg>string</arg>
is <obj>(string-append &quot;This is&quot; #\return &quot;the string&quot;)</obj> then the output is

<lisp>Foo:    This is
        the string
</lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~(<arg>str</arg>~)</obj></td><td>Performs output with case conversion.
The formatting specified by <arg>str</arg> is done, with all the letters in the
resulting output being converted to upper or lower case according to
the modifiers given to the <obj>~(</obj> command:

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>~(  <standard>without modifiers</standard></obj></td><td>Converts all the letters to lower case.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~:(</obj></td><td>Converts the first letter of each word to upper case and the rest to lower case.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~@(</obj></td><td>Converts the first letter of the first word to upper case, and all other letters
to lower case.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~:@(</obj></td><td>Converts all the letters to upper case.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~1(</obj></td><td>Converts the first letter of the first word to upper case
and does not change anything else.  If you arrange to generate
all output in lower case except for letters that should be
upper case regardless of context, you can use this directive
when the output appears at the beginning of a sentence.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<lisp><exdent amount="96"><caption>Example: </caption>&quot;~(FoO BaR~) ~:(FoO BaR~) ~@(FoO BaR~) ~:@(FoO BaR~)
~1(at the White Hart~)&quot;
</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>produces </caption>foo bar Foo Bar Foo bar FOO BAR
At the White Hart
</exdent></lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~[<arg>str0</arg>~;<arg>str1</arg>~;<arg>...</arg>~;<arg>strn</arg>~]</obj></td><td>This is a set of alternative control strings.  The alternatives
(called <arg>clauses</arg>)
are separated by <obj>~;</obj> and the construct is terminated by <obj>~]</obj>.
For example,

<lisp>&quot;~[Siamese ~;Manx ~;Persian ~;Tortoise-Shell ~
   ~;Tiger ~;Yu-Shiang ~]kitty&quot;
</lisp>
<index-entry index="concepts" title="kitty, yu-shiang"></index-entry>
The <arg>arg</arg>th
alternative is selected; <obj>0</obj> selects the first.
If a prefix parameter is given (i.e. <obj>~<arg>n</arg>[</obj>),
then the parameter is used instead of an argument
(this is useful only if the parameter is `<obj>#</obj>').
If <arg>arg</arg> is out of range no alternative is selected.
After the selected alternative has been processed, the control string
continues after the <obj>~]</obj>.

<obj>~[<arg>str0</arg>~;<arg>str1</arg>~;<arg>...</arg>~;<arg>strn</arg>~:;<arg>default</arg>~]</obj> has a default case.
If the <arg>last</arg> <obj>~;</obj> used to separate clauses
is instead <obj>~:;</obj>, then the last clause is an ``else'' clause,
which is performed if no other clause is selected.
For example,

<lisp>&quot;~[Siamese ~;Manx ~;Persian ~;Tiger ~
   ~;Yu-Shiang ~:;Bad ~] kitty&quot;
</lisp>
<obj>~[~<arg>tag00</arg>,<arg>tag01</arg>,<arg>...</arg>;<arg>str0</arg>~<arg>tag10</arg>,<arg>tag11</arg>,<arg>...</arg>;<arg>str1...</arg>~]</obj>
allows the clauses to have explicit tags.  The parameters to each <obj>~;</obj>
are numeric tags for the clause which follows it.  That clause is processed
which has a tag matching the argument.  If <obj>~<arg>a1</arg>,<arg>a2</arg>,<arg>b1</arg>,<arg>b2</arg>,<arg>...</arg>:;</obj> (note the colon)
is used, then the following clause is tagged not by single values but
by ranges of values <arg>a1</arg> through <arg>a2</arg> (inclusive), <arg>b1</arg> through <arg>b2</arg>, etc.
<obj>~:;</obj> with no parameters may be used at the end to denote a default clause.
For example,

<lisp>&quot;~[~'+,'-,'*,'//;operator ~'A,'Z,'a,'z:;letter ~
   ~'0,'9:;digit ~:;other ~]&quot;
</lisp>
<obj>~:[<arg>false</arg>~;<arg>true</arg>~]</obj> selects the <arg>false</arg> control string
if <arg>arg</arg> is <obj>nil</obj>, and selects the <arg>true</arg> control string otherwise.

<obj>~@[<arg>true</arg>~]</obj> tests the argument.  If it is not <obj>nil</obj>,
then the argument is not used up, but is the next one to be processed,
and the one clause is processed.
If it is <obj>nil</obj>, then the argument is used up, and the clause is not processed.  For example,

<lisp>(setq *print-level* nil *print-length* 5)
(format nil
        &quot;~@[ *PRINT-LEVEL*=~D~]~@[ *PRINT-LENGTH*=~D~]&quot;
        prinlevel prinlength)
   =&gt;  &quot; *PRINT-LENGTH*=5&quot;
</lisp>
The combination of <obj>~[</obj> and <obj>#</obj> is useful, for
example, for dealing with English conventions for printing lists:

<lisp>(setq foo &quot;Items:~#[ none~; ~S~; ~S and ~
           ~S~:;~@{~#[~1; and~] ~S~^,~}~].&quot;)
(format nil foo)
        =&gt;  &quot;Items: none.&quot;
(format nil foo 'foo)
        =&gt;  &quot;Items: FOO.&quot;
(format nil foo 'foo 'bar)
        =&gt;  &quot;Items: FOO and BAR.&quot;
(format nil foo 'foo 'bar 'baz)
        =&gt;  &quot;Items: FOO, BAR, and BAZ.&quot;
(format nil foo 'foo 'bar 'baz 'quux)
        =&gt;  &quot;Items: FOO, BAR, BAZ, and QUUX.&quot;
</lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~;</obj></td><td>Separates clauses in <obj>~[</obj> and <obj>~&lt;</obj> constructions.  It is undefined elsewhere.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~]</obj></td><td>Terminates a <obj>~[</obj>.  It is undefined elsewhere.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj></td><td>This is an iteration construct.  The argument should be a list,
which is used as a set of arguments as if for a recursive call to <obj>format</obj>.
The string <arg>str</arg> is used repeatedly as the control string.
Each iteration can absorb as many elements of the list as it likes;
if <arg>str</arg> uses up two arguments by itself, then two elements of the
list get used up each time around the loop.
If before any iteration step the list is empty, then the iteration is terminated.
Also, if a prefix parameter <arg>n</arg> is given, then there can be at most <arg>n</arg>
repetitions of processing of <arg>str</arg>.  Here are some simple examples:

<lisp>(format nil &quot;Here it is:~{ ~S~}.&quot; '(a b c))
     =&gt; &quot;Here it is: A B C.&quot;
(format nil &quot;Pairs of things:~{ &lt;~S,~S&gt;~}.&quot; '(a 1 b 2 c 3))
     =&gt; &quot;Pairs of things: &lt;A,1&gt; &lt;B,2&gt; &lt;C,3&gt;.&quot;
</lisp>
Using <obj>~^</obj> as well, to terminate <arg>str</arg> if no arguments remain,
we can print a list with commas between the elements:

<lisp>(format nil &quot;Elements: ~{~S~^, ~}.&quot; '(a b c))
     =&gt; &quot;Elements: A, B, C.&quot;
</lisp>
<obj>~:{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj> is similar, but the argument should be a list of sublists.
At each repetition step one sublist is used as the set of arguments for
processing <arg>str</arg>; on the next repetition a new sublist is used, whether
or not all of the last sublist had been processed.  Example:

<lisp>(format nil &quot;Pairs of things:~:{ &lt;~S,~S&gt;~}.&quot;
            '((a 1) (b 2) (c 3)))
     =&gt; &quot;Pairs of things: &lt;A,1&gt; &lt;B,2&gt; &lt;C,3&gt;.&quot;
</lisp>
<obj>~@{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj> is similar to <obj>~{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj>, but instead of
using one argument which is a list, all the remaining arguments
are used as the list of arguments for the iteration.  Example:

<lisp>(format nil &quot;Pairs of things:~@{ &lt;~S,~S&gt;~}.&quot;
            'a 1 'b 2 'c 3)
     =&gt; &quot;Pairs of things: &lt;A,1&gt; &lt;B,2&gt; &lt;C,3&gt;.&quot;
</lisp>
<obj>~:@{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj> combines the features of <obj>~:{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj> and <obj>~@{<arg>str</arg>~}</obj>.
All the remaining arguments
are used, and each one must be a list.
On each iteration the next argument is used as a list of arguments to <arg>str</arg>.
Example:

<lisp>(format nil &quot;Pairs of things:~:@{ &lt;~S,~S&gt;~}.&quot;
            '(a 1) '(b 2) '(c 3))
     =&gt; &quot;Pairs of things: &lt;A,1&gt; &lt;B,2&gt; &lt;C,3&gt;.&quot;
</lisp>
Terminating the repetition construct with <obj>~:}</obj> instead of <obj>~}</obj>
forces <arg>str</arg> to be processed at least once even if the initial
list of arguments is null (however, it does not override an explicit
prefix parameter of zero).

If <arg>str</arg> is empty, then an argument is used as <arg>str</arg>.  It must be a string,
and precedes any arguments processed by the iteration.  As an example,
the following are equivalent:

<lisp>(apply #'format stream string args)
(format stream &quot;~1{~:}&quot; string args)
</lisp>This uses <obj>string</obj> as a formatting string.  The <obj>~1{</obj> says it must
be processed at most once, and the <obj>~:}</obj> says it must be processed at least once.
Therefore it is processed exactly once, using <obj>args</obj> as the arguments.

As another example, the <obj>format</obj> function itself uses <obj>format-error</obj>
(a routine internal to the <obj>format</obj> package) to signal
error messages, which in turn uses <obj>ferror</obj>, which uses <obj>format</obj> recursively.  
Now <obj>format-error</obj> takes a string and arguments, just like <obj>format</obj>,
but also prints some additional information: if the control string in <obj>ctl-string</obj>
actually is a string (it might be a list--see below), then it prints the string
and a little arrow showing where in the processing of the control string the
error occurred.  The variable <obj>ctl-index</obj> points one character after the place of
the error.

<lisp>(defun format-error (string &amp;rest args)
  (if (stringp ctl-string)
      (ferror nil &quot;~1{~:}~%~VT↓~%~3@T/&quot;~A/&quot;~%&quot;
              string args (+ ctl-index 3) ctl-string)
    (ferror nil &quot;~1{~:}&quot; string args)))
</lisp>This first processes the given string and arguments using <obj>~1{~:}</obj>, then
tabs a variable amount for printing the down-arrow, then prints the control
string between double-quotes.  The effect is something like this:

<lisp>(format t &quot;The item is a ~[Foo~;Bar~;Loser~].&quot; 'quux)
&gt;&gt;ERROR: The argument to the FORMAT &quot;~[&quot; command 
         must be a number
                   ↓
   &quot;The item is a ~[Foo~;Bar~;Loser~].&quot;
...
</lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~}</obj></td><td>Terminates a <obj>~{</obj>.  It is undefined elsewhere.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~&lt;</obj></td><td><obj>~<arg>mincol</arg>,<arg>colinc</arg>,<arg>minpad</arg>,<arg>padchar</arg>&lt;<arg>text</arg>~&gt;</obj>
justifies <arg>text</arg> within a field at least <arg>mincol</arg> wide.  <arg>text</arg>
may be divided up into segments with <obj>~;</obj>--the
spacing is evenly divided between the text segments.
With no modifiers, the leftmost text segment is left justified in the
field, and the rightmost text segment right justified;  if there is
only one, as a special case, it is right justified.
The <obj>:</obj> modifier causes
spacing to be introduced before the first text segment;  the <obj>@</obj>
modifier causes spacing to be added after the last.
<arg>Minpad</arg>, default <obj>0</obj>, is the minimum number of <arg>padchar</arg>
(default space) padding characters to be output between each segment.
If the total width needed to satisfy these constraints is greater
than <arg>mincol</arg>, then <arg>mincol</arg> is adjusted upwards in
<arg>colinc</arg> increments.  <arg>colinc</arg> defaults to <obj>1</obj>.  <arg>mincol</arg> defaults to <obj>0</obj>.
For example,

<lisp>(format nil &quot;~10&lt;foo~;bar~&gt;&quot;)          =&gt;  &quot;foo    bar&quot;
(format nil &quot;~10:&lt;foo~;bar~&gt;&quot;)         =&gt;  &quot;  foo  bar&quot;
(format nil &quot;~10:@&lt;foo~;bar~&gt;&quot;)        =&gt;  &quot;  foo bar &quot;
(format nil &quot;~10&lt;foobar~&gt;&quot;)            =&gt;  &quot;    foobar&quot;
(format nil &quot;~10:&lt;foobar~&gt;&quot;)           =&gt;  &quot;    foobar&quot;
(format nil &quot;~10@&lt;foobar~&gt;&quot;)           =&gt;  &quot;foobar    &quot;
(format nil &quot;~10:@&lt;foobar~&gt;&quot;)          =&gt;  &quot;  foobar  &quot;
(format nil &quot;$~10,,,'*&lt;~3f~&gt;&quot; 2.5902)  =&gt;  &quot;$******2.59&quot;
</lisp>
Note that <arg>text</arg> may include format directives.  The last example
illustrates how the <obj>~&lt;</obj> directive can be combined with the <obj>~f</obj>
directive to provide more advanced control over the formatting of
numbers.

Here are some examples of the use of <obj>~^</obj> within a <obj>~&lt;</obj> construct.
<obj>~^</obj> is explained in detail below, however the general idea is that
it eliminates the segment in which it appears and all following segments
if there are no more arguments.

<lisp>(format nil &quot;~15&lt;~S~;~^~S~;~^~S~&gt;&quot; 'foo)
        =&gt;  &quot;            FOO&quot;
(format nil &quot;~15&lt;~S~;~^~S~;~^~S~&gt;&quot; 'foo 'bar)
        =&gt;  &quot;FOO         BAR&quot;
(format nil &quot;~15&lt;~S~;~^~S~;~^~S~&gt;&quot; 'foo 'bar 'baz)
        =&gt;  &quot;FOO   BAR   BAZ&quot;
</lisp>
The idea is that if a segment contains a <obj>~^</obj>, and <obj>format</obj> runs out
of arguments, it just stops there instead of getting an error, and it as
well as the rest of the segments are ignored.

If the first clause of a <obj>~&lt;</obj> is terminated with <obj>~:;</obj> instead of <obj>~;</obj>,
then it is used in a special way.  All of the clauses are processed
(subject to <obj>~^</obj>, of course), but the first one is omitted in
performing the spacing and padding.  When the padded result has been
determined, then if it will fit on the current line of output, it is output,
and the text for the first clause is discarded.  If, however, the padded text
will not fit on the current line, then the
text segment for the first clause is output before the padded text.  The first clause ought
to contain a carriage return (<obj>~%</obj>).  The first clause is
always processed, and so any arguments it refers to will be used;
the decision is whether to use the resulting segment of text, not whether to
process the first clause.  If the <obj>~:;</obj> has a prefix parameter <arg>n</arg>, then
the padded text must fit on the current line with <arg>n</arg> character positions to spare
to avoid outputting the first clause's text.
For example, the control string

<lisp>&quot;~%;; ~{~&lt;~%;; ~1:; ~S~&gt;~^,~}.~%&quot;
</lisp>can be used to print a list of items separated by commas, without
breaking items over line boundaries, and beginning each line with
`<obj>;; </obj>'.  The prefix parameter <obj>1</obj> in <obj>~1:;</obj> accounts for the width of the
comma which will follow the justified item if it is not the last
element in the list, or the period if it is.  If <obj>~:;</obj> has a second
prefix parameter, then it is used as the width of the line,
thus overriding the natural line width of the output stream.  To make
the preceding example use a line width of 50, one would write

<lisp>&quot;~%;; ~{~&lt;~%;; ~1,50:; ~S~&gt;~^,~}.~%&quot;
</lisp>
If the second argument is not specified, then <obj>format</obj> sees whether
the stream handles the <obj>:size-in-characters</obj> message.  If it does,
then <obj>format</obj> sends that message and uses the first returned value as
the line length in characters.  If it doesn't, <obj>format</obj> uses <obj>72.</obj>
as the line length.

Rather than using this complicated syntax, one can often call the function
<obj>format:print-list</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-fio" key="format:print-list-fun" title="Function format:print-list" type="fun"></ref>).

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~&gt;</obj></td><td>Terminates a <obj>~&lt;</obj>.  It is undefined elsewhere.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~^</obj></td><td>This is an escape construct.  If there are no more arguments remaining
to be processed, then the immediately enclosing <obj>~{</obj> or <obj>~&lt;</obj>
construct is terminated.  If there is no such enclosing construct, then
the entire formatting operation is terminated.
In the <obj>~&lt;</obj> case, the formatting <arg>is</arg> performed, but no
more segments are processed before doing the justification.
The <obj>~^</obj> should appear only at the <arg>beginning</arg> of a <obj>~&lt;</obj> clause,
because it aborts the entire clause.  <obj>~^</obj> may appear anywhere in a <obj>~{</obj> construct.

If a prefix parameter is given, then termination occurs if the parameter
is zero.  (Hence <obj>~^</obj> is the same as <obj>~#^</obj>.)  If two parameters are
given, termination occurs if they are equal.  If three are given, termination
occurs if the second is between the other two in ascending order.  Of course,
this is useless if all the prefix parameters are constants; at least one
of them should be a <obj>#</obj> or a <obj>V</obj> parameter.

If <obj>~^</obj> is used within a <obj>~:{</obj> construct, then it merely terminates
the current iteration step (because in the standard case it tests for
remaining arguments of the current step only); the next iteration step
commences immediately.  To terminate the entire iteration process,
use <obj>~:^</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~Q</obj></td><td>An escape to arbitrary user-supplied code.  <arg>arg</arg> is called as a function;
its arguments are the prefix parameters to <obj>~Q</obj>, if any.  <arg>args</arg> can be
passed to the function by using the <obj>V</obj> prefix parameter.  The function may
output to <obj>*standard-output*</obj> and may look at the variables <obj>format:colon-flag</obj>
and <obj>format:atsign-flag</obj>, which are <obj>t</obj> or <obj>nil</obj> to reflect the
<obj>:</obj> and <obj>@</obj> modifiers on the <obj>~Q</obj>.  For example,

<lisp>(format t &quot;~VQ&quot; foo bar)
</lisp>is a fancy way to say

<lisp>(funcall bar foo)
</lisp>and discard the value.
Note the reversal of order; the <obj>V</obj> is processed before the <obj>Q</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\</obj></td><td>This begins a directive whose name is longer than one character.
The name is terminated by another <obj>\</obj> character.
The following directives have names longer than one character
and make use of the <obj>~\</obj> mechanism as part of their operation.

<need amount="1500"></need></td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\lozenged-string\</obj></td><td>This is like <obj>~A</obj> except when output is to a window, in which case the
argument is printed in a small font inside a lozenge.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\lozenged-character\</obj></td><td>This is like <obj>~C</obj> except when output is to a window, in which case the
argument is printed in a small font inside a lozenge if it has a character name,
even if it is a formatting character or graphic character.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\date\</obj></td><td>This expects an argument that is a universal time (see
<ref definition-in-file="time" key="universal-time" type="page"></ref>), and prints it as a date and time using
<obj>time:print-universal-date</obj>.

<lisp><exdent amount="96"><caption>Example: </caption>(format t &quot;It is now ~\date\&quot; (get-universal-time))
</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>prints </caption>It is now Saturday the fourth of December, 1982; 4:00:32 am
</exdent></lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\time\</obj></td><td>This expects an argument that is a universal time (see
<ref definition-in-file="time" key="universal-time" type="page"></ref>), and prints it in a brief format using
<obj>time:print-universal-time</obj>.

<lisp><exdent amount="96"><caption>Example: </caption>(format t &quot;It is now ~\time\&quot; (get-universal-time))
</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>prints </caption>It is now 12/04/82 04:01:38
</exdent></lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\datime\</obj></td><td>This prints the current time and date.  It does not use an argument.
It is equivalent to using the <obj>~\time\</obj> directive with
<obj>(time:get-universal-time)</obj> as argument.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>~\time-interval\</obj></td><td>This prints a time interval measured in seconds using the function
<obj>time:print-interval-or-never</obj>.

<lisp><exdent amount="96"><caption>Example: </caption>(format t &quot;It took ~\time-interval\.&quot; 3601.)
</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>prints </caption>It took 1 hour 1 second.
</exdent></lisp></td></tr></tbody></table></p>

<p>You can define your own directives.  How to do this is not documented
here; read the code.  Names of user-defined directives longer than one
character may be used if they are enclosed in backslashes (e.g.
<obj>~4,3\GRAPH\</obj>).
</p>

<p>(Note: <obj>format</obj> also allows <arg>control-string</arg> to be a list.  If the
list is a list of one element, which is a string, the string is simply
printed.  This is for the use of the <obj>format:outfmt</obj> function below.
The old feature wherein a more complex interpretation of this list was
possible is now considered obsolete; use <obj>format:output</obj> if you like
using lists.)
</p>

<p>A condition instance can also be used as the <arg>control-string</arg>.  Then
the <obj>:report</obj> operation is used to print the condition instance;
any other arguments are ignored.  This way, you can pass a condition
instance directly to any function that normally expects a format string
and arguments.
</p>
<definition><define key="format:print-list-fun" name="format:print-list" type="fun"><args>destination element-format list <standard>&amp;optional</standard> separator start-line tilde-brace-options</args>
</define>

<description>This function provides a simpler interface for the specific purpose of
printing comma-separated lists with no list element split across two
lines; see the description of the <obj>~:;</obj> directive
(<ref definition-in-file="fd-fio" key="ultra-hairy-print-list" type="page"></ref>) to see the more complex way to do this
within <obj>format</obj>.  <arg>destination</arg> tells where to send the output; it
can be <obj>t</obj>, <obj>nil</obj>, a <obj>string-nconc</obj>'able string, or a stream, as
with <obj>format</obj>.  <arg>element-format</arg> is a <obj>format</obj> control-string
that tells how to print each element of <arg>list</arg>; it is used as the
body of a <obj>~{...~}</obj> construct.  <arg>separator</arg>, which defaults to
<obj>&quot;, &quot;</obj> (comma, space) is a string which goes after each element
except the last.  <obj>format</obj> control commands are not recommended in
<arg>separator</arg>.  <arg>start-line</arg>, which defaults to three spaces, is a
<obj>format</obj> control-string that is used as a prefix at the beginning of
each line of output, except the first.  <obj>format</obj> control commands are
allowed in <arg>separator</arg>, but they should not swallow arguments from
<arg>list</arg>.  <arg>tilde-brace-options</arg> is a string inserted before the
opening `<obj>{</obj>'; it defaults to the null string, but allows you to
insert colon and/or atsign.  The line-width of the stream is computed
the same way that the <obj>~:;</obj> command computes it;
it is not possible to override the natural line-width of the stream.
</description></definition><page></page></subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="The Output Subsystem"><p>The formatting functions associated with the <obj>format:output</obj> subsystem allow
you to do formatted output using Lisp-style control structure.  Instead
of a directive in a <obj>format</obj> control string, there is one formatting
function for each kind of formatted output.
</p>

<p>The calling conventions of most of the formatting functions are similar.
The first argument is usually the datum to be output.  The second
argument is usually the minimum number of columns to use.  The
remaining arguments are keyword arguments.
</p>

<p>Most of the functions accept the keyword arguments <arg>padchar</arg>, <arg>minpad</arg>
and <arg>tab-period</arg>.  <arg>padchar</arg> is a character to use for padding.
<arg>minpad</arg> is a minimum number of padding characters to output after the data.
<arg>tab-period</arg> is the distance between allowable places
to stop padding.  To make the meaning of <arg>tab-period</arg> clearer, if
the value of <arg>tab-period</arg> is 5, if the minimum size of the field
is 10, and if the value of <arg>minpad</arg> is 2, then a datum that takes 9
characters is padded out to 15 characters.  The requirement to
use at least two characters of padding means it can't fit into 10
characters, and the <arg>tab-period</arg> of 5 means the next allowable
stopping place is at 10+5 characters.  The default values for
<arg>minpad</arg> and <arg>tab-period</arg>, if they are not specified, are
zero and one.  The default value for <arg>padchar</arg> is space.
</p>

<p>The formatting functions always output to <obj>*standard-output*</obj> and do
not require an argument to specify the stream.  The macro
<obj>format:output</obj> allows you to specify the stream or a string, just
as <obj>format</obj> does, and also makes it convenient to concatenate
constant and variable output.
</p>
<definition><define key="format:output-fun" name="format:output" type="mac"><args>stream string-or-form...</args>
</define>

<description>Makes it convenient to intersperse arbitrary output
operations with printing of constant strings.
<obj>*standard-output*</obj> is bound to <arg>stream</arg>, and each <arg>string-or-form</arg>
is processed in succession from left to right.  If it is a string, it is
printed; otherwise it is a form, which is evaluated for effect.  Presumably
the forms will send output to <obj>*standard-output*</obj>.

If <arg>stream</arg> is written as <obj>nil</obj>, then the output is put into a
string which is returned by <obj>format:output</obj>.  If <arg>stream</arg> is written
as <obj>t</obj>, then the output goes to the prevailing value of
<obj>*standard-output*</obj>.  Otherwise <arg>stream</arg> is a form, which must evaluate
to a stream.

Here is an example:

<lisp>(format:output t &quot;FOO is &quot; (prin1 foo) &quot; now.&quot; (terpri))
</lisp>
Because <obj>format:output</obj> is a macro, what matters about <arg>stream</arg> is
not whether it <arg>evaluates</arg> to <obj>t</obj> or <obj>nil</obj>, but whether it
is actually written as <obj>t</obj> or <obj>nil</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:outfmt-fun" name="format:outfmt" type="mac"><args>string-or-form...</args>
</define>

<description>Some system functions ask for a <obj>format</obj> control string and
arguments, to be printed later.  If you wish to generate the output
using the formatted output functions, you can use <obj>format:outfmt</obj>, which
produces a control argument that will eventually make <obj>format</obj>
print the desired output (this is a list whose one element is a string
containing the output).  A call to <obj>format:outfmt</obj> can be used as
the second argument to <obj>ferror</obj>, for example:

<lisp>(ferror nil (format:outfmt &quot;Foo is &quot; (format:onum foo) 
                           &quot; which is too large&quot;))
</lisp></description></definition><definition><define key="format:onum-fun" name="format:onum" type="fun"><args>number <standard>&amp;optional</standard> radix minwidth <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period signed commas</args>
</define>

<description>Outputs <arg>number</arg> in base <arg>radix</arg>, padding to at least
<arg>minwidth</arg> columns and obeying the other padding options specified
as described above.

<arg>radix</arg> can be a number, or it can be <obj>:roman</obj>, <obj>:english</obj>,
or <obj>:ordinal</obj>.  The default <arg>radix</arg> is <obj>10.</obj> (decimal).

If <arg>signed</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, a <obj>+</obj> sign is printed if the number is
positive.  If <arg>commas</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, a comma is printed every third
digit in the customary way.  These arguments are meaningful only with
numeric radices.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:ofloat-fun" name="format:ofloat" type="fun"><args>number <standard>&amp;optional</standard> n-digits force-exponential-notation minwidth <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period</args>
</define>

<description>Outputs <arg>number</arg> as a floating point number using
<arg>n-digits</arg> digits.  If <arg>force-exponential-notation</arg> is
non-<obj>nil</obj>, then an exponent is always used.  <arg>minwidth</arg> and
the padding options are interpreted as usual.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:ostring-fun" name="format:ostring" type="fun"><args>string <standard>&amp;optional</standard> minwidth <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period right-justify</args>
</define>

<description>Outputs <arg>string</arg>, padding to at least
<arg>minwidth</arg> columns if <arg>minwidth</arg> is not <obj>nil</obj>, and obeying
the other padding options specified as described above.

Normally the data are left justified; any padding follows the data.
If <arg>right-justify</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, the padding comes before
the data.  The amount of padding is not affected.

The argument need not really be a string.  Any Lisp object is allowed,
and it is output with <obj>princ</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:oprint-fun" name="format:oprint" type="fun"><args>object <standard>&amp;optional</standard> minwidth <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period right-justify</args>
</define>

<description>Prints <arg>object</arg>, any Lisp object, padding to at
least <arg>minwidth</arg> columns if <arg>minwidth</arg> is not <obj>nil</obj>, and
obeying the padding options specified as described above.

Normally the data are left justified; any padding follows the data.
If <arg>right-justify</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, the padding comes before
the data.  The amount of padding is not affected.

The printing of the object is done with <obj>prin1</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:ochar-fun" name="format:ochar" type="fun"><args>character <standard>&amp;optional</standard> style top-explain minwidth <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period</args>
</define>

<description>Outputs <arg>character</arg> in one of three styles, selected
by the <arg>style</arg> argument.  <arg>minwidth</arg> and the padding options control
padding as usual.


<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:read <standard>or</standard> nil</obj></td><td>The character is printed using <obj>#\</obj> or <obj>#/</obj> so that it could be read
back in.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:editor</obj></td><td>Output is in the style of
`<obj>Meta-Rubout</obj>'.   Non-printing characters, and the two printing
characters Space and Altmode, are represented by their names.  Other printing
characters are printed directly.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:brief</obj></td><td>Brief prefixes such as `<obj>C-</obj>' and
`<obj>M-</obj>' are used, rather than `<obj>Control-</obj>' or `<obj>Meta-</obj>'.  Also,
character names are used only if there are meta bits present.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:lozenged</obj></td><td>The output is the same as that of the <obj>:editor</obj> style, but If the
character is not a graphic character or if it has meta bits, and the
stream supports the <obj>:display-lozenged-string</obj> operation, that
operation is used instead of <obj>:string-out</obj> to print the text.  On
windows this operation puts the character name inside a lozenge.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:sail</obj></td><td>`<example></example>', `<example></example>', etc. are used to represent <obj>Control</obj> and <obj>Meta</obj>,
and shorter names for characters are also used when possible.  See
<ref chapter="11" definition-in-file="fd-str" key="character-set" section="1" title="Characters" type="section"></ref>.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<arg>top-explain</arg> is useful with the <obj>:editor</obj>, <obj>:brief</obj> and
<obj>:sail</obj>
styles.  It says that any character that has to be typed using the
Top or Greek keys should be followed by an explanation of how to type
it.  For example: `<obj>→ (Top-K)</obj>' or `<obj>α (Greek-a)</obj>'.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:tab-fun" name="format:tab" type="fun"><args>mincol <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period terpri unit</args>
</define>

<description>Outputs padding at least until column <arg>mincol</arg>.  It
is the only formatting function that bases its actions on the actual
cursor position rather than the width of what is being output.  The
padding options <arg>padchar</arg>, <arg>minpad</arg>, and <arg>tab-period</arg> are
obeyed.  Thus, at least the <arg>minpad</arg> number of padding characters
are output even if that goes past <arg>mincol</arg>, and once past
<arg>mincol</arg>, padding can only stop at a multiple of <arg>tab-period</arg>
characters past <arg>mincol</arg>.

In addition, if the <arg>terpri</arg> option is <obj>t</obj>, then if column
<arg>mincol</arg> is passed, <obj>format:tab</obj> starts a new line and indents it
to <arg>mincol</arg>.

The <arg>unit</arg> option specifies the units of horizontal position.
The default is to count in units of characters.  If <arg>unit</arg> is
specified as <obj>:pixel</obj>, then the computation (and the argument
<arg>mincol</arg> and the <arg>minpad</arg> and <arg>tab-period</arg> options) are
in units of pixels.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:pad-fun" name="format:pad" type="mac"><args>(minwidth <standard>&amp;key</standard> padchar minpad tab-period...) body...</args>
</define>

<description><obj>format:pad</obj> is used for printing several items in a fixed amount of
horizontal space, padding between them to use up any excess space.
Each of the <arg>body</arg> forms prints one item.  The padding goes between
items.  The entire <obj>format:pad</obj> always uses at least <arg>minwidth</arg>
columns; any columns that the items don't need are distributed as
padding between the items.  If that isn't enough space, then more
space is allocated in units controlled by the <arg>tab-period</arg> option
until there is enough space.  If it's more than enough, the excess is
used as padding.

If the <arg>minpad</arg> option is specified, then at least that many pad
characters must go between each pair of items.

Padding goes only between items.  If you want to treat several actual
pieces of output as one item, put a <obj>progn</obj> around them.  If you
want padding before the first item or after the last, as well as
between the items, include a dummy item <obj>nil</obj> at the beginning or
the end.

If there is only one item, it is right justified.  One item followed by
<obj>nil</obj> is left-justified.  One item preceded and followed by <obj>nil</obj> is
centered.  Therefore, <obj>format:pad</obj> can be used to provide the usual
padding options for a function that does not provide them itself.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:plural-fun" name="format:plural" type="fun"><args>number singular <standard>&amp;optional</standard> plural</args>
</define>

<description>Outputs either the singular or the plural form of a
word depending on the value of <arg>number</arg>.  The singular is used if and only if
<arg>number</arg> is 1.  <arg>singular</arg> specifies the singular form of the word.
<obj>string-pluralize</obj> is used to compute the plural, unless
<arg>plural</arg> is explicitly specified.

It is often useful for <arg>number</arg> to be a value returned by
<obj>format:onum</obj>, which returns its argument.  For example:

<lisp>(format:plural (format:onum n-frobs) &quot; frob&quot;)
</lisp>prints &quot;1 frob&quot; or &quot;2 frobs&quot;.
</description></definition><definition><define key="format:breakline-fun" name="format:breakline" type="mac"><args>linel print-if-terpri print-always...</args>
</define>

<description>Goes to the next line if there is
not enough room for something to be output on the current line.
The <arg>print-always</arg> forms print the text which is supposed to fit
on the line.  <arg>linel</arg> is the column before which the text must end.
If it doesn't end before that column, then <obj>format:breakline</obj>
moves to the next line and executes the <arg>print-if-terpri</arg> form
before doing the <arg>print-always</arg> forms.

Constant strings are allowed as well as forms for <arg>print-if-terpri</arg>
and <arg>print-always</arg>.  A constant string is just printed.

To go to a new line unconditionally, simply call <obj>terpri</obj>.

Here is an example that prints the elements of a list,
separated by commas, breaking lines between elements when necessary.


<lisp>(defun pcl (list linel)
  (do ((l list (cdr l))) ((null l))
    (format:breakline linel &quot;  &quot;
      (princ (car l))
      (and (cdr l) (princ &quot;, &quot;)))))
</lisp></description></definition><page></page></subsection></section>
</document-part>