<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><a name="flavor-chapter"></a>
<chapter name="flavor-chapter" number="22" title="Objects, Message Passing, and Flavors"><index-entry index="concepts" title="flavor"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="message"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="method"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="object"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="instance"></index-entry>

<p>The object-oriented programming style used in the Smalltalk and
Actor families of languages is available in Zetalisp and used
by the Lisp Machine software system.  Its purpose is to perform
<arg>generic operations</arg> on objects.  Part of its implementation is
simply a convention in procedure-calling style; part is a powerful
language feature, called Flavors, for defining abstract objects.
This chapter attempts to explain what programming with objects and with
message passing means, the various means of implementing these in
Zetalisp, and when you should use them.  It assumes no prior
knowledge of any other languages.
</p>
<a name="Objects"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Objects" number="1" title="Objects"><p>When writing a program, it is often convenient to model what the program
does in terms of <arg>objects</arg>, conceptual entities that can be likened to
real-world things.  Choosing what objects to provide in a program is
very important to the proper organization of the program.  In an
object-oriented design, specifying what objects exist is the first
task in designing the system.  In a text editor, the objects might be
``pieces of text'', ``pointers into text'', and ``display windows''.  In an
electrical design system, the objects might be ``resistors'',
``capacitors'', ``transistors'', ``wires'', and ``display windows''.  After
specifying what objects there are, the next task of the design is to
figure out what operations can be performed on each object.  In the text
editor example, operations on ``pieces of text'' might include inserting
text and deleting text; operations on ``pointers into text'' might include
moving forward and backward; and operations on ``display windows'' might
include redisplaying the window and changing which ``piece of text'' the
window is associated with.
</p>

<p>In this model, we think of the program as being built around a set of
objects, each of which has a set of operations that can be performed on
it.  More rigorously, the program defines several <arg>types</arg> of object
(the editor above has three types), and it can create many <arg>instances</arg>
of each type (that is, there can be many pieces of text, many pointers
into text, and many windows).  The program defines a set of types of
object and, for each type, a set of operations that can be performed on
any object of the type.
</p>

<p>The new types may exist only in the programmer's mind.  For example, it
is possible to think of a disembodied property list as an abstract data
type on which certain operations such as <obj>get</obj> and <obj>putprop</obj> are
defined.  This type can be instantiated with <obj>(cons nil nil)</obj> (that
is, by evaluating this form you can create a new disembodied property
list); the operations are invoked through functions defined just for
that purpose.  The fact that disembodied property lists are really
implemented as lists, indistinguishable from any other lists, does not
invalidate this point of view.  However, such conceptual data types
cannot be distinguished automatically by the system; one cannot ask ``is
this object a disembodied property list, as opposed to an ordinary
list''.
</p>

<p>The <obj>defstruct</obj> for <obj>ship</obj> early in chapter <ref chapter="21" definition-in-file="defstr" key="defstruct-chapter" title="Defstruct" type="chapter"></ref>
defines another conceptual type.  <obj>defstruct</obj> automatically defines some
operations on this object, the operations to access its elements.  We
could define other functions that did useful things with <obj>ship</obj>'s,
such as computing their speed, angle of travel, momentum, or velocity,
stopping them, moving them elsewhere, and so on.
</p>

<p>In both cases, we represent our conceptual object by one Lisp object.
The Lisp object we use for the representation has <arg>structure</arg> and
refers to other Lisp objects.  In the disembodied property list case,
the Lisp object is a list of pairs; in the <obj>ship</obj> case, the Lisp
object is an array whose details are taken care of by <obj>defstruct</obj>.  In
both cases, we can say that the object keeps track of an <arg>internal
state</arg>, which can be <arg>examined</arg> and <arg>altered</arg> by the operations
available for that type of object.  <obj>get</obj> examines the state of a
property list, and <obj>putprop</obj> alters it; <obj>ship-x-position</obj> examines
the state of a ship, and <obj>(setf (ship-x-position <arg>ship</arg>) 5.0)</obj>
alters it.
</p>

<p>We have now seen the essence of object-oriented programming.  A
conceptual object is modeled by a single Lisp object, which bundles up
some state information.  For every type of object, there is a set of
operations that can be performed to examine or alter the state of the
object.
</p>
</section><a name="Modularity"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Modularity" number="2" title="Modularity"><p>An important benefit of the object-oriented style is that it lends
itself to a particularly simple and lucid kind of modularity.
If you have modular programming constructs and techniques available,
they help and encourage you to write
programs that are easy to read and understand, and so are more
reliable and maintainable.  Object-oriented programming lets a
programmer implement a useful facility that presents the caller with a set
of external interfaces, without requiring the caller to understand how
the internal details of the implementation work.  In other words, a program
that calls this facility can treat the facility as a black box; the
program knows what the facility's external interfaces guarantee to do,
and that is all it knows.
</p>

<p>For example, a program that uses disembodied property lists never needs
to know that the property list is being maintained as a list of
alternating indicators and values; the program simply performs the
operations, passing them inputs and getting back outputs.  The program
only depends on the external definition of these operations: it knows
that if it <obj>putprop</obj>'s a property, and doesn't <obj>remprop</obj> it (or
<obj>putprop</obj> over it), then it can do <obj>get</obj> and be sure of getting back
the same thing it put in.  The important thing about this hiding of
the details of the implementation is that someone reading a program that uses disembodied
property lists need not concern himself with how they are implemented;
he need only understand what they undertake to do.  This saves the
programmer a lot of time and lets him concentrate his energies on
understanding the program he is working on.  Another good thing about
this hiding is that the representation of property lists could be
changed and the program would continue to work.  For example, instead
of a list of alternating elements, the property list could be
implemented as an association list or a hash table.  Nothing in the
calling program would change at all.
</p>

<p>The same is true of the <obj>ship</obj> example.  The caller is presented with
a collection of operations, such as <obj>ship-x-position</obj>,
<obj>ship-y-position</obj>, <obj>ship-speed</obj>, and <obj>ship-direction</obj>; it simply
calls these and looks at their answers, without caring how they did what
they did.  In our example above, <obj>ship-x-position</obj> and
<obj>ship-y-position</obj> would be accessor functions, defined automatically
by <obj>defstruct</obj>, while <obj>ship-speed</obj> and <obj>ship-direction</obj> would be
functions defined by the implementor of the <obj>ship</obj> type.  The code
might look like this:
</p>

<lisp>(defstruct (ship :conc-name)
  x-position
  y-position
  x-velocity
  y-velocity
  mass)

(defun ship-speed (ship)
  (sqrt (+ (^ (ship-x-velocity ship) 2)
           (^ (ship-y-velocity ship) 2))))

(defun ship-direction (ship)
  (atan2 (ship-y-velocity ship)
         (ship-x-velocity ship)))
</lisp>
<p>The caller need not know that the first two functions were structure accessors
and that the second two were written by hand and do arithmetic.  Those
facts would not be considered part of the black box characteristics of
the implementation of the <obj>ship</obj> type.  The <obj>ship</obj> type does not
guarantee which functions will be implemented in which ways; such aspects
are not part of the contract between <obj>ship</obj> and its callers.  In fact,
<obj>ship</obj> could have been written this way instead:
</p>

<lisp>(defstruct (ship :conc-name)
  x-position
  y-position
  speed
  direction
  mass)

(defun ship-x-velocity (ship)
  (* (ship-speed ship) (cos (ship-direction ship))))

(defun ship-y-velocity (ship)
  (* (ship-speed ship) (sin (ship-direction ship))))
</lisp>
<p>In this second implementation of the <obj>ship</obj> type, we have decided to
store the velocity in polar coordinates instead of rectangular
coordinates.  This is purely an implementation decision.  The caller has
no idea which of the two ways the implementation uses; he just
performs the operations on the object by calling the appropriate
functions.
</p>

<p>We have now created our own types of objects, whose implementations are
hidden from the programs that use them.  Such types are usually referred to as
<arg>abstract types</arg>.  The object-oriented style of programming can be
used to create abstract types by hiding the implementation of the
operations and simply documenting what the operations are defined to do.
</p>

<p>Some more terminology: the quantities being held by the elements of the
<obj>ship</obj> structure are referred to as <arg>instance variables</arg>.  Each
instance of a type has the same operations defined on it; what
distinguishes one instance from another (besides <obj>eq</obj>-ness)
is the values that reside in its instance variables.  The example above
illustrates that a caller of operations does not know what the instance
variables are; our two ways of writing the <obj>ship</obj> operations have
different instance variables, but from the outside they have exactly the
same operations.
</p>

<p>One might ask: ``But what if the caller evaluates <obj>(aref ship 2)</obj> and
notices that he gets back the <arg>x</arg> velocity rather than the speed?  Then he
can tell which of the two implementations were used.''  This is true; if
the caller were to do that, he could tell.  However, when a facility is
implemented in the object-oriented style, only certain functions are
documented and advertised, the functions that are considered to be
operations on the type of object.  The contract from <obj>ship</obj> to its
callers only speaks about what happens if the caller calls these
functions.  The contract makes no guarantees at all about what would
happen if the caller were to start poking around on his own using
<obj>aref</obj>.  A caller who does so <arg>is in error</arg>; he is depending on
something that is not specified in the contract.  No guarantees were
ever made about the results of such action, and so anything may happen;
indeed, <obj>ship</obj> may get reimplemented overnight, and the code that does
the <obj>aref</obj> will have a different effect entirely and probably stop
working.  This example shows why the concept of a contract between a callee and
a caller is important: the contract specifies the interface
between the two modules.
</p>

<p>Unlike some other languages that provide abstract types, Zetalisp
makes no attempt to have the language automatically forbid
constructs that circumvent the contract.  This is intentional.  One
reason for this is that the Lisp Machine is an interactive system, and
so it is important to be able to examine and alter internal state
interactively (usually from a debugger).  Furthermore, there is no
strong distinction between the ``system'' programs and the ``user'' programs
on the Lisp Machine; users are allowed to get into any part of the
language system and change what they want to change.  Another reason is
the traditional MIT AI Lab philosophy that opposes ``fascist'' restrictions
which impose on the user ``for his own good''.  The user himself should
decide what is good for him.
</p>

<p>In summary: by defining a set of operations and making only a
specific set of external entrypoints available to the caller, the
programmer can create his own abstract types.  These types can be useful
facilities for other programs and programmers.  Since the implementation
of the type is hidden from the callers, modularity is maintained and
the implementation can be changed easily.
</p>

<p>We have hidden the implementation of an abstract type by making its
operations into functions which the user may call.  The important thing
is not that they are functions--in Lisp everything is done with functions.
The important thing is that we have defined a new conceptual operation
and given it a name, rather than requiring anyone who wants to do the
operation to write it out step-by-step.  Thus we say <obj>(ship-x-velocity s)</obj>
rather than <obj>(aref s 2)</obj>.
</p>

<p>Often a few abstract operation functions are simple enough that
it is desirable
to compile special code for them rather than really calling the function.
(Compiling special code like this is often called <arg>open-coding</arg>.)
The compiler is directed to do this through use of macros, substs, or
optimizers.  <obj>defstruct</obj> arranges for this kind of special compilation
for the functions that get the instance variables of a structure.
</p>

<p>When we use this optimization, the implementation of the abstract type
is only hidden in a certain sense.  It does not appear in the Lisp code
written by the user, but does appear in the compiled code.  The reason
is that there may be some compiled functions that use the macros (or whatever);
even if you change the definition of the macro, the existing compiled
code will continue to use the old definition.  Thus, if
the implementation of a module is changed programs that use it may need to be
recompiled.  This is something we sometimes accept for the sake of
efficiency.
</p>

<p>In the present implementation of flavors, which is discussed below,
there is no such compiler incorporation of nonmodular knowledge into a
program, except when the <obj>:ordered-instance-variables</obj> feature is
used; see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="ordered-instance-variables-option" type="page"></ref>, where this problem is
explained further.  If you don't use the
<obj>:ordered-instance-variables</obj> feature, you don't have to worry about
this.
</p>
</section><a name="Generic Operations"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Generic Operations" number="3" title="Generic Operations"><p>Suppose we think about the rest of the program that uses the
<obj>ship</obj> abstraction.  It may want to deal with other objects that are
like <obj>ship</obj>'s in that they are movable objects with mass, but unlike
<obj>ship</obj>s in other ways.  A more advanced model of a ship might include
the concept of the ship's engine power, the number of passengers on
board, and its name.  An object representing a meteor probably would
not have any of these, but might have another attribute such as how
much iron is in it.
</p>

<p>However, all kinds of movable objects have positions, velocities, and
masses, and the system will contain some programs that deal with these
quantities in a uniform way, regardless of what kind of object the
attributes apply to.  For example, a piece of the system that calculates
every object's orbit in space need not worry about the other, more
peripheral attributes of various types of objects; it works the same way
for all objects.  Unfortunately, a program that tries to calculate the
orbit of a ship needs to know the ship's attributes, and must therefore
call <obj>ship-x-position</obj> and <obj>ship-y-velocity</obj> and so on.  The problem is
that these functions won't work for meteors.  There would have to be a
second program to calculate orbits for meteors that would be exactly the
same, except that where the first one calls <obj>ship-x-position</obj>, the
second one would call <obj>meteor-x-position</obj>, and so on.  This would be
very bad; a great deal of code would have to exist in multiple copies,
all of it would have to be maintained in parallel, and it would take up
space for no good reason.
</p>

<p>What is needed is an operation that can be performed on objects of
several different types.  For each type, it should do the thing
appropriate for that type.  Such operations are called <arg>generic</arg>
operations.  The classic example of generic operations is the arithmetic
functions in most programming languages, including Zetalisp.  The <obj>+</obj>
(or <obj>plus</obj>) function accepts integers, floats, ratios and complex
numbers, and perform an appropriate kind of addition, based on the data
types of the objects being manipulated.  In our example, we need a
generic <obj>x-position</obj> operation that can be performed on either
<obj>ship</obj>'s, <obj>meteor</obj>'s, or any other kind of mobile object represented
in the system.  This way, we can write a single program to calculate
orbits.  When it wants to know the <arg>x</arg> position of the object it is
dealing with, it simply invokes the generic <obj>x-position</obj> operation on
the object, and whatever type of object it has, the correct operation is
performed, and the <arg>x</arg> position is returned.
</p>

<p>Another terminology for the use of such generic operations has emerged
from the Smalltalk language: performing a generic operation
is called <arg>sending a message</arg>.  The message consists of an operation
name (a symbol) and arguments.  The objects in the program are thought
of as little people, who get sent messages and respond with answers
(returned values).  In the example above, the objects are sent
<obj>x-position</obj> messages, to which they respond with their <arg>x</arg>
position.
</p>

<p>Sending a message is a way of invoking a function without specifying
which function is to be called.  Instead, the data determines the
function to use.  The caller specifies an operation name and an object;
that is, it said what operation to perform, and what object to perform
it on.  The function to invoke is found from this information.
</p>

<p>The two data used to figure out which function
to call are the <arg>type</arg> of the object, and the <arg>name</arg> of the operation.
The same set of functions are used for all instances of a given type, so
the type is the only attribute of the object used to figure out which
function to call.  The rest of the message besides the operation is data
which are passed as arguments to the function, so the operation is the only
part of the message used to find the function.  Such a function is
called a <arg>method</arg>.  For example, if we send an <obj>x-position</obj> message
to an object of type <obj>ship</obj>, then the function we find is ``the
<obj>ship</obj> type's <obj>x-position</obj> method''.  A method is a function that
handles a specific operation on a specific kind of object; this
method handles messages named <obj>x-position</obj> to objects of type
<obj>ship</obj>.
</p>

<p>In our new terminology: the orbit-calculating program finds the <arg>x</arg>
position of the object it is working on by sending that object a message
consisting of the operation <obj>x-position</obj> and no arguments.  The
returned value of the message is the <arg>x</arg> position of the object.  If
the object was of type <obj>ship</obj>, then the <obj>ship</obj> type's <obj>x-position</obj>
method was invoked; if it was of type <obj>meteor</obj>, then the <obj>meteor</obj>
type's <obj>x-position</obj> method was invoked.  The orbit-calculating program
just sends the message, and the right function is invoked based on the
type of the object.  We now have true generic functions, in the form of
message passing: the same operation can mean different things depending
on the type of the object.
</p>
</section><a name="Generic Operations in Lisp"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Generic Operations in Lisp" number="4" title="Generic Operations in Lisp"><p>How do we implement message passing in Lisp?  Our convention is that objects
that receive messages are always <arg>functional</arg> objects (that is, you
can apply them to arguments).  A message is sent to an object by
calling that object as a function, passing the operation name as
the first argument and the arguments of the message as the rest of the
arguments.  Operation names are represented by symbols; normally these
symbols are in the keyword package (see <ref chapter="28" definition-in-file="packd" key="package" section="0" title="Packages" type="section"></ref>), since messages are
a protocol for communication between different programs, which may
reside in different packages.  So if we have a variable <obj>my-ship</obj>
whose value is an object of type <obj>ship</obj>, and we want to know its
<arg>x</arg> position, we send it a message as follows:
</p>

<lisp>(send my-ship :x-position)
</lisp>
<p>To set the
ship's <arg>x</arg> position to <obj>3.0</obj>, we send it a message like this:
</p>

<lisp>(send my-ship :set :x-position 3.0)
</lisp>
<p>It should be stressed that no new features are added to Lisp for message
sending; we simply define a convention on the way objects take
arguments.  The convention says that an object accepts messages by
always interpreting its first argument as an operation name.  The object
must consider this operation name, find the function which is the method
for that operation, and invoke that function.
</p>
<definition><define key="send-fun" name="send" type="fun"><args>object operation <standard>&amp;rest</standard> arguments</args>
</define>

<description>Sends <arg>object</arg> a message with operation and arguments as specified.
Currently <obj>send</obj> is identical to <obj>funcall</obj>, but preferable when
a message is being sent, just for clarity.

There are vague ideas of making <arg>send</arg> different from <arg>funcall</arg>
if <arg>object</arg> is a symbol, list, number, or other object that does not
normally handle messages when funcalled, but the meaning of this is
not completely clear.
</description></definition><definition><define key="lexpr-send-fun" name="lexpr-send" type="fun"><args>object operation <standard>&amp;rest</standard> arguments</args>
</define>

<description>Currently <obj>lexpr-send</obj> is the same as <arg>apply</arg>.
</description></definition>
<p>This raises the question of how message receiving works.  The object
must somehow find the right method for the message it is sent.
Furthermore, the object now has to be callable as a function.  But an
ordinary function will not do.  We need something that can store the
instance variables (the internal state) of the object.  We need a
function with internal state; that is, we need a coroutine.
</p>

<p>Of the Zetalisp features presented so far, the most appropriate
is the closure (see <ref chapter="13" definition-in-file="fd-clo" key="closure" section="0" title="Closures" type="section"></ref>).  A message-receiving object could be
implemented as a closure over a set of instance variables.  The function
inside the closure would have a big <obj>selectq</obj> form to dispatch on its
first argument.  (Actually, rather than using closures and a <obj>selectq</obj>,
you would probably use entities (<ref chapter="13" definition-in-file="fd-clo" key="entity" section="4" title="Entities" type="section"></ref>) and <obj>defselect</obj> (<ref definition-in-file="fd-fun" key="defselect-fun" title="Special Form defselect" type="spec"></ref>).)
</p>

<p>While using closures (or entities) does work, it has several serious
problems.  The main problem is that in order to add a new operation to a
system, it is necessary to modify a lot of code; you have to find all
the types that understand that operation, and add a new clause to the
<obj>selectq</obj>.  The problem with this is that you cannot textually
separate the implementation of your new operation from the rest of the
system; the methods must be interleaved with the other operations for
the type.  Adding a new operation should only require <arg>adding</arg> Lisp code;
it should not require <arg>modifying</arg> Lisp code.
</p>

<p>The conventional way of making generic operations is to have a procedure
for each operation, which has a big <obj>selectq</obj> for all the types; this
means you have to modify code to add a type.  The way described above is
to have a procedure for each type, which has a big <obj>selectq</obj> for all
the operations; this means you have to modify code to add an operation.
Neither of these has the desired property that extending the system
should only require adding code, rather than modifying code.
</p>

<p>Closures (and entities) are also somewhat clumsy and crude.  A far more
streamlined, convenient, and powerful system for creating
message-receiving objects exists; it is called the <arg>flavor</arg> mechanism.
With flavors, you can add a new method simply by adding code, without
modifying anything.  Furthermore, many common and useful things
are very easy to do with flavors.  The rest of this chapter describes
flavors.
</p>
</section><a name="Simple Use of Flavors"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Simple Use of Flavors" number="5" title="Simple Use of Flavors"><p>A <arg>flavor</arg>, in its simplest form, is a definition of an abstract type.
New flavors are created with the <obj>defflavor</obj> special form, and
methods of the flavor are created with the <obj>defmethod</obj> special form.
New instances of a flavor are created with the <obj>make-instance</obj>
function.  This section explains simple uses of these forms.
</p>

<p>For an example of a simple use of flavors, here is how the <obj>ship</obj>
example above would be implemented.
</p>

<lisp>(defflavor ship (x-position y-position 
                 x-velocity y-velocity mass)
                ()
  :gettable-instance-variables)

(defmethod (ship :speed) ()
  (sqrt (+ (^ x-velocity 2)
           (^ y-velocity 2))))

(defmethod (ship :direction) ()
  (atan2 y-velocity x-velocity))
</lisp>
<p>The code above creates a new flavor.  The first subform of the
<obj>defflavor</obj> is <obj>ship</obj>, which is the name of the new flavor.  Next
is the list of instance variables; they are the five that should be
familiar by now.  The next subform is something we will get to later.
The rest of the subforms are the body of the <obj>defflavor</obj>, and each
one specifies an option about this flavor.  In our example, there is
only one option, namely <obj>:gettable-instance-variables</obj>.  This means
that for each instance variable, a method should automatically be
generated to return the value of that instance variable.  The name of
the operation is a symbol with the same name as the instance variable, but
interned on the keyword package.  Thus, methods are created to handle
the operations <obj>:x-position</obj>, <obj>:y-position</obj>, and so on.
</p>

<p>Each of the two <obj>defmethod</obj> forms adds a method to the flavor.  The
first one adds a handler to the flavor <obj>ship</obj> for the operation
<obj>:speed</obj>.  The second subform is the lambda-list, and the rest is the
body of the function that handles the <obj>:speed</obj> operation.  The body can
refer to or set any instance variables of the flavor, just like variables
bound by a containing <obj>let</obj>.  When any instance of the
<obj>ship</obj> flavor is invoked with a first argument of <obj>:direction</obj>, the
body of the second <obj>defmethod</obj> is evaluated in an environment in
which the instance variables of <obj>ship</obj> refer to the instance variables
of this instance (the one to which the message was sent).  So the arguments
passed to <obj>cli:atan</obj> are the the velocity components of this particular ship.
The result of <obj>cli:atan</obj> becomes the value returned by the <obj>:direction</obj>
operation.
</p>

<p>Now we have seen how to create a new abstract type: a new flavor.  Every
instance of this flavor has the five instance variables named in
the <obj>defflavor</obj> form, and the seven methods we have seen (five that
were automatically generated because of the
<obj>:gettable-instance-variables</obj> option, and two that we wrote
ourselves).  The way to create an instance of our new flavor is with the
<obj>make-instance</obj> function.  Here is how it could be used:
</p>

<lisp>(setq my-ship (make-instance 'ship))
</lisp>
<p>This returns an object whose printed representation is
<obj>#&lt;SHIP 13731210&gt;</obj>.
(Of course, the value of the magic number will vary; it is just
the object address in octal.)  The argument to <obj>make-instance</obj> is
the name of the flavor to be instantiated.  Additional
arguments, not used here, are <arg>init options</arg>, that is, commands
to the flavor of which we are making an instance, selecting optional
features.  This will be discussed more in a moment.
</p>

<p>Examination of the flavor we have defined shows that it is quite useless
as it stands, since there is no way to set any of the parameters.  We
can fix this up easily by putting the <obj>:settable-instance-variables</obj>
option into the <obj>defflavor</obj> form.  This option tells <obj>defflavor</obj> to
generate methods for operation <obj>:set</obj> for first argument
<obj>:x-position</obj>, <obj>:y-position</obj>, and so on; each such method takes one
additional argument and sets the corresponding instance variable to that value.
It also generates methods for the operations <obj>:set-x-position</obj>,
<obj>:set-y-position</obj> and so on; each of these takes one argument
and sets the corresponding variable.
</p>

<p>Another option we can add to the <obj>defflavor</obj> is
<obj>:inittable-instance-variables</obj>, which allows us to initialize the values
of the instance variables when an instance is first created.
<obj>:inittable-instance-variables</obj> does not create any methods; instead,
it makes <arg>initialization keywords</arg> named <obj>:x-position</obj>,
<obj>:y-position</obj>, etc., that can be used as init-option arguments to
<obj>make-instance</obj> to initialize the corresponding instance variables.
The list of init options is sometimes called the <arg>init-plist</arg> because
it is like a property list.
</p>

<p>Here is the improved <obj>defflavor</obj>:

<lisp>(defflavor ship (x-position y-position
                 x-velocity y-velocity mass) 
                ()
  :gettable-instance-variables
  :settable-instance-variables
  :inittable-instance-variables)
</lisp></p>

<p>All we have to do is evaluate this new <obj>defflavor</obj>, and the existing
flavor definition is updated and now includes the new methods and
initialization options.  In fact, the instance we generated a while ago
now accepts the new operations!  We can set the mass of
the ship we created by evaluating

<lisp>(send my-ship :set-mass 3.0)
<exdent amount="96"><caption>or </caption>(send my-ship :set :mass 3.0)
</exdent></lisp>and the <obj>mass</obj> instance variable of <obj>my-ship</obj> is properly set to
<obj>3.0</obj>.  Whether you use <obj>:set-mass</obj> or the general operation
<obj>:set</obj> is a matter of style; <obj>:set</obj> is used by the expansion of
<obj>(setf (send my-ship :mass) 3.0)</obj>.
</p>

<p>If you want to play around with flavors, it is useful
to know that <obj>describe</obj> of an instance tells you the flavor of the
instance and the values of its instance variables.  If we were to evaluate
<obj>(describe my-ship)</obj> at this point, the following would be printed:
</p>

<lisp>#&lt;SHIP 13731210&gt;, an object of flavor SHIP,
 has instance variable values:
        X-POSITION:         void
        Y-POSITION:         void
        X-VELOCITY:         void
        Y-VELOCITY:         void
        MASS:               3.0
</lisp>
<p>Now that the instance variables are <arg>inittable</arg>, we can create another
ship and initialize some of the instance variables using the init-plist.
Let's do that and <obj>describe</obj> the result:
</p>

<lisp>(setq her-ship (make-instance 'ship :x-position 0.0
                                    :y-position 2.0
                                    :mass 3.5))
                =&gt; #&lt;SHIP 13756521&gt;


(describe her-ship)
#&lt;SHIP 13756521&gt;, an object of flavor SHIP,
 has instance variable values:
        X-POSITION:         0.0
        Y-POSITION:         2.0
        X-VELOCITY:         void
        Y-VELOCITY:         void
        MASS:               3.5
</lisp>
<p>A flavor can also establish default initial values for instance
variables.  These default values are used when a new instance is created
if the values are not initialized any other way.  The syntax for
specifying a default initial value is to replace the name of the
instance variable by a list, whose first element is the name and whose
second is a form to evaluate to produce the default initial value.  For
example:
</p>

<lisp>(defvar *default-x-velocity* 2.0)
(defvar *default-y-velocity* 3.0)

(defflavor ship ((x-position 0.0)
                 (y-position 0.0)
                 (x-velocity *default-x-velocity*)
                 (y-velocity *default-y-velocity*)
                 mass) 
                ()
  :gettable-instance-variables
  :settable-instance-variables
  :inittable-instance-variables)

(setq another-ship (make-instance 'ship :x-position 3.4))
 =&gt; #&lt;SHIP 14563643&gt;

(describe another-ship)
#&lt;SHIP 14563643&gt;, an object of flavor SHIP,
 has instance variable values:
        X-POSITION:         3.4
        Y-POSITION:         0.0
        X-VELOCITY:         2.0
        Y-VELOCITY:         3.0
        MASS:               void
</lisp>
<p><obj>x-position</obj> was initialized explicitly, so the default was ignored.
<obj>y-position</obj> was initialized from the default value, which was
<obj>0.0</obj>.  The two velocity instance variables were initialized from
their default values, which came from two global variables.  <obj>mass</obj>
was not explicitly initialized and did not have a default
initialization, so it was left void.
</p>

<p>There are many other options that can be used in <obj>defflavor</obj>, and the
init options can be used more flexibly than just to initialize instance
variables; full details are given later in this chapter.  But even with
the small set of features we have seen so far, it is easy to write
object-oriented programs.
</p>
</section><a name="Mixing Flavors"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Mixing Flavors" number="6" title="Mixing Flavors"><p>Now we have a system for defining message-receiving objects so that we
can have generic operations.  If we want to create a new type called
<obj>meteor</obj> that would accept the same generic operations as <obj>ship</obj>, we
could simply write another <obj>defflavor</obj> and two more <obj>defmethod</obj>'s
that looked just like those of <obj>ship</obj>, and then meteors and ships
would both accept the same operations.  <obj>ship</obj> would have some
more instance variables for holding attributes specific to ships
and some more methods for operations that are not generic, but
are only defined for ships; the same would be true of <obj>meteor</obj>.
</p>

<p>However, this would be a a wasteful thing to do.  The same code has to
be repeated in several places, and several instance variables have to be
repeated.  The code now needs to be maintained in many places, which is
always undesirable.  The power of flavors (and the name ``flavors'') comes
from the ability to mix several flavors and get a new flavor.  Since the
functionality of <obj>ship</obj> and <obj>meteor</obj> partially overlap, we can take
the common functionality and move it into its own flavor, which might be
called <obj>moving-object</obj>.  We would define <obj>moving-object</obj> the same
way as we defined <obj>ship</obj> in the previous section.  Then, <obj>ship</obj> and
<obj>meteor</obj> could be defined like this:
</p>

<lisp>(defflavor ship (engine-power number-of-passengers name) 
                (moving-object)
   :gettable-instance-variables)

(defflavor meteor (percent-iron)
                  (moving-object)
   :inittable-instance-variables)
</lisp>
<p>These <obj>defflavor</obj> forms use the second subform, which we ignored
previously.  The second subform is a list of flavors to be combined to
form the new flavor; such flavors are called <arg>components</arg>.
Concentrating on <obj>ship</obj> for a moment (analogous things are true of
<obj>meteor</obj>), we see that it has exactly one component flavor:
<obj>moving-object</obj>.  It also has a list of instance variables, which
includes only the ship-specific instance variables and not the ones that
it shares with <obj>meteor</obj>.  By incorporating <obj>moving-object</obj>, the <obj>ship</obj>
flavor acquires all of its instance variables, and so need not name them
again.  It also acquires all of <obj>moving-object</obj>'s methods, too.  So
with the new definition, <obj>ship</obj> instances still implement the
<obj>:x-velocity</obj> and <obj>:speed</obj> operations, with the same meaning as before.
However, the <obj>:engine-power</obj> operation is also understood (and
returns the value of the <obj>engine-power</obj> instance variable).
</p>

<p>What we have done here is to take an abstract type, <obj>moving-object</obj>,
and build two more specialized and powerful abstract types on top of it.
Any ship or meteor can do anything a moving object can do, and each also
has its own specific abilities.  This kind of building can continue; we
could define a flavor called <obj>ship-with-passenger</obj> that was built on
top of <obj>ship</obj>, and it would inherit all of <obj>moving-object</obj>'s
instance variables and methods as well as <obj>ship</obj>'s instance variables
and methods.  Furthermore, the second subform of <obj>defflavor</obj> can be a
list of several components, meaning that the new flavor should combine
all the instance variables and methods of all the flavors in the list,
as well as the ones <arg>those</arg> flavors are built on, and so on.  All the
components taken together form a big tree of flavors.  A flavor is built
from its components, its components' components, and so on.  We
sometimes use the term ``components'' to mean the immediate components
(the ones listed in the <obj>defflavor</obj>), and sometimes to mean all the
components (including the components of the immediate components and so
on).  (Actually, it is not strictly a tree, since some flavors might be
components through more than one path.  It is really a directed graph;
it can even be cyclic.)
</p>

<p>The order in which the components are combined to form a flavor is
important.  The tree of flavors is turned into an ordered list by
performing a <arg>top-down, depth-first</arg> walk of the tree, including
non-terminal nodes <arg>before</arg> the subtrees they head, ignoring any
flavor that has been encountered previously somewhere else in the tree.
For example, if <obj>flavor-1</obj>'s immediate components are <obj>flavor-2</obj> and
<obj>flavor-3</obj>, and <obj>flavor-2</obj>'s components are <obj>flavor-4</obj> and
<obj>flavor-5</obj>, and <obj>flavor-3</obj>'s component was <obj>flavor-4</obj>, then the
complete list of components of <obj>flavor-1</obj> would be:

<lisp>flavor-1, flavor-2, flavor-4, flavor-5, flavor-3
</lisp>The flavors earlier in this list are the more specific, less basic ones;
in our example, <obj>ship-with-passengers</obj> would be first in the list,
followed by <obj>ship</obj>, followed by <obj>moving-object</obj>.  A flavor is always
the first in the list of its own components.  Notice that <obj>flavor-4</obj>
does not appear twice in this list.  Only the first occurrence of a
flavor appears; duplicates are removed.  (The elimination of duplicates
is done during the walk; if there is a cycle in the directed graph, it
does not cause a non-terminating computation.)
</p>

<p>The set of instance variables for the new flavor is the union of all the
sets of instance variables in all the component flavors.  If both
<obj>flavor-2</obj> and <obj>flavor-3</obj> have instance variables named <obj>foo</obj>,
then <obj>flavor-1</obj> has an instance variable named <obj>foo</obj>, and any
methods that refer to <obj>foo</obj> refer to this same instance variable.
Thus different components of a flavor can communicate with one another
using shared instance variables.  (Typically, only one component ever
sets the variable; the others only look at it.)  The default initial
value for an instance variable comes from the first component flavor to
specify one.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="combined method"></index-entry>

<p>The way the methods of the components are combined is the heart of the
flavor system.  When a flavor is defined, a single function, called a
<arg>combined method</arg>, is constructed for each operation supported by the
flavor.  This function is constructed out of all the methods for that
operation from all the components of the flavor.  There are many different
ways that methods can be combined; these can be selected by the user
when a flavor is defined.  The user can also create new forms of
combination.
</p>

<p>There are several kinds of methods, but
so far, the only kinds of methods we have seen are <arg>primary</arg> methods.
The default way primary methods are combined is that all but the
earliest one provided are ignored.  In other words, the combined method
is simply the primary method of the first flavor to provide a primary
method.  What this means is that if you are starting with a flavor
<obj>foo</obj> and building a flavor <obj>bar</obj> on top of it, then you can
override <obj>foo</obj>'s method for an operation by providing your own method.
Your method will be called, and <obj>foo</obj>'s will never be called.
</p>

<p>Simple overriding is often useful; for example, if you want to make a
new flavor <obj>bar</obj> that is just like <obj>foo</obj> except that it reacts
completely differently to a few operations.  However, often you don't
want to completely override the base flavor's (<obj>foo</obj>'s) method;
sometimes you want to add some extra things to be done.  This is where
combination of methods is used.
</p>

<p>The usual way methods are combined is that one flavor provides a primary
method, and other flavors provide <arg>daemon methods</arg>.  The idea
is that the primary method is ``in charge'' of the main business of
handling the operation, but other flavors just want to keep informed
that the message was sent, or just want to do the part of the operation
associated with their own area of responsibility.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="daemon methods"></index-entry>

<p><arg>daemon</arg> methods come in two kinds, <arg>before</arg> and <arg>after</arg>.  There is
a special syntax in <obj>defmethod</obj> for defining such methods.  Here is an example
of the syntax.  To give the <obj>ship</obj> flavor an after-daemon method for the
<obj>:speed</obj> operation, the following syntax would be used:

<lisp>(defmethod (ship :after :speed) () <arg>body</arg>)
</lisp></p>

<p>Now, when a message is sent, it is handled by a new function called the
<arg>combined</arg> method.  The combined method first calls all of the before daemons,
then the primary method, then all the after daemons.  Each method is passed the
same arguments that the combined method was given.  The returned values from the
combined method are the values returned by the primary method; any values
returned from the daemons are ignored.  Before-daemons are called in the order
that flavors are combined, while after-daemons are called in the reverse order.
In other words, if you build <obj>bar</obj> on top of <obj>foo</obj>, then <obj>bar</obj>'s
before-daemons run before any of those in <obj>foo</obj>, and <obj>bar</obj>'s
after-daemons run after any of those in <obj>foo</obj>.
</p>

<p>The reason for this order is to keep the modularity order correct.  If
we create <obj>flavor-1</obj> built on <obj>flavor-2</obj>, then it should not matter
what <obj>flavor-2</obj> is built out of.  Our new before-daemons go before all
methods of <obj>flavor-2</obj>, and our new after-daemons go after all methods of
<obj>flavor-2</obj>.  Note that if you have no daemons, this reduces to the
form of combination described above.  The most recently added component
flavor is the highest level of abstraction; you build a higher-level
object on top of a lower-level object by adding new components to the
front.  The syntax for defining daemon methods can be found in the
description of <obj>defmethod</obj> below.
</p>

<p>To make this a bit more clear, let's consider a simple example that is
easy to play with: the <obj>:print-self</obj> method.  The Lisp printer
(i.e. the <obj>print</obj> function; see <ref chapter="24" definition-in-file="rdprt" key="printer" section="1" title="What the Printer Produces" type="section"></ref>) prints instances of flavors by sending
them <obj>:print-self</obj> messages.  The first argument to the
<obj>:print-self</obj> operation is a stream (we can ignore the others for now),
and the receiver of the message is supposed to print its printed
representation on the stream.  In the <obj>ship</obj> example above, the reason
that instances of the <obj>ship</obj> flavor printed the way they did is
because the <obj>ship</obj> flavor was actually built on top of a very basic
flavor called <obj>vanilla-flavor</obj>; this component is provided
automatically by <obj>defflavor</obj>.  It was <obj>vanilla-flavor</obj>'s
<obj>:print-self</obj> method that was doing the printing.  Now, if we give
<obj>ship</obj> its own primary method for the <obj>:print-self</obj> operation, then
that method completely takes over the job of printing;
<obj>vanilla-flavor</obj>'s method will not be called at all.  However, if we
give <obj>ship</obj> a before-daemon method for the <obj>:print-self</obj> operation,
then it will get invoked before the <obj>vanilla-flavor</obj> method, and so
whatever it prints will appear before what <obj>vanilla-flavor</obj> prints.
So we can use before-daemons to add prefixes to a printed
representation; similarly, after-daemons can add suffixes.
</p>

<p>There are other ways to combine methods besides daemons, but this way is the
most common.  The more advanced ways of combining methods are explained
in a later section; see <ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="method-combination" section="11" title="Method Combination" type="section"></ref>.  <obj>vanilla-flavor</obj> and what it does for
you are also explained later; see <ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="vanilla-flavor" section="10" title="Vanilla Flavor" type="section"></ref>.
</p>
</section><a name="Flavor Functions"></a>

<section chapter-number="22" name="Flavor Functions" number="7" title="Flavor Functions"><definition>
<define key="defflavor-fun" name="defflavor" type="mac"></define>

<description>A flavor is defined by a form

<lisp>(defflavor <arg>flavor-name</arg> (<arg>var1</arg> <arg>var2</arg>...) (<arg>flav1</arg> <arg>flav2</arg>...)
        <arg>opt1</arg> <arg>opt2</arg>...)
</lisp><arg>flavor-name</arg> is a symbol which serves to name this flavor.  It is given an <obj>si:flavor</obj>
property which is the internal data-structure containing the details of the flavor.

<obj>(type-of <arg>obj</arg>)</obj>, where <arg>obj</arg> is an instance of the flavor named
<arg>flavor-name</arg>, returns the symbol <arg>flavor-name</arg>.
<obj>(typep <arg>obj</arg> <arg>flavor-name</arg>)</obj> is <obj>t</obj> if <arg>obj</arg> is an instance of a
flavor, one of whose components (possibly itself) is <arg>flavor-name</arg>.

<arg>var1</arg>, <arg>var2</arg>, etc. are the names of the instance-variables
containing the local state for this flavor.  A list of the name of an
instance-variable and a default initialization form is also acceptable;
the initialization form is evaluated when an instance of
the flavor is created if no other initial value for
the variable is obtained.  If no initialization is specified, the variable
remains void.

<arg>flav1</arg>, <arg>flav2</arg>, etc. are the names of the component flavors out of
which this flavor is built.  The features of those flavors are inherited
as described previously.

<arg>opt1</arg>, <arg>opt2</arg>, etc. are options; each option may be either a
keyword symbol or a list of a keyword symbol and arguments.  The options
to <obj>defflavor</obj> are described in <ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="defflavor-options" section="8" title="Defflavor Options" type="section"></ref>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="*all-flavor-names*-var" name="*all-flavor-names*" type="var"></define>

<description>A list of the names of all the flavors that have ever been <obj>defflavor</obj>'ed.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="defmethod-fun" name="defmethod" type="mac"></define>

<description>A method, that is, a function to handle a particular operation for instances
of a particular flavor, is defined by a form such as

<lisp>(defmethod (<arg>flavor-name</arg> <arg>method-type</arg> <arg>operation</arg>) <arg>lambda-list</arg>
  <arg>form1</arg> <arg>form2</arg>...)
</lisp><arg>flavor-name</arg> is a symbol which is the name of the flavor which is to
receive the method.
<arg>operation</arg> is a keyword symbol which names the operation
to be handled.  <arg>method-type</arg> is a keyword symbol for the type of method;
it is omitted when you are defining a primary method.  For some method-types,
additional information is expected.  It comes after <arg>operation</arg>.

The meaning of <arg>method-type</arg> depends on what style of
method combination is declared for this operation.  For instance, if
<obj>:daemon</obj> combination (the default style) is in use,
method types <obj>:before</obj> and <obj>:after</obj> are allowed.  See
<ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="method-combination" section="11" title="Method Combination" type="section"></ref> for a complete description of method types and
the way methods are combined.

<arg>lambda-list</arg> describes the arguments and aux variables of the
function; the first argument to the method, which is the operation
name itself, is automatically handled and so is not included in the
lambda-list.  Note that methods may not have unevaluated (<obj>&amp;quote</obj>) arguments;
that is, they must be functions, not special forms.  <arg>form1</arg>,
<arg>form2</arg>, etc. are the function body; the value of the last form
is returned.

The variant form

<lisp>(defmethod (<arg>flavor-name</arg> <arg>operation</arg>) <arg>function</arg>)
</lisp>where <arg>function</arg> is a symbol, says that <arg>flavor-name</arg>'s method for
<arg>operation</arg> is <arg>function</arg>, a symbol which names a function.  That
function must take appropriate arguments; the first argument is the
operation.  When the function is called, <obj>self</obj> will be bound.

If you redefine a method that is already defined, the old definition is
replaced by the new one.  Given a flavor, an operation name, and a
method type, there can only be one function (with the exception of
<obj>:case</obj> methods; see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="case-method-combination" type="page"></ref>), so if you define a <obj>:before</obj> daemon method for the
<obj>foo</obj> flavor to handle the <obj>:bar</obj> operation, then you replace the
previous before-daemon; however, you do not affect the primary method or
methods of any other type, operation or flavor.

The function spec for a method (see <ref chapter="12" definition-in-file="fd-fun" key="method-function-spec" section="2" title="Function Specs" type="section"></ref>) looks like:

<lisp>(:method <arg>flavor-name</arg> <arg>operation</arg>)  <standard>or</standard>
(:method <arg>flavor-name</arg> <arg>method-type</arg> <arg>operation</arg>)  <standard>or</standard>
(:method <arg>flavor-name</arg> <arg>method-type</arg> <arg>operation</arg> <arg>suboperation</arg>)
</lisp>This is useful to know if you want to trace (<ref definition-in-file="db-aid" key="trace-fun" title="Special Form trace" type="spec"></ref>), breakon
(<ref definition-in-file="db-aid" key="breakon-fun" title="Function breakon" type="fun"></ref>) or advise (<ref definition-in-file="db-aid" key="advise-fun" title="Macro advise" type="mac"></ref>) a method, or if you want to
poke around at the method function itself, e.g.  disassemble it
(see <ref definition-in-file="fd-hac" key="disassemble-fun" title="Function disassemble" type="fun"></ref>).
</description></definition><definition><define key="make-instance-fun" name="make-instance" type="fun"><args>flavor-name init-option1 value1 init-option2 value2... </args>
</define>

<description>Creates and returns an instance of the specified flavor.  Arguments
after the first are alternating init-option keywords and arguments to
those keywords.  These options are used to initialize instance variables
and to select arbitrary options, as described above.  An <obj>:init</obj>
message is sent to the newly-created object with one argument, the
init-plist.  This is a disembodied property-list containing the
init-options specified and those defaulted from the flavor's
<obj>:default-init-plist</obj> (however, init keywords that simply initialize instance
variables, and the corresponding values, may be absent when the
<obj>:init</obj> methods are called).  <obj>make-instance</obj> is an easy-to-call
interface to <obj>instantiate-flavor</obj>, below.

If <obj>:allow-other-keys</obj> is used as an init keyword
with a non-<obj>nil</obj> value, this error check is suppressed.
Then unrecognized keywords are simply ignored.  Example:

<lisp>(make-instance 'foo :lose 5 :allow-other-keys t)
</lisp>specifies the init keyword <obj>:lose</obj>, but prevents an error
should the keyword not be handled.
</description></definition><definition><define key="instantiate-flavor-fun" name="instantiate-flavor" type="fun"><args>flavor-name init-plist <standard>&amp;optional</standard> send-init-message-p return-unhandled-keywords area</args>
</define>

<description>This is an extended version of <obj>make-instance</obj>, giving you more features.
Note that it takes the <arg>init-plist</arg> as an individual argument, rather than taking a rest
argument of init options and values.

The <arg>init-plist</arg> argument must be a disembodied property list;
<obj>locf</obj> of a rest argument is satisfactory.  Beware!  This property list
can be modified; the properties from the default init plist are
<obj>putprop</obj>'ed on if not already present, and some <obj>:init</obj> methods
do explicit <obj>putprop</obj>'s onto the <arg>init-plist</arg>.

In the event that <obj>:init</obj> methods <obj>remprop</obj> properties already on
the <arg>init-plist</arg> (as opposed to simply doing <obj>get</obj> and <obj>putprop</obj>),
then the <arg>init-plist</arg> is <obj>rplacd</obj>'ed.  This means that the actual
supplied list of options is modified.  It also means that <obj>locf</obj> of a
rest argument does not work; the caller of <obj>instantiate-flavor</obj>
must copy its rest argument (e.g. with <obj>copylist</obj>); this is because
<obj>rplacd</obj> is not allowed on stack lists.

Do not use <obj>nil</obj> as the <arg>init-plist</arg> argument.  This would mean
to use the properties of the symbol <obj>nil</obj> as the init options.
If your goal is to have no init options, you must provide a property list
containing no properties, such as the list <obj>(nil)</obj>.

Here is the sequence of actions by which <obj>instantiate-flavor</obj> creates
a new instance:

First, the specified flavor's instantiation flavor function
(<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="instantiation-flavor-function" type="page"></ref>), if it exists, is called to determine
which flavor should actually be instantiated.  If there is no instantiation
flavor function, the specified flavor is instantiated.

If the flavor's method hash-table and other internal information have
not been computed or are not up to date, they are computed.  This may
take a substantial amount of time or even invoke the compiler, but
it happens only once for each time you define or redefine a particular flavor.

Next, the instance itself is created.  If the <arg>area</arg> argument is
specified, it is the number of an area in which to cons the instance;
otherwise the flavor's instance area function is called to choose an area
if there is one; otherwise, <obj>default-cons-area</obj> is used.  See
<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="instance-area-function" type="page"></ref>.

Then the initial values of the instance variables are computed.  If an
instance variable is declared inittable, and a keyword with the same
spelling as its name appears in <arg>init-plist</arg>, the property for that
keyword is used as the initial value.

Otherwise, if the default init plist specifies such a property, it is
evaluated and the value is used.  Otherwise, if the flavor definition
specifies a default initialization form, it is evaluated and the value
is used.  The initialization form may not refer to any instance
variables.  It can find the new instance in <obj>self</obj> but should not
invoke any operations on it and should not refer directly to any
instance variables.  It can get at instance variables using accessor
macros created by the <obj>:outside-accessible-instance-variables</obj> option
(<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="outside-accessible-instance-variables-option" type="page"></ref>) or the function
<obj>symeval-in-instance</obj> (<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="symeval-in-instance-fun" title="Function symeval-in-instance" type="fun"></ref>).

If an instance variable does not get initialized either of these ways it
is left void; an <obj>:init</obj> method may initialize it (see below).

All remaining keywords and values specified in the
<obj>:default-init-plist</obj> option to <obj>defflavor</obj>, that do not initialize
instance variables and are not overridden by anything explicitly specified
in <arg>init-plist</arg> are then merged into <arg>init-plist</arg> using <obj>putprop</obj>.
The default init plist of the instantiated flavor is considered first,
followed by those of all the component flavors in the standard order.
See <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="default-init-plist-option" type="page"></ref>.

Then keywords appearing in the <arg>init-plist</arg> but not defined with the
<obj>:init-keywords</obj> option or the <obj>:inittable-instance-variables</obj>
option for some component flavor are collected.  If the
<obj>:allow-other-keys</obj> option is specified with a non-<obj>nil</obj> value
(either in the original <arg>init-plist</arg> argument or by some default init
plist) then these <arg>unhandled</arg> keywords are ignored.  If the
<arg>return-unhandled-keywords</arg> argument is non-<obj>nil</obj>, a list of these
keywords is returned as the second value of <obj>instantiate-flavor</obj>.
Otherwise, an error is signaled if any unrecognized init keywords are
present.

If the <arg>send-init-message-p</arg> argument is supplied and non-<obj>nil</obj>, an
<obj>:init</obj> message is sent to the newly-created instance, with one
argument, the <arg>init-plist</arg>.  <obj>get</obj> can be used to extract options
from this property-list.  Each flavor that needs initialization can
contribute an <obj>:init</obj> method by defining a daemon.

The <obj>:init</obj> methods should not look on the <arg>init-plist</arg> for keywords
that simply initialize instance variables (that is, keywords defined
with <obj>:inittable-instance-variables</obj> rather than <obj>:init-keywords</obj>).
The corresponding instance variables are already set up when the
<obj>:init</obj> methods are called, and sometimes the keywords and their
values may actually be missing from the <arg>init-plist</arg> if it is more
efficient not to put them on.  To avoid problems, always refer to the
instance variables themselves rather than looking for the init keywords
that initialize them.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;all-method" name="&quot;all" type="metamethod"><args>flavor instances&quot; :init init-plist</args>
</define>

<description>This operation is implemented on all flavor instances.  Its purpose is to
examine the init keywords and perform whatever initializations are
appropriate.  <arg>init-plist</arg> is the argument that was given to
<obj>instantiate-flavor</obj>, and may be passed directly to <obj>get</obj>
to examine the value of any particular init option.

The default definition of this operation does nothing.  However,
many flavors add <obj>:before</obj> and <obj>:after</obj> daemons to it.
</description></definition><definition><define key="instancep-fun" name="instancep" type="fun"><args>object</args>
</define>

<description>Returns <obj>t</obj> if <obj>object</obj> is an instance.
This is equivalent to <obj>(typep <arg>object</arg> 'instance)</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="defwrapper-fun" name="defwrapper" type="mac"></define>

<description>This is hairy and if you don't understand it you should skip it.

Sometimes the way the flavor system combines the methods of different
flavors (the daemon system) is not powerful enough.  In that case <obj>defwrapper</obj>
can be used to define a macro that expands into code that is wrapped around
the invocation of the methods.  This is best explained by an example;
suppose you needed a lock locked during the processing of the
<obj>:foo</obj> operation on flavor <obj>bar</obj>, which takes two arguments,
and you have a <obj>lock-frobboz</obj> special-form that knows how to lock the lock
(presumably it generates an <obj>unwind-protect</obj>).  <obj>lock-frobboz</obj> needs to see
the first argument to the operation; perhaps that tells it what sort of operation
is going to be performed (read or write).

<lisp>(defwrapper (bar :foo) ((arg1 arg2) . body)
  `(lock-frobboz (self arg1)
     . ,body))
</lisp>The use of the <obj>body</obj> macro-argument prevents the macro defined by
<obj>defwrapper</obj> from knowing the exact implementation and allows
several <obj>defwrapper</obj>'s from different flavors to be combined
properly.

Note well that the argument variables, <obj>arg1</obj> and <obj>arg2</obj>, are not referenced
with commas before them.  These may look like <obj>defmacro</obj> ``argument'' variables,
but they are not.  Those variables are not bound at the time the <obj>defwrapper</obj>-defined
macro is expanded and the back-quoting is done; rather the result of that
macro-expansion and back-quoting is code which, when a message is sent, will
bind those variables to the arguments in the message as local variables of
the combined method.

Consider another example.  Suppose you thought you wanted a <obj>:before</obj> daemon,
but found that if the argument was <obj>nil</obj> you needed to return from processing
the message immediately, without executing the primary method.  You could write
a wrapper such as

<lisp>(defwrapper (bar :foo) ((arg1) . body)
  `(cond ((null arg1))
         (t (print &quot;About to do :FOO&quot;)
            . ,body)))
</lisp>
Suppose you need a variable for communication among the daemons for a particular
operation; perhaps the <obj>:after</obj> daemons need to know what the primary method did,
and it is something that cannot be easily deduced from just the arguments.  You
might use an instance variable for this, or you might create a special variable
which is bound during the processing of the operation and used free by the methods.

<lisp>(defvar *communication*)
(defwrapper (bar :foo) (ignore . body)
  `(let ((*communication* nil))
     . ,body))
</lisp>
Similarly you might want a wrapper that puts a <obj>catch</obj> around the processing
of an operation so that any one of the methods could throw out in the event of
an unexpected condition.

Like daemon methods, wrappers work in outside-in order; when you add a
<obj>defwrapper</obj> to a flavor built on other flavors, the new wrapper
is placed outside any wrappers of the component flavors.  However,
<arg>all</arg> wrappers happen before <arg>any</arg> daemons happen.  When the combined
method is built, the calls to the before-daemon methods, primary methods,
and after-daemon methods are all placed together, and then the wrappers
are wrapped around them.  Thus, if a component flavor defines a wrapper,
methods added by new flavors execute within that wrapper's context.

<obj>:around</obj> methods can do some of the same things that wrappers can.  See
<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="around-method-type" type="page"></ref>.  If one flavor defines both a wrapper and an
<obj>:around</obj> method for the same operation, the <obj>:around</obj> method is
executed inside the wrapper.

By careful about inserting the body into an internal lambda-expression
within the wrapper's code.  Doing so interacts with the internals of the
flavor system and requires knowledge of things not documented in the
manual in order to work properly.  It is much simpler to use an
<obj>:around</obj> method instead.
</description></definition><definition><define key="undefmethod-fun" name="undefmethod" type="mac"><args>(flavor [type] operation [suboperation])</args>
</define>


<description><lisp>(undefmethod (flavor :before :operation))
<exdent amount="96"><caption>removes the method created by </caption>(defmethod (flavor :before :operation) (<arg>args</arg>) ...)
</exdent></lisp>
To remove a wrapper, use <obj>undefmethod</obj> with <obj>:wrapper</obj> as the method type.

<obj>undefmethod</obj> is simply an interface to <obj>fundefine</obj>
(see <ref definition-in-file="fd-fun" key="fundefine-fun" title="Function fundefine" type="fun"></ref>) that accepts the same syntax as
<obj>defmethod</obj>.

If a file that used to contain a method definition is reloaded
and if that method no longer seems to have a definition in the file,
the user is asked whether to <obj>undefmethod</obj> that method.  This may be
important to enable the modified program to inherit the methods it is
supposed to inherit.  If the method in question has been redefined by some
other file, this is not done, the assumption being that the definition was
merely moved.
</description></definition><definition><define key="undefflavor-fun" name="undefflavor" type="fun"><args>flavor</args>
</define>

<description>Undefines flavor <arg>flavor</arg>.  All methods of the flavor are lost.
<arg>flavor</arg> and all flavors that depend on it are no longer valid to
instantiate.

If instances of the discarded definition exist, they continue to
use that definition.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="self-var" name="self" type="var"></define>

<description>When a message is sent to an object, the variable <obj>self</obj> is automatically
bound to that object, for the benefit of methods which want to manipulate
the object itself (as opposed to its instance variables).
</description></definition><definition><define key="funcall-self-fun" name="funcall-self" type="fun"><args>operation arguments...</args>
</define><define key="lexpr-funcall-self-fun" name="lexpr-funcall-self" type="fun"><args>operation arguments... list-of-arguments</args>
</define>

<description><obj>funcall-self</obj> is nearly equivalent to <obj>funcall</obj> with <obj>self</obj> as
the first argument.  <obj>funcall-self</obj> used to be faster, but now
<obj>funcall</obj> of <obj>self</obj> is just as fast.  Therefore, <obj>funcall-self</obj>
is obsolete.  It should be replaced with <obj>funcall</obj> or <obj>send</obj> of <obj>self</obj>.

Likewise, <obj>lexpr-funcall-self</obj> should be replaced with use of
<obj>lexpr-send</obj> to <obj>self</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="funcall-with-mapping-table-fun" name="funcall-with-mapping-table" type="fun"><args>function mapping-table <standard>&amp;rest</standard> arguments</args>
</define>

<description>Applies <arg>function</arg> to <arg>arguments</arg> with <obj>sys:self-mapping-table</obj>
bound to <arg>mapping-table</arg>.  This is faster than binding the variable
yourself and doing an ordinary <obj>funcall</obj>, because the system assumes
that the mapping table you specify is the correct one for <arg>function</arg>
to be run with.  However, if you pass the wrong mapping table, incorrect
execution will take place.

This function is used in the code for combined methods and is also useful
for the user in <obj>:around</obj> methods (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="around-method-type" type="page"></ref>).
</description></definition><definition><define key="lexpr-funcall-with-mapping-table-fun" name="lexpr-funcall-with-mapping-table" type="fun"><args>function mapping-table <standard>&amp;rest</standard> arguments</args>
</define>

<description>Applies <arg>function</arg> to <arg>arguments</arg> using <obj>lexpr-funcall</obj>, with
<obj>sys:self-mapping-table</obj> bound to <arg>mapping-table</arg>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="declare-flavor-instance-variables-fun" name="declare-flavor-instance-variables" type="mac"><args>(flavor) body...</args>
</define>

<description>Sometimes it is useful to have a function which is not itself a method, but
which is to be called by methods and wants to be able to access the
instance variables of the object <obj>self</obj>.  The form

<lisp>(declare-flavor-instance-variables (<arg>flavor-name</arg>)
  (defun <arg>function</arg> <arg>args</arg> <arg>body</arg>...))
</lisp>surrounds the function definition with a peculiar kind of declaration 
which makes the instance variables of flavor <arg>flavor-name</arg>
accessible by name.  Any kind of function definition is allowed;
it does not have to use <obj>defun</obj> per se.

If you call such a function when <obj>self</obj>'s value is an instance whose
flavor does not include <arg>flavor-name</arg> as a component, it is an error.

Cleaner than using <obj>declare-flavor-instance-variables</obj>, because it
does not involve putting anything around the function definition, is using
a local declaration.  Put <obj>(declare (:self-flavor <arg>flavorname</arg>))</obj> as
the first expression in the body of the function.  For example:

<lisp>(defun foo (a b)
  (declare (:self-flavor myobject))
  (+ a (* b speed)))
</lisp>(where <obj>speed</obj> is an instance variable of the flavor <obj>myobject</obj>)
is equivalent to

<lisp>(declare-flavor-instance-variables (myobject)
(defun foo (a b)
  (+ a (* b speed))))
</lisp></description></definition><definition><define key="with-self-variables-bound-fun" name="with-self-variables-bound" type="spec"><args>body...</args>
</define>

<description>Within the body of this special form, all of <obj>self</obj>'s instance
variables are bound as specials to the values inside <obj>self</obj>.
(Normally this is true only of those instance variables that are
specified in <obj>:special-instance-variables</obj> when <obj>self</obj>'s flavor was
defined.)  As a result, inside the body you can use <obj>set</obj>, <obj>boundp</obj>
and <obj>symeval</obj>, etc., freely on the instance variables of <obj>self</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="recompile-flavor-fun" name="recompile-flavor" type="fun"><args>flavor-name <standard>&amp;optional</standard> single-operation (use-old-combined-methods <obj>t</obj>) (do-dependents <obj>t</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>Updates the internal data of the flavor and any flavors that depend on it.
If <arg>single-operation</arg> is supplied non-<obj>nil</obj>, only the methods for that
operation are changed.  The system does this when you define a new method that
did not previously exist.
If <arg>use-old-combined-methods</arg> is <obj>t</obj>, then the existing combined
method functions are used if possible.  New ones are generated only
if the set of methods to be called has changed.  This
is the default.
If <arg>use-old-combined-methods</arg> is <obj>nil</obj>, automatically-generated functions
to call multiple methods or to contain code generated by wrappers are regenerated
unconditionally.
If <arg>do-dependents</arg> is <obj>nil</obj>, only the specific flavor you specified
is recompiled.  Normally all flavors that depend on it are also recompiled.

<obj>recompile-flavor</obj> affects only flavors that have already been compiled.
Typically this means it affects flavors that have been instantiated,
but does not bother with mixins (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="mixin-flavor" type="page"></ref>).
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="si:*dont-recompile-flavors*-var" name="si:*dont-recompile-flavors*" type="var"></define>

<description>If this variable is non-<obj>nil</obj>, automatic recompilation of combined methods
is turned off.

If you wish to make several changes each of which will cause recompilation
of the same combined methods, you can use this variable to speed things up by
making the recompilations happen only once.  Set the variable to <obj>t</obj>,
make your changes, and then set the variable back to <obj>nil</obj>.
Then use <obj>recompile-flavor</obj> to recompile whichever combined methods
need it.  For example:

<lisp>(setq si:*dont-recompile-flavors* t)
(undefmethod (tv:sheet :after :bar))
(defmethod (tv:sheet :before :bar) ...)
(setq si:*dont-recompile-flavors* nil)
(recompile-flavor 'tv:sheet :bar)
</lisp><obj>tv:sheet</obj> has very many dependents; <obj>recompile-flavor</obj> even once
takes painfully long.  It's nice to avoid spending the time twice.
</description></definition><definition><define key="compile-flavor-methods-fun" name="compile-flavor-methods" type="mac"><args>flavor...</args>
</define>

<description>The form <obj>(compile-flavor-methods <arg>flavor-name-1</arg>
<arg>flavor-name-2</arg>...)</obj>, placed in a file to be compiled, directs the
compiler to include the automatically-generated combined methods for the
named flavors in the resulting QFASL file, provided all of the necessary
flavor definitions have been made.  Furthermore, all internal data
structures needed to instantiate the flavor will be computed when the
QFASL file is loaded rather than waiting until the first attempt to
instantiate it.

This means that the combined methods get compiled at compile time and
the data structures get generated at load time, rather than both things
happening at run time.  This is a very good thing, since if the
the compiler must be invoked at run time, the program will be
slow the first time it is run.  (The compiler must be called in any case if
incompatible changes have been made, such as addition or deletion of
methods that must be called by a combined method.)

You should only use <obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> for flavors that are
going to be instantiated.  For a flavor that is never to be instantiated
(that is, a flavor that only serves to be a component of other flavors
that actually do get instantiated), it is a complete waste of time,
except in the unusual case where those other flavors can all inherit
the combined methods of this flavor instead of each one having its
own copy of a combined method which happens to be identical to the
others.  In this unusual case, you should use the <obj>:abstract-flavor</obj>
option in <obj>defflavor</obj> (<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="abstract-flavor-option" type="page"></ref>).

The <obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> forms should be compiled after all of
the information needed to create the combined methods is available.  You
should put these forms after all of the definitions of all relevant
flavors, wrappers, and methods of all components of the flavors mentioned.

The methods used by <obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> to form the combined
methods that go in the QFASL file are all those present in the file
being compiled and all those defined in the Lisp world.

When a <obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> form is seen by the interpreter,
the combined methods are compiled and the internal data structures
are generated.
</description></definition><definition><define key="get-handler-for-fun" name="get-handler-for" type="fun"><args>object operation</args>
</define>

<description>Given an object and an operation, this returns the object's method for that
operation, or <obj>nil</obj> if it has none.  When <arg>object</arg> is an instance of
a flavor, this function can be useful to find which of that flavor's
components supplies the method.  If you get back a combined method,
you can use the <obj>Meta-X List Combined Methods</obj> editor command (<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="list-combined-methods" type="page"></ref>)
to find out what it does.

This is related to the <obj>:handler</obj> function spec
(see <ref chapter="12" definition-in-file="fd-fun" key="function-spec" section="2" title="Function Specs" type="section"></ref>).

It is preferable to use the generic operation <obj>:get-handler-for</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="flavor-allows-init-keyword-p-fun" name="flavor-allows-init-keyword-p" type="fun"><args>flavor-name keyword</args>
</define>

<description>Returns non-<obj>nil</obj> if the flavor named <arg>flavor-name</arg> allows <arg>keyword</arg>
in the init options when it is instantiated, or <obj>nil</obj> if it does not.
The non-<obj>nil</obj> value is the name of the component flavor that contributes
the support of that keyword.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:flavor-all-allowed-init-keywords-fun" name="si:flavor-all-allowed-init-keywords" type="fun"><args>flavor-name</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a list of all the init keywords that may be used
in instantiating <arg>flavor-name</arg>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="symeval-in-instance-fun" name="symeval-in-instance" type="fun"><args>instance symbol <standard>&amp;optional</standard> no-error-p</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the value of the instance variable <arg>symbol</arg> inside
<arg>instance</arg>.  If there is no such instance variable, an error is
signaled, unless <arg>no-error-p</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj> in which case <obj>nil</obj>
is returned.
</description></definition><definition><define key="set-in-instance-fun" name="set-in-instance" type="fun"><args>instance symbol value</args>
</define>

<description>Sets the value of the instance variable <arg>symbol</arg> inside <arg>instance</arg>
to <arg>value</arg>.  If there is no such instance variable, an error is
signaled.
</description></definition><definition><define key="locate-in-instance-fun" name="locate-in-instance" type="fun"><args>instance symbol</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a locative pointer to the cell inside <arg>instance</arg> which holds the
value of the instance variable named <arg>symbol</arg>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="describe-flavor-fun" name="describe-flavor" type="fun"><args>flavor-name</args>
</define>

<description>Prints descriptive information about a flavor; it is self-explanatory.
An important thing it tells you that can be hard to figure out
yourself is the combined list of component flavors; this list is what
is printed after the phrase `and directly or indirectly depends on'.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="si:*flavor-compilations*-var" name="si:*flavor-compilations*" type="var"></define>

<description>Contains a history of when the flavor mechanism invoked
the compiler.  It is a list; elements toward the front of the list
represent more recent compilations.  Elements are typically of the
form

<lisp>(<arg>function-spec</arg> <arg>pathname</arg>)
</lisp>where the function spec starts with <obj>:method</obj> and has a method type of
<obj>:combined</obj>.

You may <obj>setq</obj> this variable to <obj>nil</obj> at any time; for instance before
loading some files that you suspect may have missing or obsolete
<obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> in them.
</description></definition><definition><define key="sys:unclaimed-message-condition" name="sys:unclaimed-message" type="condition"><args>(<obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This condition is signaled whenever a flavor instance is sent a message whose
operation it does not handle.  The condition instance supports these operations:

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:object</obj></td><td>The flavor instance that received the message.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:operation</obj></td><td>The operation that was not handled.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:arguments</obj></td><td>The list of arguments to that operation
</td></tr></tbody></table></description></definition></section><a name="defflavor-options"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="defflavor-options" number="8" title="Defflavor Options"><p>There are quite a few options to <obj>defflavor</obj>.  They are all described here,
although some are for very specialized purposes and not of interest to most users.
Each option can be written in two forms; either the keyword by itself, or a list
of the keyword and arguments to that keyword.
</p>

<p>Several of these options declare things about instance variables.
These options can be given with arguments which are instance variables,
or without any arguments in which case they refer to all of the
instance variables listed at the top of the <obj>defflavor</obj>.  This is
<arg>not</arg> necessarily all the instance variables of the component
flavors, just the ones mentioned in this flavor's <obj>defflavor</obj>.  When
arguments are given, they must be instance variables that were listed
at the top of the <obj>defflavor</obj>; otherwise they are assumed to be
misspelled and an error is signaled.  It is legal to declare things
about instance variables inherited from a component flavor, but to do
so you must list these instance variables explicitly in the instance
variable list at the top of the <obj>defflavor</obj>.
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:gettable-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":gettable-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
Enables automatic generation of methods for getting the values of
instance variables.  The operation name is the name of the variable, in
the keyword package (i.e. it has a colon in front of it).

Note that there is nothing special about these methods; you could easily
define them yourself.  This option generates them automatically to save
you the trouble of writing out a lot of very simple method definitions.
(The same is true of methods defined by the
<obj>:settable-instance-variables</obj> option.)  If you define a method for the
same operation name as one of the automatically generated methods, the
explicit definition overrides the automatic one.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:settable-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":settable-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
Enables automatic generation of methods for setting the values of
instance variables.  The operation name is `<obj>:set-</obj>' followed by the
name of the variable.  All settable instance
variables are also automatically made gettable and inittable.
(See the note in the description of the <obj>:gettable-instance-variables</obj>
option, above.)

In addition, <obj>:case</obj> methods are generated for the <obj>:set</obj> operation
with suboperations taken from the names of the variables, so that
<obj>:set</obj> can be used to set them.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:inittable-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":inittable-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
The instance variables listed as arguments, or all instance variables
listed in this <obj>defflavor</obj> if the keyword is given alone, are made
<arg>inittable</arg>.  This means that they can be initialized through use of a
keyword (a colon followed by the name of the variable) as an init-option
argument to <obj>make-instance</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:special-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":special-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
The instance variables listed as arguments, or all instance variables
listed in this <obj>defflavor</obj> if the keyword is given alone, will
be bound dynamically when handling messages.  (By default, instance
variables are bound lexically with the scope being the method.)
You must do this to any instance variables that you wish to be accessible
through <obj>symeval</obj>, <obj>set</obj>, <obj>boundp</obj> and <obj>makunbound</obj>, since they
see only dynamic bindings.

This should also be done for any instance variables that are declared
globally special.  If you omit this, the flavor system does it for
you automatically when you instantiate the flavor, and gives you a
warning to remind you to fix the <obj>defflavor</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:init-keywords</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":init-keywords defflavor"></index-entry>
The arguments are declared to be valid keywords to use in
<obj>instantiate-flavor</obj> when creating an instance of this flavor (or any
flavor containing it).  The system uses this for error-checking: before
the system sends the <obj>:init</obj> message, it makes sure that all the
keywords in the init-plist are either inittable instance variables or
elements of this list.  If any is not recognized, an error is signaled.
When you write a <obj>:init</obj> method that accepts some keywords, they
should be listed in the <obj>:init-keywords</obj> option of the flavor.

If <obj>:allow-other-keys</obj> is used as an init keyword
with a non-<obj>nil</obj> value, this error check is suppressed.
Then unrecognized keywords are simply ignored.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:default-init-plist</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":default-init-plist defflavor"></index-entry>
The arguments are alternating keywords and value forms, like a
property list.  When the flavor is instantiated, these properties and
values are put into the init-plist unless already present.  This allows
one component flavor to default an option to another component flavor.
The value forms are only evaluated when and if they are used.  For
example,

<lisp>(:default-init-plist :frob-array
                     (make-array 100))
</lisp>would provide a default ``frob array'' for any instance for which the
user did not provide one explicitly.


<lisp>(:default-init-plist :allow-other-keys t)
</lisp>prevents errors for unhandled init keywords in all instantiation
of this flavor and other flavors that depend on it.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:required-init-keywords defflavor</obj></td><td>The arguments are init keywords which are to be required each time
this flavor (or any flavor containing it) is instantiated.
An error is signaled if any required init keyword is missing.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:required-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":required-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
Declares that any flavor incorporating this one that is instantiated
into an object must contain the specified instance variables.
An error occurs if there is an attempt to instantiate a flavor that
incorporates this one if it does not have these in its set of instance
variables.  Note that this option is not one of those that checks
the spelling of its arguments in the way described at the start of this section
(if it did, it would be useless).

Required instance variables may be freely accessed by methods just like
normal instance variables.  The difference between listing instance
variables here and listing them at the front of the <obj>defflavor</obj> is
that the latter declares that this flavor ``owns'' those variables and
accepts responsibility for initializing them, while the former declares that this
flavor depends on those variables but that some other flavor must be
provided to manage them and whatever features they imply.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:required-methods</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":required-methods defflavor"></index-entry>
The arguments are names of operations that any flavor incorporating this
one must handle.  An error occurs if there is an attempt to instantiate
such a flavor and it is lacking a method for one of these operations.
Typically this option appears in the <obj>defflavor</obj> for a base flavor
(see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="base-flavor" type="page"></ref>).  Usually this is used when a base flavor does a
<obj>(send self ...)</obj> to send itself a message that is
not handled by the base flavor itself; the idea is that the base flavor
will not be instantiated alone, but only with other components (mixins)
that do handle the message.  This keyword allows the error of having no
handler for the message to be detected when the flavor instantiated or when
<obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> is done, rather than when the missing
operation is used.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:required-flavors</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":required-flavors defflavor"></index-entry>
The arguments are names of flavors that any flavor incorporating this one
must include as components, directly or indirectly.  The difference between
declaring flavors as required and listing them directly as components at the
top of the <obj>defflavor</obj> is that declaring flavors to be required does not make
any commitments about where those flavors will appear in the ordered list of
components; that is left up to whoever does specify them as components.
The purpose of declaring a flavor to be required is to allow
instance variables declared by that flavor to be accessed.  It also provides
error checking: an attempt to instantiate a flavor that does not include the
required flavors as components signals an error.  Compare this with
<obj>:required-methods</obj> and <obj>:required-instance-variables</obj>.

For an example of the use of required flavors, consider the <obj>ship</obj>
example given earlier, and suppose we want to define a <obj>relativity-mixin</obj>
which increases the mass dependent on the speed.  We might write,

<lisp>(defflavor relativity-mixin () (moving-object))
(defmethod (relativity-mixin :mass) ()
  (// mass (sqrt (- 1 (^ (// (send self :speed)
                             *speed-of-light*)
                         2)))))
</lisp>but this would lose because any flavor that had <obj>relativity-mixin</obj>
as a component would get <obj>moving-object</obj> right after it in its
component list.  As a base flavor, <obj>moving-object</obj> should be last
in the list of components so that other components mixed in can replace
its methods and so that daemon methods combine in the right order.
<obj>relativity-mixin</obj> has no business changing the order in which flavors
are combined, which should be under the control of its caller.  For example,

<lisp>(defflavor starship ()
           (relativity-mixin long-distance-mixin ship))
</lisp>puts <obj>moving-object</obj> last (inheriting it from <obj>ship</obj>).

So instead of the definition above we write,

<lisp>(defflavor relativity-mixin () ()
        (:required-flavors moving-object))
</lisp>which allows <obj>relativity-mixin</obj>'s methods to access <obj>moving-object</obj>
instance variables such as <obj>mass</obj> (the rest mass), but does not
specify any place for <obj>moving-object</obj> in the list of components.

It is very common to specify the <arg>base flavor</arg> of a mixin with the
<obj>:required-flavors</obj> option in this way.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:included-flavors</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":included-flavors defflavor"></index-entry>
The arguments are names of flavors to be included in this flavor.  The difference
between declaring flavors here and declaring them at the top of the <obj>defflavor</obj>
is that when component flavors are combined, if an included flavor is not specified
as a normal component, it is inserted into the list of components immediately after
the last component to include it.  Thus included flavors act like defaults.
The important thing is that if an included flavor <arg>is</arg> specified as a component,
its position in the list of components is completely controlled by that specification,
independently of where the flavor that includes it appears in the list.

<obj>:included-flavors</obj> and <obj>:required-flavors</obj> are used in similar ways; it would
have been reasonable to use <obj>:included-flavors</obj> in the <obj>relativity-mixin</obj>
example above.  The difference is that when a flavor is required but not given
as a normal component, an error is signaled, but when a flavor is included
but not given as a normal component, it is automatically inserted into the list
of components at a reasonable place.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:no-vanilla-flavor</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":no-vanilla-flavor defflavor"></index-entry>
Normally when a flavor is instantiated, the special flavor
<obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj> is included automatically at the end of its list of
components.  The vanilla flavor provides some default methods for the
standard operations which all objects are supposed to understand.  These
include <obj>:print-self</obj>, <obj>:describe</obj>, <obj>:which-operations</obj>, and several
other operations.  See <ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="vanilla-flavor" section="10" title="Vanilla Flavor" type="section"></ref>.

If any component of a flavor specifies the <obj>:no-vanilla-flavor</obj> option,
then <obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj> is not included in that flavor.  This option
should not be used casually.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:default-handler</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":default-handler defflavor"></index-entry>
The argument is the name of a function that is to be called to handle
any operation for which there is no method.  Its arguments are
the arguments of the <obj>send</obj> which invoked the operation,
including the operation name as the first argument.  Whatever values
the default handler returns are the values of the operation.

Default handlers can be inherited from component flavors.  If a flavor
has no default handler, any operation for which there is no method
signals a <obj>sys:unclaimed-message</obj> error.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:ordered-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":ordered-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
This option is mostly for esoteric internal system uses.
The arguments are names of instance variables which must appear first (and in this order)
in all instances of this flavor, or any flavor depending on this flavor.
This is used for instance variables that are specially known about by
microcode, and also in connection with the <obj>:outside-accessible-instance-variables</obj>
option.  If the keyword is given alone, the arguments default to the list
of instance variables given at the top of this <obj>defflavor</obj>.

Removing any of the <obj>:ordered-instance-variables</obj>, or changing their
positions in the list, requires that you recompile all methods that use
any of the affected instance variables.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:outside-accessible-instance-variables</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":outside-accessible-instance-variables defflavor"></index-entry>
The arguments are instance variables which are to be accessible from
outside of this flavor's methods.
A macro (actually a subst) is defined which takes an object of
this flavor as an argument and returns the value of the instance variable;
<obj>setf</obj> may be used to set the value of the instance variable.  The name
of the macro is the name of the flavor concatenated with a hyphen and the
name of the instance variable.  These macros are similar to the accessor
macros created by <obj>defstruct</obj> (see <ref chapter="21" definition-in-file="defstr" key="defstruct" section="0" title="Defstruct" type="section"></ref>.)

This feature works in two different ways, depending on whether the instance
variable has been declared to have a fixed slot in all instances, via the
<obj>:ordered-instance-variables</obj> option.

If the variable is not ordered, the position of its value cell in the
instance must be computed at run time.  This takes noticeable
time, although less than actually sending a message would take.  An
error is signaled if the argument to the accessor macro is
not an instance or is an instance that does not have an instance
variable with the appropriate name.  However, there is no error check
that the flavor of the instance is the flavor the accessor macro was
defined for, or a flavor built upon that flavor.  This error check
would be too expensive.

If the variable is ordered, the compiler compiles a call to
the accessor macro into a subprimitive which simply accesses that
variable's assigned slot by number.  This subprimitive is only three
or four times slower than <obj>car</obj>.  The only error-checking
performed is to make sure that the argument is really an instance
and is really big enough to contain that slot.  There is no check
that the accessed slot really belongs to an instance variable of
the appropriate name.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:accessor-prefix</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":accessor-prefix defflavor"></index-entry>
Normally the accessor macro created by the <obj>:outside-accessible-instance-variables</obj>
option to access the flavor <arg>f</arg>'s instance variable <arg>v</arg> is named <arg>f-v</arg>.
Specifying <obj>(:accessor-prefix get$)</obj> causes it to be named <obj>get$<arg>v</arg></obj> instead.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:alias-flavor</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":alias-flavor defflavor"></index-entry>
Marks this flavor as being an alias for another flavor.  This flavor
should have only one component, which is the flavor it is an alias for,
and no instance variables or other options.  No methods should be defined for it.

The effect of the <obj>:alias-flavor</obj> option is that an attempt to instantiate
this flavor actually produces an instance of the other flavor.  Without
this option, it would make an instance of this flavor, which might behave
identically to an instance of the other flavor.  <obj>:alias-flavor</obj> eliminates
the need for separate mapping tables, method tables, etc. for this flavor,
which becomes truly just another name for its component flavor.

The alias flavor and its base flavor are also equivalent when used as
an argument of <obj>subtypep</obj> or as the second argument of <obj>typep</obj>;
however, if the alias status of a flavor is changed, you must
recompile any code which uses it as the second argument to <obj>typep</obj>
in order for such code to function.

<obj>:alias-flavor</obj> is mainly useful for changing a flavor's name gracefully.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:abstract-flavor</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":abstract-flavor defflavor"></index-entry>
This option marks the flavor as one that is not supposed to be
instantiated (that is, is supposed to be used only as a component of other
flavors).  An attempt to instantiate the flavor signals an error.

It is sometimes useful to do <obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> on a flavor that
is not going to be instantiated, if the combined methods for this flavor
will be inherited and shared by many others.  <obj>:abstract-flavor</obj> tells
<obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> not to complain about missing required
flavors, methods or instance variables.  Presumably the flavors that
depend on this one and actually are instantiated will supply what is
lacking.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:method-combination</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":method-combination defflavor"></index-entry>
Specifies the method combination style to be used for certain
operations.
Each argument to this option is a list <obj>(<arg>style order operation1 operation2</arg>...)</obj>.
<arg>operation1</arg>, <arg>operation2</arg>, etc. are names of operations whose methods
are to be combined in the declared fashion.  <arg>style</arg> is a keyword that
specifies a style of combination; see <ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="method-combination" section="11" title="Method Combination" type="section"></ref>.  <arg>order</arg>
is a keyword whose interpretation is up to <arg>style</arg>; typically it is
either <obj>:base-flavor-first</obj> or <obj>:base-flavor-last</obj>.

Any component of a flavor may specify the type of method combination to
be used for a particular operation.  If no component specifies a style
of method combination, then the default style is used, namely
<obj>:daemon</obj>.  If more than one component of a flavor specifies the
combination style for a given operation, then they must agree on the
specification, or else an error is signaled.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:instance-area-function defflavor</obj></td><td>The argument is the name of a function to be used when this flavor is
instantiated, to determine which area to create the new instance in.
Use a function name rather than an explicit lambda expression.

<lisp>(:instance-area-function <arg>function-name</arg>)
</lisp>
When the instance area function is called, it is given the init plist as
an argument, and should return an area number or <obj>nil</obj> to use the
default.  Init keyword values can be accessed using <obj>get</obj> on the init
plist.

Instance area functions can be inherited from component flavors.
If a flavor does not have or inherit an instance area function,
its instances are created in <obj>default-cons-area</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:instantiation-flavor-function defflavor</obj></td><td>You can define a flavor <obj>foo</obj> so that, when you try to instantiate it,
it calls a function to decide what flavor it should really instantiate
(not necessarily <obj>foo</obj>).  This is done by giving <obj>foo</obj> an
instantiation flavor function:

<lisp>(:instantiation-flavor-function <arg>function-name</arg>)
</lisp>
When <obj>(make-instance 'foo <arg>keyword-args</arg>...)</obj> is done, the
instantiation flavor function is called with two arguments: the flavor
name specified (<obj>foo</obj> in this case) and the init plist (the list of
keyword args).  It should return the name of the flavor that should
actually be instantiated.

Note that the instantiation flavor function applies only to the flavor it is
specified for.  It is not inherited by dependent flavors.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:run-time-alternatives defflavor</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>:mixture defflavor</obj></td><td>A run-time-alternative flavor defines a collection of similar flavors,
all built on the same base flavor but having various mixins as well.
Instantiation chooses a flavor of the collection at run time based on
the init keywords specified, using an automatically generated
instantiation flavor function.

A simple example would be

<lisp>(defflavor foo () (basic-foo)
  (:run-time-alternatives
     (:big big-foo-mixin))
  (:init-keywords :big))
</lisp>
Then <obj>(make-instance 'foo :big t)</obj> makes an instance of a flavor
whose components are <obj>big-foo-mixin</obj> as well as <obj>foo</obj>.  But
<obj>(make-instance 'foo)</obj> or <obj>(make-instance 'foo :big nil)</obj> makes an
instance of <obj>foo</obj> itself.  The clause <obj>(:big big-foo-mixin)</obj> in the
<obj>:run-time-alternatives</obj> says to incorporate <obj>big-foo-mixin</obj> if
<obj>:big</obj>'s value is <obj>t</obj>, but not if it is <obj>nil</obj>.

There may be several clauses in the <obj>:run-time-alternatives</obj>.  Each
one is processed independently.  Thus, two keywords <obj>:big</obj> and
<obj>:wide</obj> could independently control two mixins, giving four
possibilities.

<lisp>(defflavor foo () (basic-foo)
  (:run-time-alternatives
     (:big big-foo-mixin)
     (:wide wide-foo-mixin))
  (:init-keywords :big))
</lisp>
It is possible to test for values other than <obj>t</obj> and <obj>nil</obj>.  The clause

<lisp>(:size (:big big-foo-mixin)
       (:small small-foo-mixin)
       (nil nil))
</lisp>allows the value for the keyword <obj>:size</obj> to be <obj>:big</obj>, <obj>:small</obj> or <obj>nil</obj> (or omitted).
If it is <obj>nil</obj> or omitted, no mixin is used (that's what the second <obj>nil</obj> means).
If it is <obj>:big</obj> or <obj>:small</obj>, an appropriate mixin is used.  This kind of clause
is distinguished from the simpler kind by having a list as its second element.
The values to check for can be anything, but <obj>eq</obj> is used to compare them.

The value of one keyword can control the interpretation of others
by nesting clauses within clauses.  If an alternative has more than two elements,
the additional elements are subclauses which are considered only if that
alternative is selected.  For example, the clause

<lisp>(:etherial (t etherial-mixin)
           (nil nil
                (:size (:big big-foo-mixin)
                       (:small small-foo-mixin)
                       (nil nil))))
</lisp>says to consider the <obj>:size</obj> keyword only if <obj>:etherial</obj> is <obj>nil</obj>.

<obj>:mixture</obj> is synonymous with <obj>:run-time-alternatives</obj>.  It exists
for compatibility with Symbolics systems.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:documentation</obj></td>
<td><index-entry index="keywords" title=":documentation defflavor"></index-entry>
Specifies the documentation string for the flavor definition, which is
made accessible through <obj>(documentation <arg>flavorname</arg> 'flavor)</obj>.

This documentation can be viewed with the <obj>describe-flavor</obj> function
(see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="describe-flavor-fun" title="Function describe-flavor" type="fun"></ref>) or the editor's <obj>Meta-X Describe Flavor</obj>
command (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="describe-flavor-command" type="page"></ref>).

Previously this option expected two arguments, a keyword and a string.
The keyword was intended to classify the flavor as a base flavor,
mixin or combination.  But no way was found for this classification
to serve a useful purpose.  Keyword are still accepted but no longer
recommended for use.

</td></tr></tbody></table></section><a name="Flavor Families"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Flavor Families" number="9" title="Flavor Families"><index-entry index="concepts" title="base-flavor"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="mixin"></index-entry>

<p>The following organization conventions are recommended for programs that use flavors.
</p>

<p>A <arg>base flavor</arg> is a flavor that defines a whole family of related flavors,
all of which have that base flavor as a component.
Typically the base flavor includes things relevant to the whole family,
such as instance variables, <obj>:required-methods</obj> and <obj>:required-instance-variables</obj>
declarations, default methods for certain operations, <obj>:method-combination</obj>
declarations, and documentation on the general protocols and conventions
of the family.  Some base flavors are complete and can be instantiated, but
most are not instantiatable and merely serve as a base upon which to build
other flavors.  The base flavor for the <arg>foo</arg> family is often named <obj>basic-<arg>foo</arg></obj>.
</p>

<p>A <arg>mixin flavor</arg> is a flavor that defines one particular feature of an object.
A mixin cannot be instantiated, because it is not a complete description.
Each module or feature of a program
is defined as a separate mixin; a usable flavor can be constructed by choosing
the mixins for the desired characteristics and combining them, along with the
appropriate base flavor.  By organizing your flavors this way, you keep separate
features in separate flavors, and you can pick and choose among them.
Sometimes the order of combining mixins does not matter,
but often it does, because the order of flavor combination controls the order
in which daemons are invoked and wrappers are wrapped.  Such order dependencies
should be documented as part of the conventions of the appropriate family of flavors.
A mixin flavor that provides the <arg>mumble</arg> feature is often named <arg>mumble<obj>-mixin</obj></arg>.
</p>

<p>If you are writing a program that uses someone else's facility to do something,
using that facility's flavors and methods, your program may still define
its own flavors, in a simple way.  The facility provides a base flavor and
a set of mixins: the caller can combine these in various ways depending
on exactly what it wants, since the facility probably does not provide all possible
useful combinations.  Even if your private flavor has exactly the
same components as a pre-existing flavor, it can still be useful since
you can use its <obj>:default-init-plist</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="default-init-plist-option" type="page"></ref>) to
select options of its component flavors and you can define one or two methods
to customize it ``just a little''.
</p>
</section><a name="vanilla-flavor"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="vanilla-flavor" number="10" title="Vanilla Flavor"><p>The operations described in this section are a standard protocol, which all
message-receiving objects are assumed to understand.  The standard methods
that implement this protocol are automatically supplied by the flavor
system unless the user specifically tells it not to do so.  These methods
are associated with the flavor <obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj>:
</p>
<definition>
<define key="si:vanilla-flavor-flavor" name="si:vanilla-flavor" type="flavor"></define>

<description>Unless you specify otherwise (with the <obj>:no-vanilla-flavor</obj> option to
<obj>defflavor</obj>), every flavor includes the ``vanilla'' flavor, which has no
instance variables but provides some basic useful methods.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":print-self-message" name=":print-self" type="message"><args>stream prindepth escape-p</args>
</define>

<description>The object should output its printed-representation to a stream.  The
printer sends this message when it encounters an instance or an entity.
The arguments are the stream, the current depth in list-structure (for
comparison with <obj>prinlevel</obj>), and whether escaping is enabled (a copy
of the value of <obj>*print-escape*</obj>; see <ref definition-in-file="rdprt" key="*print-escape*-var" title="Variable *print-escape*" type="var"></ref>).
<obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj> ignores the last two arguments and prints something like
<obj>#&lt;<arg>flavor-name octal-address</arg>&gt;</obj>.  The <arg>flavor-name</arg> tells you
what type of object it is and the <arg>octal-address</arg> allows you to tell
different objects apart (provided the garbage collector doesn't move
them behind your back).
</description></definition><definition>
<define key=":describe-message" name=":describe" type="message"></define>

<description>The object should describe itself, printing a description onto the
<obj>*standard-output*</obj> stream.  The <obj>describe</obj> function sends this
message when it encounters an instance.  <obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj>
outputs in a reasonable format the object, the name of its flavor, and
the names and values of its instance-variables.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":set-message" name=":set" type="message"><args>keyword value</args>
</define>

<description>The object should set the internal value specified by <arg>keyword</arg>
to the new value <arg>value</arg>.  For flavor instances, the <obj>:set</obj>
operation uses <obj>:case</obj> method combination, and a method is
generated automatically to set each settable instance variable,
with <arg>keyword</arg> being the variable's name as a keyword.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key=":which-operations-message" name=":which-operations" type="message"></define>

<description>The object should return a list of the operations it can handle.
<obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj> generates the list once per flavor and remembers
it, minimizing consing and compute-time.  If the set of operations
handled is changed, this list is regenerated the next time someone asks
for it.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":operation-handled-p-message" name=":operation-handled-p" type="message"><args>operation</args>
</define>

<description><arg>operation</arg> is an operation name.  The object should return <obj>t</obj> if it
has a handler for the specified operation, <obj>nil</obj> if it does not.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":get-handler-for-message" name=":get-handler-for" type="message"><args>operation</args>
</define>

<description><arg>operation</arg> is an operation name.
The object should return the method it uses to handle <arg>operation</arg>.
If it has no handler for that operation, it should return <obj>nil</obj>.
This is like the <obj>get-handler-for</obj> function (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="get-handler-for-fun" title="Function get-handler-for" type="fun"></ref>),
but, of course, you can use it only on objects known to accept messages.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":send-if-handles-message" name=":send-if-handles" type="message"><args>operation <standard>&amp;rest</standard> arguments</args>
</define>

<description><arg>operation</arg> is an operation name and <arg>arguments</arg> is a list of
arguments for the operation.  If the object handles the operation, it
should send itself a message with that operation and arguments, and
return whatever values that message returns.  If it doesn't handle the
operation it should just return <obj>nil</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":eval-inside-yourself-message" name=":eval-inside-yourself" type="message"><args>form</args>
</define>

<description>The argument is a form that is evaluated in an environment in which special
variables with the names of the instance variables are bound to the values
of the instance variables.  It works to <obj>setq</obj> one of these special variables;
the instance variable is modified.  This is intended to be used mainly
for debugging.
</description></definition><definition><define key=":funcall-inside-yourself-message" name=":funcall-inside-yourself" type="message"><args>function <standard>&amp;rest</standard> args</args>
</define>

<description><arg>function</arg> is applied to <arg>args</arg> in an environment in which special
variables with the names of the instance variables are bound to the values
of the instance variables.  It works to <obj>setq</obj> one of these special variables;
the instance variable is modified.  This is a way of allowing callers
to provide actions to be performed in an environment set up by the instance.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key=":break-message" name=":break" type="message"></define>

<description><obj>break</obj> is called in an environment in which special
variables with the names of the instance variables are bound to the values
of the instance variables.
</description></definition></section><a name="method-combination"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="method-combination" number="11" title="Method Combination"><index-entry index="concepts" title="method combination"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="combined method"></index-entry>

<p>When a flavor has or inherits more than one method for an operation,
they must be called in a specific sequence.
The flavor system creates a function called a <arg>combined method</arg>
which calls all the user-specified methods in the proper order.
Invocation of the operation actually calls the combined method,
which is responsible for calling the others.
</p>

<p>For example, if the flavor <obj>foo</obj> has components and methods as follows:
</p>

<lisp>(defflavor foo () (foo-mixin foo-base))
(defflavor foo-mixin () (bar-mixin))

(defmethod (foo :before :hack) ...)
(defmethod (foo :after :hack) ...)

(defmethod (foo-mixin :before :hack) ...)
(defmethod (foo-mixin :after :hack) ...)

(defmethod (bar-mixin :before :hack) ...)
(defmethod (bar-mixin :hack) ...)

(defmethod (foo-base :hack) ...)
(defmethod (foo-base :after :hack) ...)
</lisp><nopara></nopara>
<p>then the combined method generated looks like this (ignoring many
important details not related to this issue):
</p>

<lisp>(defmethod (foo :combined :hack) (&amp;rest args)
  (apply #'(:method foo :before :hack) args)
  (apply #'(:method foo-mixin :before :hack) args)
  (apply #'(:method bar-mixin :before :hack) args)
  (multiple-value-prog1
      (apply #'(:method bar-mixin :hack) args)
    (apply #'(:method foo-base :after :hack) args)
    (apply #'(:method foo-mixin :after :hack) args)
    (apply #'(:method foo :after :hack) args)))
</lisp>
<index-entry index="concepts" title="method types"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="untyped methods"></index-entry>

<p>This example shows the default style of method combination, the one
described in the introductory parts of this chapter, called <obj>:daemon</obj>
combination.  Each style of method combination defines which <arg>method types</arg>
it allows, and what they mean.  <obj>:daemon</obj> combination
accepts method types <obj>:before</obj> and <obj>:after</obj>,
in addition to <arg>untyped</arg> methods; then it creates a combined method which
calls all the <obj>:before</obj> methods, only one of the untyped methods, and
then all the <obj>:after</obj> methods, returning the value of the untyped
method.  The combined method is constructed by a function much like a
macro's expander function, and the precise technique used to create the
combined method is what gives <obj>:before</obj> and <obj>:after</obj> their meaning.
</p>

<p>Note that the <obj>:before</obj> methods are called in the order <obj>foo</obj>,
<obj>foo-mixin</obj>, <obj>bar-mixin</obj> and <obj>foo-base</obj>.  (<obj>foo-base</obj> does not
have a <obj>:before</obj> method, but if it had one that one would be last.)
This is the standard ordering of the components of the flavor <obj>foo</obj>
(see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="flavor-components" type="page"></ref>); since it puts the base flavor last, it is
called <obj>:base-flavor-last</obj> ordering.  The <obj>:after</obj> methods are
called in the opposite order, in which the base flavor comes first.
This is called <obj>:base-flavor-first</obj> ordering.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="primary method"></index-entry>

<p>Only one of the untyped methods is used; it is the one that comes first
in <obj>:base-flavor-last</obj> ordering.  An untyped method used in this way
is called a <arg>primary</arg> method.
</p>

<p>Other styles of method combination define their own method types
and have their own ways of combining them.  Use of another
style of method combination is requested with the <obj>:method-combination</obj> option to
<obj>defflavor</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="method-combination-option" type="page"></ref>).  Here is an example
which uses <obj>:list</obj> method combination, a style of combination
that allows <obj>:list</obj> methods and untyped methods:
</p>

<lisp>(defflavor foo () (foo-mixin foo-base))
(defflavor foo-mixin () (bar-mixin))
(defflavor foo-base () ()
  (:method-combination (:list :base-flavor-last :win)))

(defmethod (foo :list :win) ...)
(defmethod (foo :win) ...)

(defmethod (foo-mixin :list :win) ...)

(defmethod (bar-mixin :list :win) ...)
(defmethod (bar-mixin :win) ...)

(defmethod (foo-base :win) ...)

<exdent amount="96"><caption>yielding the combined method </caption>
(defmethod (foo :combined :win) (&amp;rest args)
  (list
    (apply #'(:method foo :list :win) args)
    (apply #'(:method foo-mixin :list :win) args)
    (apply #'(:method bar-mixin :list :win) args)
    (apply #'(:method foo :win) args)
    (apply #'(:method bar-mixin :win) args)
    (apply #'(:method foo-base :win) args)))
</exdent></lisp>
<p>The <obj>:method-combination</obj> option in the <obj>defflavor</obj> for <obj>foo-base</obj>
causes <obj>:list</obj> method combination to be used for the <obj>:win</obj>
operation on all flavors that have <obj>foo-base</obj> as a component,
including <obj>foo</obj>.  The result is a combined method which calls all the
methods, including all the untyped methods rather than just one, and
makes a list of the values they return.  All the <obj>:list</obj> methods are
called first, followed by all the untyped methods; and within each type,
the <obj>:base-flavor-last</obj> ordering is used as specified.  If the <obj>:method-combination</obj>
option said <obj>:base-flavor-first</obj>, the relative order of the <obj>:list</obj>
methods would be reversed, and so would the untyped methods, but
the <obj>:list</obj> methods would still be called before the untyped ones.
<obj>:base-flavor-last</obj> is more often right, since it means that
<obj>foo</obj>'s own methods are called first and <obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj>'s
methods (if it has any) are called last.
</p>

<p>A few specific method types, such as <obj>:default</obj> and <obj>:around</obj>, have
standard meanings independent of the style of method combination, and
can be used with any style.  They are described in a table below.
</p>

<p>Here are the standardly defined method combination styles.
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:daemon</obj></td><td>The default style of method combination.  All the <obj>:before</obj>
methods are called, then the primary (untyped) method for the outermost
flavor that has one is called, then all the <obj>:after</obj> methods are
called.  The value returned is the value of the primary method.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:daemon-with-or</obj></td><td>Like the <obj>:daemon</obj> method combination style, except that the primary
method is wrapped in an <obj>:or</obj> special form with all <obj>:or</obj> methods.
Multiple values can be returned from the primary method, but not from
the <obj>:or</obj> methods (as in the <obj>or</obj> special form).  This produces
code like the following in combined methods:

<lisp>(progn (foo-before-method)
       (multiple-value-prog1
         (or (foo-or-method)
             (foo-primary-method))
         (foo-after-method)))
</lisp>
This is useful primarily for flavors in which a mixin introduces an
alternative to the primary method.  Each <obj>:or</obj> method gets a chance
to run before the primary method and to decide whether the primary
method should be run or not; if any <obj>:or</obj> method returns a non-<obj>nil</obj>
value, the primary method is not run (nor are the rest of the <obj>:or</obj>
methods).  Note that the ordering of the combination of the <obj>:or</obj> methods
is controlled by the <arg>order</arg> keyword in the <obj>:method-combination</obj> option.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:daemon-with-and</obj></td><td>Like <obj>:daemon-with-or</obj> except that it combines <obj>:and</obj> methods
in an <obj>and</obj> special form.  The primary method is run only
if all of the <obj>:and</obj> methods return non-<obj>nil</obj> values.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:daemon-with-override</obj></td><td>Like the <obj>:daemon</obj> method combination style, except an <obj>or</obj>
special form is wrapped around the entire combined method with all
<obj>:override</obj> typed methods before the combined method.  This differs
from <obj>:daemon-with-or</obj> in that the <obj>:before</obj> and <obj>:after</obj> daemons
are run only if <arg>none</arg> of the <obj>:override</obj> methods returns
non-<obj>nil</obj>.  The combined method looks something like this:

<lisp>(or (foo-override-method)
    (progn (foo-before-method)
           (foo-primary-method)
           (foo-after-method)))
</lisp>
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:progn</obj></td><td>Calls all the methods inside a <obj>progn</obj> special form.  Only
untyped and <obj>:progn</obj> methods are allowed.  The combined method calls
all the <obj>:progn</obj> methods and then all the untyped methods.  The result
of the combined method is whatever the last of the methods returns.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:or</obj></td><td>Calls all the methods inside an <obj>or</obj> special form.  This means
that each of the methods is called in turn.  Only untyped methods and
<obj>:or</obj> methods are allowed; the <obj>:or</obj> methods are called first.  If a
method returns a non-<obj>nil</obj> value, that value is returned and none of
the rest of the methods are called; otherwise, the next method is
called.  In other words, each method is given a chance to handle the
message; if it doesn't want to handle the message, it can return
<obj>nil</obj>, and the next method gets a chance to try.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:and</obj></td><td>Calls all the methods inside an <obj>and</obj> special form.  Only
untyped methods and <obj>:and</obj> methods are allowed.  The basic idea is
much like <obj>:or</obj>; see above.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:append</obj></td><td>Calls all the methods and appends the values together.
Only untyped methods and <obj>:append</obj> methods are allowed; the
<obj>:append</obj> methods are called first.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:nconc</obj></td><td>Calls all the methods and <obj>nconc</obj>'s the values together.
Only untyped methods and <obj>:nconc</obj> methods are allowed, etc.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:list</obj></td><td>Calls all the methods and returns a list of their returned values.
Only untyped methods and <obj>:list</obj> methods are allowed, etc.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:inverse-list</obj></td><td>Calls each method with one argument; these arguments are successive
elements of the list that is the sole argument to the operation.
Returns no particular value.  Only untyped methods and <obj>:inverse-list</obj>
methods are allowed, etc.

If the result of a <obj>:list</obj>-combined operation is
sent back with an <obj>:inverse-list</obj>-combined operation, with the same
ordering and with corresponding method definitions, each component
flavor receives the value that came from that flavor.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:pass-on</obj></td><td>Calls each method on the values returned by the preceeding one.  The values
returned by the combined method are those of the outermost call.  The format
of the declaration in the <obj>defflavor</obj> is:

<lisp>(:method-combination (:pass-on (<arg>ordering</arg> . <arg>arglist</arg>))
                     . <arg>operation-names</arg>)
</lisp>
where <arg>ordering</arg> is <obj>:base-flavor-first</obj> or <obj>:base-flavor-last</obj>.
<arg>arglist</arg> may include the <obj>&amp;aux</obj> and <obj>&amp;optional</obj> keywords.

Only untyped methods and <obj>:pass-on</obj> methods are allowed.
The <obj>:pass-on</obj> methods are called first.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:case</obj></td><td>With <obj>:case</obj> method combination, the combined method automatically
does a <obj>selectq</obj> dispatch on the first argument of the operation,
known as the <arg>suboperation</arg>.  Methods of type <obj>:case</obj> can be used,
and each one specifies one suboperation that it applies to.  If no
<obj>:case</obj> method matches the suboperation, the primary method, if any,
is called.


<lisp><exdent amount="96"><caption>Example: </caption>(defflavor foo (a b) ()
  (:method-combination (:case :base-flavor-last :win)))

</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>This method handles <obj>(send a-foo :win :a)</obj>: </caption>(defmethod (foo :case :win :a) ()
  a)

</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>This method handles <obj>(send a-foo :win :a*b)</obj>: </caption>(defmethod (foo :case :win :a*b) ()
  (* a b))

</exdent><exdent amount="96"><caption>This method handles <obj>(send a-foo :win :something-else)</obj>: </caption>(defmethod (foo :win) (suboperation)
  (list 'something-random suboperation))
</exdent></lisp>
<obj>:case</obj> methods are unusual in that one flavor can have many <obj>:case</obj>
methods for the same operation, as long as they are for different
suboperations.

The suboperations <obj>:which-operations</obj>, <obj>:operation-handled-p</obj>,
<obj>:send-if-handles</obj> and <obj>:get-handler-for</obj> are all handled
automatically based on the collection of <obj>:case</obj> methods that are
present.

Methods of type <obj>:or</obj> are also allowed.  They are called just before
the primary method, and if one of them returns a non-<obj>nil</obj> value, that
is the value of the operation, and no more methods are called.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Here is a table of all the method types recognized by the standard
styles of method combination.
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj><standard>(no type)</standard></obj></td><td>If no type is given to <obj>defmethod</obj>, a primary method is created.
This is the most common type of method.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:before</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>:after</obj></td><td>Used for the before-daemon and after-daemon
methods used by <obj>:daemon</obj> method combination.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:default</obj></td><td>If there are no untyped methods among any of the flavors being combined,
then the <obj>:default</obj> methods (if any) are treated as if they were untyped.
If there are any untyped methods, the <obj>:default</obj> methods are ignored.

Typically a base-flavor (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="base-flavor" type="page"></ref>) defines some default
methods for certain of the operations understood by its family.  When
using the default kind of method combination these default methods are
suppressed if another component provides a primary method.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:or</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>:and</obj></td><td>Used for <obj>:daemon-with-or</obj> and <obj>:daemon-with-and</obj>
method combination.  The <obj>:or</obj> methods are wrapped in an <obj>or</obj>,
or the <obj>:and</obj> methods are wrapped in an <obj>and</obj>, together
with the primary method, between the <obj>:before</obj> and <obj>:after</obj> methods.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:override</obj></td><td>Allows the features of <obj>:or</obj> method combination to
be used together with daemons.  If you specify
<obj>:daemon-with-override</obj> method combination, you may use
<obj>:override</obj> methods.  The <obj>:override</obj> methods are executed first, until
one of them returns non-<obj>nil</obj>.  If this happens, that method's value(s)
are returned and no more methods are used.  If all the <obj>:override</obj>
methods return <obj>nil</obj>, the <obj>:before</obj>, primary and <obj>:after</obj> methods are
executed as usual.

In typical usages of this feature, the
<obj>:override</obj> method usually returns <obj>nil</obj> and does nothing,
but in exceptional circumstances it takes over the handling of the
operation.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:or<standard>, </standard>:and<standard>, </standard>:progn<standard>, </standard>:list<standard>, </standard>:inverse-list<standard>, </standard>pass-on<standard>, </standard>:append<standard>, </standard>:nconc<standard>.</standard></obj></td><td>Each of these methods types is allowed in the method combination style
of the same name.  In those method combination styles, these typed
methods work just like untyped ones, but all the typed methods are
called before all the untyped ones.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:case</obj></td><td><obj>:case</obj> methods are used by <obj>:case</obj> method combination.
</td></tr></tbody></table><nopara></nopara>
<p>These method types can be used with any method combination style; they
have standard meanings independent of the method combination style being
used.
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:around</obj></td><td>An <obj>:around</obj> method is able to control when, whether and how the
remaining methods are executed.  It is given a continuation that is a
function that will execute the remaining methods, and has complete
responsibility for calling it or not, and deciding what arguments to give
it.  For the simplest behavior, the arguments should be the operation name
and operation arguments that the <obj>:around</obj> method itself received; but
sometimes the whole purpose of the <obj>:around</obj> method is to modify the
arguments before the remaining methods see them.

The <obj>:around</obj> method receives three special arguments before the
arguments of the operation itself: the <arg>continuation</arg>, the
<arg>mapping-table</arg>, and the <arg>original-argument-list</arg>.  The last is a list
of the operation name and operation arguments.  The simplest way
for the <obj>:around</obj> method to invoke the remaining methods is to do

<lisp>(lexpr-funcall-with-mapping-table
  <arg>continuation</arg> <arg>mapping-table</arg>
  <arg>original-argument-list</arg>)
</lisp>In general, the <arg>continuation</arg> should be called with either
<obj>funcall-with-mapping-table</obj> or <obj>lexpr-funcall-with-mapping-table</obj>,
providing the <arg>continuation</arg>, the <arg>mapping-table</arg>, and the operation name
(which you know because it is the same as in the <obj>defmethod</obj>), followed
by whatever arguments the remaining methods are supposed to see.


<lisp>(defflavor foo-one-bigger-mixin () ())

(defmethod (foo-one-bigger-mixin :around :set-foo)
           (cont mt ignore new-foo)
  (funcall-with-mapping-table cont mt :set-foo
                              (1+ new-foo)))
</lisp>
is a mixin which modifies the <obj>:set-foo</obj> operation so that the value
actually used in it is one greater than the value specified in the message.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:inverse-around</obj></td><td><obj>:inverse-around</obj> methods work like <obj>:around</obj> methods, but they are
invoked at a different time and in a different order.

With <obj>:around</obj> methods, those of earlier flavor components components
are invoked first, starting with the instantiated flavor itself, and
those of earlier components are invoked within them.
<obj>:inverse-around</obj> methods are invoked in the opposite order:
<obj>si:vanilla-flavor</obj> would come first.  Also, all <obj>:around</obj> methods
and wrappers are invoked inside all the <obj>:inverse-around</obj> methods.

For example, the <obj>:inverse-around</obj> <obj>:init</obj> method for <obj>tv:sheet</obj> (a base
flavor for all window flavors) is used to handle the init keywords
<obj>:expose-p</obj> and <obj>:activate-p</obj>, which cannot be handled correctly
until the window is entirely set up.  They are handled in this method
because it is guaranteed to be the first method invoked by the <obj>:init</obj>
operation on any flavor of window (because no component of <obj>tv:sheet</obj>
defines an <obj>:inverse-around</obj> method for this operation).  All the rest
of the work of making a new window valid takes place in this method's
continuation; when the continuation returns, the window must be as valid
as it will ever be, and it is ready to be exposed or activated.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:wrapper</obj></td><td>Used internally by <obj>defwrapper</obj>.

Note that if one flavor defines both a wrapper and an <obj>:around</obj> method
for the same operation, the <obj>:around</obj> method is executed inside the
wrapper.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:combined</obj></td><td>Used internally for automatically-generated <arg>combined</arg> methods.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>The most common form of combination is <obj>:daemon</obj>.  One thing may not
be clear: when do you use a <obj>:before</obj> daemon and when do you use an <obj>:after</obj>
daemon?  In some cases the primary method performs a clearly-defined
action and the choice is obvious:  <obj>:before :launch-rocket</obj> puts in the
fuel, and <obj>:after :launch-rocket</obj> turns on the radar tracking.
</p>

<p>In other cases the choice can be less obvious.  Consider the <obj>:init</obj>
message, which is sent to a newly-created object.  To decide what kind
of daemon to use, we observe the order in which daemon methods are
called.  First the <obj>:before</obj> daemon of the instantiated flavor
is called, then <obj>:before</obj> daemons of successively more basic
flavors are called, and finally the <obj>:before</obj> daemon (if
any) of the base flavor is called.  Then the primary method is called.
After that, the <obj>:after</obj> daemon for the base flavor is
called, followed by the <obj>:after</obj> daemons at successively less
basic flavors.
</p>

<p>Now, if there is no interaction among all these methods, if their
actions are completely independent, then it doesn't matter whether you
use a <obj>:before</obj> daemon or an <obj>:after</obj> daemon.  There is a difference
if there is some interaction.  The interaction we are talking about is
usually done through instance variables; in general, instance variables
are how the methods of different component flavors communicate with each
other.  In the case of the <obj>:init</obj> operation, the <arg>init-plist</arg> can be
used as well.  The important thing to remember is that no method knows
beforehand which other flavors have been mixed in to form this flavor; a
method cannot make any assumptions about how this flavor has been
combined, and in what order the various components are mixed.
</p>

<p>This means that when a <obj>:before</obj> daemon has run, it must assume that
none of the methods for this operation have run yet.  But the <obj>:after</obj>
daemon knows that the <obj>:before</obj> daemon for each of the other flavors
has run.  So if one flavor wants to convey information to the other, the
first one should ``transmit'' the information in a <obj>:before</obj> daemon, and
the second one should ``receive'' it in an <obj>:after</obj> daemon.  So while
the <obj>:before</obj> daemons are run, information is ``transmitted''; that is,
instance variables get set up.  Then, when the <obj>:after</obj> daemons are
run, they can look at the instance variables and act on their values.
</p>

<p>In the case of the <obj>:init</obj> method, the <obj>:before</obj> daemons typically set up
instance variables of the object based on the init-plist, while the
<obj>:after</obj> daemons actually do things, relying on the fact that all of the
instance variables have been initialized by the time they are called.
</p>

<p>The problems become most difficult when you are creating a network of
instances of various flavors that are supposed to point to each other.
For example, suppose you have flavors for ``buffers'' and ``streams'', and
each buffer should be accompanied by a stream.  If you create the stream
in the <obj>:before</obj> <obj>:init</obj> method for buffers, you can inform the
stream of its corresponding buffer with an init keyword, but the stream
may try sending messages back to the buffer, which is not yet ready to
be used.  If you create the stream in the <obj>:after</obj> <obj>:init</obj> method
for buffers, there will be no problem with stream creation, but some
other <obj>:after</obj> <obj>:init</obj> methods of other mixins may have run and made
the assumption that there is to be no stream.  The only way to guarantee
success is to create the stream in a <obj>:before</obj> method and inform it of
its associated buffer by sending it a message from the buffer's
<obj>:after</obj> <obj>:init</obj> method.  This scheme--creating associated objects
in <obj>:before</obj> methods but linking them up in <obj>:after</obj> methods--often
avoids problems, because all the various associated objects used by
various mixins at least exist when it is time to make other objects
point to them.
</p>

<p>Since flavors are not hierarchically organized, the notion of
levels of abstraction is not rigidly applicable.  However, it remains a
useful way of thinking about systems.
</p>
</section><a name="Implementation of Flavors"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Implementation of Flavors" number="12" title="Implementation of Flavors"><p>An object that is an instance of a flavor is implemented using the
data type <obj>dtp-instance</obj>.  The representation is a structure whose
first word, tagged with <obj>dtp-instance-header</obj>, points to a structure
(known to the microcode as an ``instance descriptor'') containing the
internal data for the flavor.  The remaining words of the structure are value cells
containing the values of the instance variables.  The instance descriptor
is a <obj>defstruct</obj> that appears on the <obj>si:flavor</obj> property of the flavor
name.  It contains, among other things, the name of the flavor, the
size of an instance, the table of methods for handling operations, and
information for accessing the instance variables.
</p>

<p><obj>defflavor</obj> creates such a data structure for each flavor, and
links them together according to the dependency relationships
between flavors.
</p>

<p>A message is sent to an instance simply by calling it as a function,
with the first argument being the operation.
The microcode binds <obj>self</obj> to the object and binds those instance
variables that are supposed to be special to the value
cells in the instance.  Then it
passes on the operation and arguments to a funcallable hash table taken
from the flavor-structure for this flavor.
</p>

<p>When the funcallable hash table is called as a function, it hashes the
first argument (the operation) to find a function to handle the operation
and an array called a mapping table.  The variable
<obj>sys:self-mapping-table</obj> is bound to the mapping table, which tells
the microcode how to access the lexical instance variables, those not
defined to be special.  Then the function is called.  If there is only
one method to be invoked, this function is that method; otherwise it is
an automatically-generated function called the combined method (see
<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="combined-method" type="page"></ref>),
which calls the appropriate methods in the right order.
If there are wrappers, they are incorporated into this combined
method.
</p>

<p>The mapping table is an array whose elements correspond to the instance
variables which can be accessed by the flavor to which the currently
executing method belongs.  Each element contains the position in
<obj>self</obj> of that instance variable.  This position varies with the other
instance variables and component flavors of the flavor of <obj>self</obj>.
</p>

<p>Each time the combined method calls another method, it sets up the
mapping table required by that method--not in general the same
one which the combined method itself uses.  The mapping tables for the
called methods are extracted from the array leader of the mapping table
used by the combined method, which is kept in a local variable of the
combined method's stack frame while <obj>sys:self-mapping-table</obj> is set to
the mapping tables for the component methods.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="sys:self-mapping-table-var" name="sys:self-mapping-table" type="var"></define>

<description>Holds the current mapping table, which tells the running
flavor method where in <obj>self</obj> to find each instance variable.
</description></definition>
<p>Ordered instance variables are referred to directly without going
through the mapping table.  This is a little faster, and reduces the
amount of space needed for mapping tables.  It is also the reason why
compiled code contains the positions of the ordered instance variables
and must be recompiled when they change.
</p>



<subsection name="NIL" title="Order of Definition"><p>There is a certain amount of freedom to the order in which you do <obj>defflavor</obj>'s,
<obj>defmethod</obj>'s, and <obj>defwrapper</obj>'s.  This freedom is designed to make it easy
to load programs containing complex flavor structures without having to do things
in a certain order.  It is considered important that not all the methods for a flavor
need be defined in the same file.  Thus the partitioning of a program into files
can be along modular lines.
</p>

<p>The rules for the order of definition are as follows.
</p>

<p>Before a method can be defined (with <obj>defmethod</obj> or <obj>defwrapper</obj>) its flavor
must have been defined (with <obj>defflavor</obj>).  This makes sense because the system
has to have a place to remember the method, and because it has to know the
instance-variables of the flavor if the method is to be compiled.
</p>

<p>When a flavor is defined (with <obj>defflavor</obj>) it is not necessary that
all of its component flavors be defined already.  This is to allow
<obj>defflavor</obj>'s to be spread between files according to the modularity
of a program, and to provide for mutually-dependent flavors.
Methods can be defined for a flavor some of whose component flavors are
not yet defined; however, in certain cases compiling those methods may
produce a warning that an instance variable was declared
special (because the system did not realize it was an instance
variable).  If this happens, you should fix the problem and recompile.
</p>

<p>The methods automatically generated by the <obj>:gettable-instance-variables</obj>
and <obj>:settable-instance-variables</obj> <obj>defflavor</obj> options
(see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="gettable-instance-variables-option" type="page"></ref>) are generated at the time
the <obj>defflavor</obj> is done.
</p>

<p>The first time a flavor is instantiated, or when
<obj>compile-flavor-methods</obj> is done, the system looks through all of the
component flavors and gathers various information.  At this point an
error is signaled if not all of the components have been
<obj>defflavor</obj>'ed.  This is also the time at which certain other errors
are detected, for instance lack of a required instance-variable (see the
<obj>:required-instance-variables</obj> <obj>defflavor</obj> option,
<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="required-instance-variables-option" type="page"></ref>).  The combined methods (see
<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="combined-method" type="page"></ref>) are generated at this time also, unless they already
exist.
</p>

<p>After a flavor has been instantiated, it is possible to make changes to it.
Such changes affect all existing instances if possible.  This is
described more fully immediately below.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Changing a Flavor"><p>You can change anything about a flavor at any time.  You can change the
flavor's general attributes by doing another <obj>defflavor</obj> with the same
name.  You can add or modify methods by doing <obj>defmethod</obj>'s.  If you
do a <obj>defmethod</obj> with the same flavor-name, operation (and
suboperation if any), and (optional) method-type as an existing method,
that method is replaced by the new definition.  You can remove a
method with <obj>undefmethod</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="undefmethod-fun" title="Macro undefmethod" type="mac"></ref>).
</p>

<p>These changes always propagate to all flavors that depend upon the
changed flavor.  Normally the system propagates the changes to all
existing instances of the changed flavor and its dependent flavors.
However, this is not possible when the flavor has been changed so
drastically that the old instances would not work properly with the new
flavor.  This happens if you change the number of instance variables,
which changes the size of an instance.  It also happens if you change
the order of the instance variables (and hence the storage layout of an
instance), or if you change the component flavors (which can change
several subtle aspects of an instance).  The system does not keep a list
of all the instances of each flavor, so it cannot find the instances and
modify them to conform to the new flavor definition.  Instead it gives
you a warning message, on the <obj>*error-output*</obj> stream, to the effect
that the flavor was changed incompatibly and the old instances will not
get the new version.  The system leaves the old flavor data-structure
intact (the old instances continue to point at it) and makes a new
one to contain the new version of the flavor.  If a less drastic change
is made, the system modifies the original flavor data-structure, thus
affecting the old instances that point at it.  However, if you redefine
methods in such a way that they only work for the new version of the
flavor, then trying to use those methods with the old instances won't
work.
</p>
</subsection></section><a name="Useful Editor Commands"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Useful Editor Commands" number="13" title="Useful Editor Commands"><p>This section briefly documents
some editor commands that are useful in conjunction with flavors.
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>Meta-.</obj></td><td>The <obj>Meta-.</obj> (<obj>Edit Definition</obj>) command can find the definition of a flavor
in the same way that it can find the definition of a function.

<obj>Edit Definition</obj> can find the definition of a method if you give it
a suitable function spec starting with <obj>:method</obj>, such as <obj>(:method
tv:sheet :expose)</obj>.  The keyword <obj>:method</obj> may be omitted if the
definition is in the editor already.  Completion is available on the
flavor name and operation name, as usual only for definitions
loaded into the editor.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Describe Flavor</obj></td><td>Asks for a flavor name in the mini-buffer and describes its characteristics.
When typing the flavor name you have completion over the names of all defined
flavors (thus this command can be used to aid in guessing the name of a flavor).
The display produced is mouse sensitive where there are names of flavors and
of methods; as usual the right-hand mouse button gives you a menu of
editor commands to apply to the name
and the left-hand mouse button does one of them, typically positioning
the editor to the source code for that name.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X List Methods</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Edit Methods</obj></td><td>Asks you for an operation in the mini-buffer and lists all the flavors
that have a method for that operation.  You may type in the operation name,
point to it with the mouse, or let it default to the operation of the message
being sent by the Lisp form the cursor is on.  <obj>List Methods</obj>
produces a mouse-sensitive display allowing you to edit selected methods
or just to see which flavors have methods, while <obj>Edit Methods</obj> skips the
display and proceeds directly to editing the methods.

As usual with this type of command, the editor command <obj>Control-Shift-P</obj>
advances the editor cursor to the next method in the list, reading in
its source file if necessary.  Typing <obj>Control-Shift-P</obj>, while the display
is on the screen, edits the first method.

In addition, you can find a copy of the list in the editor buffer
<obj>*Possibilities*</obj>.  While in that buffer, the command <obj>Control-/</obj>
visits the definition of the method described on the line the cursor is
pointing at.

These techniques of moving through the objects listed apply to all the
following commands as well.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X List Combined Methods</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Edit Combined Methods</obj></td><td>Asks you for an operation name and a flavor in two mini-buffers and lists all
the methods that would be called to handle that operation for an instance of that
flavor.

<obj>List Combined Methods</obj> can be very useful for telling what a flavor
will do in response to a message.  It shows you the primary method,
the daemons, and the wrappers and lets you see the code for all of
them; type <obj>Control-Shift-P</obj> to get to successive ones.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X List Flavor Components</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Edit Flavor Components</obj></td><td>Asks you for a flavor and lists or begins visiting all the flavors it depends on.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X List Flavor Dependents</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Edit Flavor Dependents</obj></td><td>Asks you for a flavor and lists or begins visiting all the flavors that depend on it.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X List Flavor Direct Dependents</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Edit Flavor Direct Dependents</obj></td><td>Asks you for a flavor and lists or begins visiting all the flavors
that depend directly on it.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X List Flavor Methods</obj></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><obj>Meta-X Edit Flavor Methods</obj></td><td>Asks you for a flavor and lists or begins visiting all the methods defined
for that flavor.  (This does not include methods inherited from its component
flavors.)
</td></tr></tbody></table></section><a name="Property List Operations"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Property List Operations" number="14" title="Property List Operations"><p>It is often useful to associate a property list with an abstract object,
for the same reasons that it is useful to have a property list
associated with a symbol.  This section describes a mixin flavor that
can be used as a component of any new flavor in order to provide that
new flavor with a property list.  For more details and examples, see the
general discussion of property lists (<ref chapter="5" definition-in-file="fd-con" key="plist" section="10" title="Property Lists" type="section"></ref>).  The usual property
list functions (<obj>get</obj>, <obj>putprop</obj>, etc.) all work on instances by
sending the instance the corresponding message.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="si:property-list-mixin-flavor" name="si:property-list-mixin" type="flavor"></define>

<description>This mixin flavor provides the basic operations on property lists.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-get-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="get" type="method"><args>property-name <standard>&amp;optional</standard> default</args>
</define>

<description>Looks up the object's <arg>property-name</arg> property.
If it finds such a property, it returns the value; otherwise it
returns <arg>default</arg>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-getl-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="getl" type="method"><args>property-name-list</args>
</define>

<description>Like the <obj>:get</obj> operation, except that the
argument is a list of property names.  The <obj>:getl</obj> operation searches
down the property list until it finds a property whose property name is
one of the elements of <arg>property-name-list</arg>.  It returns the portion
of the property list begining with the first such property that it
found.  If it doesn't find any, it returns <obj>nil</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-putprop-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="putprop" type="method"><args>value property-name</args>
</define>

<description>Gives the object an <arg>property-name</arg> property of <arg>value</arg>.

<lisp>(send <arg>object</arg> :set :get <arg>property-name</arg> <arg>value</arg>)
</lisp>also has this effect.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-remprop-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="remprop" type="method"><args>property-name</args>
</define>

<description>Removes the object's <arg>property-name</arg> property, by splicing it out
of the property list.  It returns one of the cells spliced out, whose car
is the former value of the property that was just removed.  If there was
no such property to begin with, the value is <obj>nil</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-get-location-or-nil-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="get-location-or-nil" type="method"><args>property-name</args>
</define><define key="si:property-list-mixin-get-location-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="get-location" type="method"><args>property-name</args>
</define>

<description>Both return a locative pointer to the cell in which this object's
<arg>property-name</arg> property is stored.  If there is no such property,
<obj>:get-location-or-nil</obj> returns <obj>nil</obj>, but <obj>:get-location</obj>
adds a cell to the property list and initialized to <obj>nil</obj>, and a
pointer to that cell is returned.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-push-property-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="push-property" type="method"><args>value property-name</args>
</define>

<description>The <arg>property-name</arg> property of the object should be a list (note that
<obj>nil</obj> is a list and an absent property is <obj>nil</obj>).  This operation sets
the <arg>property-name</arg> property of the object to a list whose car is
<arg>value</arg> and whose cdr is the former <arg>property-name</arg> property of the
list.  This is analogous to doing

<lisp>(push <arg>value</arg> (get <arg>object</arg> <arg>property-name</arg>))
</lisp>See the <obj>push</obj> special form (<ref definition-in-file="fd-con" key="push-fun" title="Macro push" type="mac"></ref>).
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="si:property-list-mixin-property-list-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="property-list" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns the list of alternating property names and values that implements
the property list.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="si:property-list-mixin-property-list-location-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="property-list-location" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns a locative pointer to the cell in the instance which holds
the property list data.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-set-property-list-method" name="si:property-list-mixin" method-name="set-property-list" type="method"><args>list</args>
</define>

<description>Sets the list of alternating property names and values that implements
the property list to <arg>list</arg>.  So does

<lisp>(send <arg>object</arg> :set :property-list <arg>list</arg>)
</lisp></description></definition><definition><define key="si:property-list-mixin-initoption" name="si:property-list-mixin" type="initoption"><args>:property-list list</args>
</define>

<description>This initializes the list of alternating property names and values that implements
the property list to <arg>list</arg>.
</description></definition></section><a name="Printing Flavor Instances Readably"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="Printing Flavor Instances Readably" number="15" title="Printing Flavor Instances Readably"><p>A flavor instance can print out so that it can be read back in, as long
as you give it a <obj>:print-self</obj> method that produces a suitable
printed representation, and provide a way to parse it.  The convention
for doing this is to print as

<lisp>#<arg>flavor-name</arg> <arg>additional-data</arg>
</lisp>and make sure that the flavor defines or inherits a <obj>:read-instance</obj>
method that can parse the <arg>additional-data</arg> and return an instance
(see <ref definition-in-file="rdprt" key="horseshoe-read" type="page"></ref>).  A convenient way of doing this is to use
<obj>si:print-readably-mixin</obj>.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="si:print-readably-mixin-flavor" name="si:print-readably-mixin" type="flavor"></define>

<description>Provides for flavor instances to print out using the <obj>#</obj>
syntax, and also for reading things that were printed in that way.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="si:print-readably-mixin-reconstruction-init-plist-method" name="si:print-readably-mixin" method-name="reconstruction-init-plist" type="method"></define>

<description>When you use <obj>si:print-readably-mixin</obj>, you must define the operation
<obj>:reconstruction-init-plist</obj>.  This should return an alternating list
of init options and values that could be passed to <obj>make-instance</obj> to
create an instance ``like'' this one.  Sufficient similarity is defined
by the practical purposes of the flavor's implementor.
</description></definition></section><a name="io"></a>


<section chapter-number="22" name="io" number="16" title="Copying Instances"><p>Many people have asked ``How do I copy an instance?'' and have
expressed surprise when told that the flavor system does not
include any built-in way to copy instances.  Why isn't there
just a function <obj>copy-instance</obj> that creates a new instance
of the same flavor with all its instance variables having the same
values as in the original instance?  This would work for the
simplest use of flavors, but it isn't good enough for most
advanced uses of flavors.  A number of issues are raised by
copying:
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><standard>*</standard></td><td>Do you or do you not send an <obj>:init</obj> message to the new instance?
If you do, what init-plist options do you supply?

</td></tr><tr><td><standard>*</standard></td><td>If the instance has a property list, you should copy the property
list (e.g. with <obj>copylist</obj>) so that <obj>putprop</obj> or <obj>remprop</obj>
on one of the instances does not affect the properties of the
other instance.

</td></tr><tr><td><standard>*</standard></td><td>If the instance is a pathname, the concept of copying is not even meaningful.
Pathnames are <arg>interned</arg>, which means that there can only be one pathname
object with any given set of instance-variable values.

</td></tr><tr><td><standard>*</standard></td><td>If the instance is a stream connected to a network, some of the
instance variables represent an agent in another host elsewhere in the
network.  Should the copy talk to the same agent, or should a new
agent be constructed for it?

</td></tr><tr><td><standard>*</standard></td><td>If the instance is a stream connected to a file, should copying the
stream make a copy of the file or should it make another stream open
to the same file?  Should the choice depend on whether the file is
open for input or for output?
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>In general, you can see that in order to copy an instance one must understand
a lot about the instance.  One must know what the instance variables mean so
that the values of the instance variables can be copied if necessary.  One must
understand what relations to the external environment the instance has so
that new relations can be established for the new instance.  One must even
understand what the general concept `copy' means in the context of this
particular instance, and whether it means anything at all.
</p>

<p>Copying is a generic operation, whose implementation for a particular instance
depends on detailed knowledge relating to that instance.  Modularity dictates
that this knowledge be contained in the instance's flavor, not in a ``general
copying function''.  Thus the way to copy an instance is to send it a message,
as in <obj>(send object :copy)</obj>.  It is up to you to implement the
operation in a suitable fashion, such as

<lisp>(defflavor foo (a b c) ()
  (:inittable-instance-variables a b))

(defmethod (foo :copy) ()
  (make-instance 'foo :a a :b b))
</lisp></p>

<p>The flavor system chooses not to provide any default method for copying an
instance, and does not even suggest a standard name for the copying message,
because copying involves so many semantic issues.
</p>

<p>If a flavor supports the <obj>:reconstruction-init-plist</obj> operation, a
suitable copy can be made by invoking this operation and passing the
result to <obj>make-instance</obj> along with the flavor name.  This is
because the definition of what the <obj>:reconstruction-init-plist</obj>
operation should do requires it to address all the problems listed
above.  Implementing this operation is up to you, and so is making
sure that the flavor implements sufficient init keywords to transmit
any information that is to be copied.  See
<ref definition-in-file="flavor" key="si:print-readably-mixin-reconstruction-init-plist-method" title="Method si:print-readably-mixin :reconstruction-init-plist" type="method"></ref>.
</p>
</section></chapter>
</document-part>