<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part>
 <center>Preface to the Hypertext Edition</center>
 <p>
  This is the hypertext edition of the Lisp Machine Manual.  It
  describes the Lisp Machine system software, which had been
  developed between 1978 and 1984 at the MIT.
 </p>
 <p>
  This version of the manual is the result of automatically
  converting the source files of the printed 6th edition of the
  original manual, edited by Richard Stallman. The intention of the
  conversion is to bring the manual into a more modern format that
  could be read and edited using contemporary tools.  The goal is to
  make the Lisp Machine documentation widely available and editable.
 </p>
 <p>
  Originally, the manual was authored as text files with markup for
  the ``Bolio'' text processor, which ran on the PDP-10 systems and
  Lisp machines at the MIT in the 1980s.  Neither the source nor the
  documentation for Bolio were available at the time the conversion
  was done.  As such the meaning of the markup had to be deduced from
  the context and there may be errors or deficiencies in the hypertext
  edition that are a result of the conversion process.
 </p>
 <p>
  The conversion was done with slightly edited Bolio source files.
  The edits were done to correct problems introduced while converting
  the tape backups back to text files and slight structural changes to
  ease the conversion.  Additionally, the chapter on Resources has not
  been an own chapter in the printed 6th edition, but rather a section
  in the "Manipulating List Structure" chapter.  This presumably
  happened by accident.  The source was changed that so that
  "Resources" is now in it's own chapter.
 </p>
 <p>
  The hypertext edition of the manual consists of files in an XML
  format that resembles the original document stucture.  It does not
  use a well-known XML schema or DTD.  XSL templates are provided to
  convert the XML format to HTML for online browsing.  Conversion to
  other documentation formats like DocBook or Texinfo are possible,
  but the intention is to support these format in an output-only
  matter.
 </p>
 <p>
  If you have comments, bug reports or suggestions, please contact <a
  href="mailto:hans.huebner@gmail.com">Hans Hübner</a>.
 </p>
</document-part>