<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><a name="pathname-chapter"></a>
<chapter name="pathname-chapter" number="25" title="Naming of Files"><index-entry index="concepts" title="filename"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="pathname"></index-entry>

<p>A Lisp Machine generally has access to many file systems.  While it may
have its own file system on its own disks, usually a community of Lisp
Machine users want to have a shared file system accessible by any of the
Lisp Machines over a network.  These shared file systems can be
implemented by any computer that is capable of providing file system
service.  A file server computer may be a special-purpose computer that
does nothing but service file system requests from computers on a
network, or it may be a time-sharing system.
</p>

<p>Programs need to use names to designate files within these file systems.
The main difficulty in dealing with names of files is that different
file systems have different naming formats for files.  For example, in
the ITS file system, a typical name looks like:

<lisp>        DSK: GEORGE; FOO QFASL
</lisp>with <obj>DSK</obj> being a device name, <obj>GEORGE</obj> being a directory name, <obj>FOO</obj>
being the first file name and <obj>QFASL</obj> being the second file name.  However, in
TOPS-20, a similar file name is expressed as:

<lisp>        PS:&lt;GEORGE&gt;FOO.QFASL
</lisp>It would be unreasonable for each program that deals with file names to
be expected to know about each different file name format that exists, or
new formats that could get added in the future.  However, existing
programs should retain their abilities to manipulate the names.
</p>

<p>The functions and flavors described in this chapter exist to solve this
problem.  They provide an interface through which a program can deal with
names of files and manipulate them without depending on anything about
their syntax.  This lets a program deal with multiple remote file
servers simultaneously, using a uniform set of conventions.
</p>
<a name="Pathnames"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="Pathnames" number="1" title="Pathnames"><p>All file systems dealt with by the Lisp Machine are mapped into a common
model, in which files are named by something called a <arg>pathname</arg>.  A
pathname always has six components, each with a standard meaning.  These
components are the common interface that allows programs to work the
same way with different file systems; the mapping of the pathname
components into the concepts peculiar to each file system is taken care
of by the pathname software.  Pathname components are described in the
following section, and the mappings between components and user syntax
is described for each file system later in this chapter.
</p>
<definition><define key="pathnamep-fun" name="pathnamep" type="fun"><args>object</args>
</define>

<description><obj>t</obj> if <arg>object</arg> is a pathname.
</description></definition>
<p>A pathname is an instance of a flavor (see <ref chapter="22" definition-in-file="flavor" key="flavor" section="0" title="Objects, Message Passing, and Flavors" type="section"></ref>); exactly which
flavor depends on what the host of the pathname is, but <obj>pathname</obj>
is always one of its component flavors.  If <arg>p</arg> is a pathname, then
<obj>(typep <arg>p</arg> 'pathname)</obj> returns <obj>t</obj>.  One of the messages
handled by host objects is the <obj>:pathname-flavor</obj> operation, which
returns the name of the flavor to use for pathnames on that host.  And
one of the differences between host flavors is how they handle this
operation.
</p>

<p>There are functions for manipulating pathnames, and there are also
messages that can be sent to them.  These are described later in this
chapter.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="parse (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="merge (pathname)"></index-entry>

<p>Two important operations of the pathname system are <arg>parsing</arg> and <arg>merging</arg>.
Parsing is the conversion of a string--which might be something typed in by the
user when asked to supply the name of a file--into a pathname object.  This involves
finding out what host the pathname is for, then using the file name syntax
conventions of that host to parse the string into the standard pathname components.
Merging is the operation that takes a pathname with missing components and
supplies values for those components from a set of defaults.
</p>

<p>The function <obj>string</obj>, applied to a pathname, converts it into a
string that is in the file name syntax of its host's file system, except
that the name of the host followed by a colon is inserted at the front.
This is the inverse of parsing.  <obj>princ</obj> of a pathname also does this,
then prints the contents of the string.  Flavor operations such as
<obj>:string-for-dired</obj> exist which convert all or part of a pathname to a
string in other fashions that are designed for specific applications.
<obj>prin1</obj> of a pathname prints the pathname using the <example>#⊂</example> syntax so
it can be read back in to produce an equivalent pathname (or the same
pathname, if read in the same session).
</p>

<p>Since each kind of file server can have its own character string
representation of names of its files, there has to be a different parser
for each of these representations, capable of examining such a character
string and figuring out what each component is.  The parsers all work
differently.  How can the parsing operation know which parser to use?
The first thing that the parser does is to figure out which host this
filename belongs to.  A filename character string may specify a host
explicitly by having the name of the host, followed by a colon, at
either the beginning or the end of the string.  For example, the following
strings all specify hosts explicitly:

<lisp>AI: COMMON; GEE WHIZ            ;<standard> This specifies host AI.</standard>
COMMON; GEE WHIZ AI:            ;<standard> So does this.</standard>
AI: ARC: USERS1; FOO BAR        ;<standard> So does this.</standard>
ARC: USERS1; FOO BAR AI:        ;<standard> So does this.</standard>
EE:PS:&lt;COMMON&gt;GEE.WHIZ.5        ;<standard> This specifies host EE.</standard>
PS:&lt;COMMON&gt;GEE.WHIZ.5 EE:       ;<standard> So does this.</standard>
</lisp>If the string does not specify a host explicitly, the parser chooses a
host by default and uses the syntax for that host.  The optional
arguments passed to the parsing function (<obj>fs:parse-pathname</obj>) tell it
which host to assume.  Note: the parser is not confused by strings
starting with <obj>DSK:</obj> or <obj>PS:</obj> because it knows that neither of
those is a valid host name.  But if the default host has a device whose
name happens to match the name of some host, you can prevent the device
name from being misinterpreted as a host name by writing an extra colon
at the beginning of the string: For example, <obj>:EE:&lt;RMS&gt;FOO.BAR</obj> refers
to the device <obj>EE</obj> on the default host (assumed to use TOPS-20 syntax)
rather than to the host named <obj>EE</obj>.
</p>

<p>Pathnames are kept unique, like symbols, so that there is only one
object with a given set of components.  This is useful because a
pathname object has a property list (see <ref chapter="5" definition-in-file="fd-con" key="plist" section="10" title="Property Lists" type="section"></ref>) on which you can
store properties describing the file or family of files that the
pathname represents.  The uniqueness implies that each time the same
components are typed in, the program gets the same pathname object
and finds there the properties it ought to find.
</p>

<p>Note that a pathname is not necessarily the name of a specific file.  Rather,
it is a way to get to a file; a pathname need not correspond to any file that
actually exists, and more than one pathname can refer to the same file.  For
example, the pathname with <obj>:newest</obj> as its version refers to the same file
as a pathname which has the appropriate number as the version.
In systems with links, multiple file names, logical devices, etc., two pathnames
that look quite different may really turn out to address the same file.
To get from a pathname to a file requires doing a file system operation
such as <obj>open</obj>.
</p>

<p>When you want to store properties describing an individual file,
use the pathname you get by sending <obj>:truename</obj> to a stream rather
than the pathname you open.  This avoids problems with different pathnames
that refer to the same file.
</p>

<p>To get a unique pathname object representing a family of files, send the
message <obj>:generic-pathname</obj> to a pathname for any file in the family
(see <ref chapter="25" definition-in-file="pathnm" key="generic-pathname" section="5" title="Generic Pathnames" type="section"></ref>).
</p>
</section><a name="canonical-types"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="canonical-types" number="2" title="Pathname Components"><index-entry index="concepts" title="host (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="device (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="directory (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="name (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="type (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="version (pathname)"></index-entry>

<p>These are the components of a pathname.  They are clarified by an example below.

<table><tbody><tr><td><arg>host</arg></td><td>An object that represents the file system machine on which the file
resides.  A host object is an instance of a flavor one of whose
components is <obj>si:basic-host</obj>.  The precise flavor varies depending on the type
of file system and how the files are to be accessed.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>device</arg></td><td>Corresponds to the ``device'' or ``file structure'' concept in many host file systems.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>directory</arg></td><td>The name of a group of related files belonging to a single user or project.
Corresponds to the ``directory'' concept in many host file systems.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>name</arg></td><td>The name of a group of files that can be thought of as conceptually the
``same'' file.  Many host file systems have a concept of ``name'' which maps
directly into this component.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>type</arg></td><td>Corresponds to the ``filetype'' or ``extension'' concept in many host file systems.
This says what kind of file this is; such as, a Lisp source file, a QFASL file, etc.

</td></tr><tr><td><arg>version</arg></td><td>Corresponds to the ``version number'' concept in many host file systems.
This is a number that increments every time the file is modified.
Some host systems do not support version numbers.
</td></tr></tbody></table></p>

<p>As an example, consider a Lisp program named <obj>CONCH</obj>.  If it belongs
to <obj>GEORGE</obj>, who uses the <obj>FISH</obj> machine, the host would be the
host-object for the machine <obj>FISH</obj>, the device would probably be the default
and the directory would be <obj>GEORGE</obj>.  On this directory
would be a number of files related to the <obj>CONCH</obj> program.  The source
code for this program would live in a set of files with name <obj>CONCH</obj>,
type <obj>LISP</obj>, and versions <obj>1</obj>, <obj>2</obj>, <obj>3</obj>, etc.  The compiled form
of the program would live in files named <obj>CONCH</obj> with type <obj>QFASL</obj>;
each would have the same version number as the source file that it came
from.  If the program had a documentation file, it would have type
<obj>INFO</obj>.
</p>

<p>Not all of the components of a pathname need to be specified.  If a
component of a pathname is missing, its value is <obj>nil</obj>.  Before a file
server can do anything interesting with a file, such as opening the
file, all the missing components of a pathname must be filled in from
defaults.  But pathnames with missing components are often handed around
inside the machine, since almost all pathnames typed by users do not
specify all the components explicitly.  The host is not allowed to be
missing from any pathname; since the behavior of a pathname is
host-dependent to some extent, it has to know what its host is.  All
pathnames have host attributes, even if the string being parsed does not
specify one explicitly.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="unspecific pathname components"></index-entry>

<p>A component of a pathname can also be the special symbol
<obj>:unspecific</obj>.  <obj>:unspecific</obj> means, explicitly, ``this component has
been specified as missing'', whereas <obj>nil</obj> means that the component was
not specified and should default.  In merging, <obj>:unspecific</obj> counts as
a specified component and is not replaced by a default.  <obj>:unspecific</obj>
does <arg>not</arg> mean ``unspecified''; it is unfortunate that those two words
are similar.
</p>

<p><obj>:unspecific</obj> is used in <arg>generic</arg> pathnames, which refer not to a
file but to a whole family of files.  The version, and usually the type,
of a generic pathname are <obj>:unspecific</obj>.  Another way <obj>:unspecific</obj>
is used has to do with mapping of pathnames into file systems such as
ITS that do not have all six components.  A component that is really ``not
there'' is <obj>:unspecific</obj> in the pathname.  When a pathname is
converted to a string, <obj>nil</obj> and <obj>:unspecific</obj> both cause the
component not to appear in the string.
</p>

<p>A component of a pathname can also be the special symbol <obj>:wild</obj>.  This is
useful only when the pathname is being used with a directory primitive such
as <obj>fs:directory-list</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="files" key="fs:directory-list-fun" title="Function fs:directory-list" type="fun"></ref>), where it means that this pathname component matches
anything.  The printed representation of a pathname usually designates
<obj>:wild</obj> with an asterisk; however, this is host-dependent.
</p>

<p>What values are allowed for components of a pathname depends, in general,
on the pathname's host.  However, in order for pathnames to be usable
in a system-independent way certain global conventions are adhered to.
These conventions are stronger for the type and version than for the
other components, since the type and version are actually understood by
many programs, while the other components are usually just treated as something
supplied by the user that only needs to be remembered.
</p>

<p>In general, programs can interpret the components of a pathname
independent of the file system; and a certain minimum set of possible
values of each component are supported on all file systems.  The
same pathname component value may have very different representations
when the pathname is made into a string, depending on the file system.
This does not affect programs that operate on the components.  The user,
when asked to type a pathname, always uses the system-dependent string
representation.  This is convenient for the user who moves between using
the Lisp Machine on files stored on another host and making direct use of that
host.  However, when the mapping between string form and components is
complicated, the components may not be obvious from what you type.
</p>

<p>The type is always a string, or one of the special symbols <obj>nil</obj>,
<obj>:unspecific</obj>, and <obj>:wild</obj>.  Certain hosts impose a limit on the
size of string allowed, often very small.  Many programs that deal with
files have an idea of what type they want to use.  For example, Lisp
source programs are usually <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj>, compiled Lisp programs are
<obj>&quot;QFASL&quot;</obj>, etc.  However, these file type conventions are
host-specific, for the important reason that some hosts do not allow a
string five characters long to be used as the type.  Therefore, programs
should use a <arg>canonical type</arg> rather than an actual string to specify
their conventional default file types.  Canonical types are described below.
</p>

<p>For the version, it is always legitimate to use a positive fixnum, or
certain special symbols.  <obj>nil</obj>, <obj>:unspecific</obj>, and <obj>:wild</obj> have
been explained above.  The other standardly allowed symbols are
<obj>:newest</obj> and <obj>:oldest</obj>.  <obj>:newest</obj> refers to the largest version
number that exists when reading a file, or that number plus one when
writing a new file.  <obj>:oldest</obj> refers to the smallest version number
that exists.  Some file systems may define other special version
symbols, such as <obj>:installed</obj> for example, or may allow negative
numbers.  Some do not support versions at all.  Then a pathname may still
contain any of the standard version components, but it does not matter
what the value is.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="structured pathname components"></index-entry>

<p>The device, directory, and name are more system-dependent.  These can be strings
(with host-dependent rules on allowed characters and length) or they can
be <arg>structured</arg>.  A structured component is a list of strings.  This
is used for file system features such as hierarchical directories.  The system is
arranged so that programs do not need to know about structured components
unless they do host-dependent operations.  Giving a string as a pathname component
to a host that wants a structured value converts the string to the appropriate
form.  Giving a structured component to a host that does not understand them
converts it to a string by taking the first element and ignoring the rest.
</p>

<p>Some host file systems have features that do not fit into this pathname
model.  For instance, directories might be accessible as files, there
might be complicated structure in the directories or names, or there
might be relative directories, such as `&lt;' in Multics.  These features
appear in the parsing of strings into pathnames, which is one reason why
the strings are written in host-dependent syntax.  Pathnames for hosts with
these features are also likely to handle additional messages besides the
common ones documented in this chapter, for the benefit of
host-dependent programs that want to access those features.  However,
once your program depends on any such features, it will
work only for certain file servers and not others; in general, it is a good
idea to make your program work just as well no matter what file server
is being used.
</p>



<subsection name="NIL" title="Raw Components and Interchange Components"><index-entry index="concepts" title="interchange form of pathname components"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="raw pathname components"></index-entry>

<p>On some host file systems it is conventional to use lower-case letters
in file names, while in others upper case is customary, or possibly
required.  When pathname components are moved from pathnames of one file
system to pathnames of another file system, it is useful to convert the
case if necessary so that you get the right case convention for the
latter file system as a default.  This is especially useful when copying
files from one file system to another.
</p>

<p>The Lisp Machine system defines two representations for each of several
pathname components (the device, directory, name and type).  There is
the <arg>raw</arg> form, which is what actually appears in the filename on the
host file system, and there is the <arg>interchange</arg> form, which may
differ in alphabetic case from the raw form.  The raw form is what is
stored inside the pathname object itself, but programs nearly always
operate on the interchange form.  The <obj>:name</obj>, <obj>:type</obj>, etc.,
operations return the interchange form, and the <obj>:new-name</obj>, etc.,
operations expect the interchange form.  Additional operations
<obj>:raw-name</obj>, etc., are provided for working with the raw components,
but these are rarely needed.
</p>

<p>The interchange form is defined so that it is always customarily in
upper case.  If upper case is customary on the host file system, then
the interchange form of a component is the same as the raw form.  If
lower case is customary on the host file system, as on Unix, then the
interchange form has case inverted.  More precisely, an all-upper-case
component is changed to all-lower-case, an all-lower-case component is
changed to all-upper-case, and a mixed-case component is not changed.
(This is a one-to-one mapping).  Thus, a Unix pathname with a name
component of <obj>&quot;foo&quot;</obj> has an interchange-format name of
<obj>&quot;FOO&quot;</obj>, and vice versa.
</p>

<p>For host file systems which record case when files are created but
ignore case when comparing filenames, the interchange form is always
upper case.
</p>

<p>The host component is not really a name, and case is always ignored in
host names, so there is no need for two forms of host component.  The
version component does not need them either, because it is never a string.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="NIL" title="Pathname Component Operations"><definition>
<define key="pathname-host-method" name="pathname-host-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-device-method" name="pathname-device-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-directory-method" name="pathname-directory-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-name-method" name="pathname-name-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-type-method" name="pathname-type-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-version-method" name="pathname-version-method" type="method"></define>

<description>These return the components of the pathname, in interchange form.  The
returned values can be strings, special symbols, or lists of strings in
the case of structured components.  The type is always a string or
a symbol.  The version is always a number or a symbol.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-raw-device-method" name="pathname-raw-device-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-raw-directory-method" name="pathname-raw-directory-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-raw-name-method" name="pathname-raw-name-method" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-raw-type-method" name="pathname-raw-type-method" type="method"></define>

<description>These return the components of the pathname, in raw form.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-new-device-method" name="pathname-new-device-method" type="method"><args>dev</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-directory-method" name="pathname-new-directory-method" type="method"><args>dir</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-name-method" name="pathname-new-name-method" type="method"><args>name</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-type-method" name="pathname-new-type-method" type="method"><args>type</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-version-method" name="pathname-new-version-method" type="method"><args>version</args>
</define>

<description>These return a new pathname that is the same as the pathname they are
sent to except that the value of one of the components has been changed.
The specified component value is interpreted as being in interchange
form, which means its case may be converted.  The <obj>:new-device</obj>,
<obj>:new-directory</obj> and <obj>:new-name</obj> operations accept a string (or a
special symbol) or a list that is a structured name.  If the host does
not define structured components, and you specify a list, its first
element is used.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-new-raw-device-method" name="pathname-new-raw-device-method" type="method"><args>dev</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-raw-directory-method" name="pathname-new-raw-directory-method" type="method"><args>dir</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-raw-name-method" name="pathname-new-raw-name-method" type="method"><args>name</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-raw-type-method" name="pathname-new-raw-type-method" type="method"><args>type</args>
</define>

<description>These return a new pathname that is the same as the pathname they are
sent to except that the value of one of the components has been changed.
The specified component value is interpreted as raw.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-new-suggested-name-method" name="pathname-new-suggested-name-method" type="method"><args>name</args>
</define><define key="pathname-new-suggested-directory-method" name="pathname-new-suggested-directory-method" type="method"><args>dir</args>
</define>

<description>These differ from the <obj>:new-name</obj> and <obj>:new-directory</obj> operations in
that the new pathname constructed has a name or directory based on the
suggestion, but not necessarily identical to it.  It tries, in a
system-dependent manner, to adapt the suggested name or directory to the
usual customs of the file system in use.

For example, on a TOPS-20 system, these operations would convert
<arg>name</arg> or <arg>dir</arg> to upper case, because while lower-case letters
<arg>may</arg> appear in TOPS-20 pathnames, it is not customary to generate
such pathnames by default.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-new-pathname-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args><standard>&amp;rest</standard> options</args>
</define>

<description>This returns a new pathname that is the same as the pathname it is sent
to except that the values of some of the components have been changed.
<arg>options</arg> is a list of alternating keywords and values.  The keywords
all specify values of pathname components; they are <obj>:host</obj>,
<obj>:device</obj>, <obj>:directory</obj>, <obj>:name</obj>, <obj>:type</obj>, and <obj>:version</obj>.
Alternatively, the keywords <obj>:raw-device</obj>, <obj>:raw-directory</obj>,
<obj>:raw-name</obj> and <obj>:raw-type</obj> may be used to specify a component in
raw form.

Two additional keywords, <obj>:canonical-type</obj> and <obj>:original-type</obj>,
allow the type field to be specified as a canonical type.  See the
following section for a description of canonical types.  Also, the value
specified for the keyword <obj>:type</obj> may be a canonical type symbol.

If an invalid component is specified, it is replaced by some valid
component so that a valid pathname can be returned.  You can tell
whether a component is valid by specifying it in <obj>:new-pathname</obj>
and seeing whether that component of the resulting pathname
matches what you specified.

The operations <obj>:new-name</obj>, etc., are equivalent to <obj>:new-pathname</obj>
specifying only one component to be changed; in fact, that is how those
operations are implemented.
</description></definition></subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Canonical Types"><index-entry index="concepts" title="canonical type (of a pathname)"></index-entry>

<p><arg>Canonical types</arg> are a way of specifying a pathname type component
using host-dependent conventions without making the program itself
explicitly host dependent.  For example, the function <obj>compile-file</obj>
normally provides a default type of <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj>, but on VMS systems the
default must be <obj>&quot;LSP&quot;</obj> instead, and on Unix systems it is <obj>&quot;l&quot;</obj>.
What <obj>compile-file</obj> actually does is to use a canonical type, the keyword
<obj>:lisp</obj>, as the default.  This keyword is given a definition as a
canonical type, which specifies what it maps into on various file
systems.
</p>

<p>A single canonical type may have more than one mapping on a particular
file system.  For example, on TOPS-20 systems the canonical type
<obj>:LISP</obj> maps into either <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj> or <obj>&quot;LSP&quot;</obj>.  One of the
possibilities is marked as ``preferred''; in this case, it is <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj>.
The effect of this is that either <obj>FOO.LISP</obj> or <obj>FOO.LSP</obj> would be
acceptable as having canonical type <obj>:lisp</obj>, but merging
yields <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj> as the type when defaulting from <obj>:lisp</obj>.
</p>

<p>Note that the canonical type of a pathname is not a distinct component.
It is another way of describing or specifying the type component.
</p>

<p>A canonical type must be defined before it is used.
</p>
<definition><define key="fs:define-canonical-type-fun" name="fs:define-canonical-type" type="mac"><args>symbol standard-mapping system-dependent-mappings...</args>
</define>

<description>Defines <arg>symbol</arg> as a canonical type.  <arg>standard-mapping</arg> is the
actual type component that it maps into (a string), with exceptions as
specified by <arg>system-dependent-mappings</arg>.  Each element of
<arg>system-dependent-mappings</arg> (that is, each additional argument) is a list of the form

<lisp>(<arg>system-type</arg> <arg>preferred-mapping</arg> <arg>other-mappings</arg>...)
</lisp><arg>system-type</arg> is one of the system-type keywords the <obj>:system-type</obj>
operation on a host object can return, such as <obj>:unix</obj>, <obj>:tops20</obj>,
and <obj>:lispm</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="si:host-alist-var" title="Variable si:host-alist" type="var"></ref>).  The argument describes how
to map this canonical type on that type of file system.
<arg>preferred-map</arg> (a string) is the preferred mapping of the canonical
type, and <arg>other-mappings</arg> are additional strings that are accepted as
matching the canonical type.

<arg>system-type</arg> may also be a list of system types.  Then the argument
applies to all of those types of file systems.

All of the mapping strings are in interchange form.

For example, the canonical type <obj>:lisp</obj> is defined as follows:

<lisp>(fs:define-canonical-type :lisp &quot;LISP&quot;
  (:unix &quot;L&quot; &quot;LISP&quot;)
  (:vms &quot;LSP&quot;)
  ((:tops20 :tenex) &quot;LISP&quot; &quot;LSP&quot;))
</lisp>
Other canonical types defined by the system include <obj>:qfasl</obj>,
<obj>:text</obj>, <obj>:press</obj>, <obj>:qwabl</obj>, <obj>:babyl</obj>, <obj>:mail</obj>, <obj>:xmail</obj>,
<obj>:init</obj>, <obj>:patch-directory</obj>, <obj>:midas</obj>, <obj>:palx</obj>, <obj>:unfasl</obj>,
<obj>:widths</obj>, <obj>:output</obj>, <obj>mac</obj>, <obj>tasm</obj>, <obj>doc</obj>, <obj>mss</obj>, <obj>tex</obj>,
<obj>pl1</obj> and <obj>clu</obj>.  The standard mapping for each is the symbol's
pname.
</description></definition>
<p>To match a pathname against a canonical type, use the <obj>:canonical-type</obj> operation.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="pathname-canonical-type-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns two values which describe whether and how this pathname's type
component matches any canonical type.

If the type component is one of the possible mappings of some canonical
type, the first value is that canonical type (the symbol).  The second
value is <obj>nil</obj> if the type component is the preferred mapping of the
canonical type; otherwise it is the actual type component, in
interchange form.  The second value is called the <arg>original type</arg> of
the pathname.

If the type component does not match a canonical type, the first value is the
type component in interchange form (a string), and the second value is <obj>nil</obj>.

This operation is useful in matching a pathname against a canonical
type; the first value is <obj>eq</obj> to the canonical type if the pathname
matches it.  The operation is also useful for transferring a type field
from one file system to another while preserving canonical type; this is
described below.
</description></definition>
<p>A new pathname may also be constructed by specifying a canonical type.
</p>
<definition><define key="pathname-new-canonical-type-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>canonical-type <standard>&amp;optional</standard> original-type</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a pathname different from this one in having a type component
that matches <arg>canonical-type</arg>.

If <arg>original-type</arg> is a possible mapping for <arg>canonical-type</arg> on
this pathname's host, then it is used as the type component.  Otherwise,
the preferred mapping for <arg>canonical-type</arg> is used.  If
<arg>original-type</arg> is not specified, it defaults to this pathname's type
component.  If it is specified as <obj>nil</obj>, the preferred mapping of the
canonical type is always used.  If <arg>canonical-type</arg> is a string rather
than an actual canonical type, it is used directly as the type
component, and the <arg>original-type</arg> does not matter.

The <obj>:new-pathname</obj> operation accepts the keywords <obj>:canonical-type</obj>
and <obj>:original-type</obj>.  The <obj>:new-canonical-type</obj> operation is
equivalent to <obj>:new-pathname</obj> with those keywords.
</description></definition>
<p>Suppose you wish to copy the file named <arg>old-pathname</arg> to a directory
named <arg>target-directory-pathname</arg>, possibly on another host, while
preserving the name, version and canonical type.  That is, if the original file
has a name acceptable for a QFASL file, the new file should also.
Here is how to compute the new pathname:

<lisp>(multiple-value-bind (canonical original)
    (send old-pathname :canonical-type)
  (send target-directory-pathname :new-pathname 
        :name (send old-pathname :name)
        :version (send old-pathname :version)
        :canonical-type canonical
        :original-type original))
</lisp></p>

<p>Suppose that <arg>old-pathname</arg> is <obj>OZ:&lt;FOO&gt;A.LISP.5</obj>, where <obj>OZ</obj> is a
TOPS-20, and the target directory is on a VMS host.  Then <obj>canonical</obj> is
<obj>:lisp</obj> and <obj>original</obj> is <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj>.  Since <obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj> is
not an acceptable mapping for <obj>:lisp</obj> on a VMS system, the resulting pathname
has as its type component the preferred mapping for <obj>:lisp</obj> on VMS,
namely, <obj>&quot;LSP&quot;</obj>.
</p>

<p>But if the target host is a Unix host, the new file's type is
<obj>&quot;LISP&quot;</obj>, since that is an acceptable (though not preferred) mapping
for <obj>:lisp</obj> on Unix hosts.
If you would rather that the preferred mapping always be used for the
new file's type, omit the <obj>:original-type</obj> argument to the
<obj>:new-pathname</obj> operation.  This would result in a type component of
<obj>&quot;L&quot;</obj> in interchange form, or <obj>&quot;l&quot;</obj> in raw form, in the new file's pathname.
</p>

<p>The function <obj>compile-file</obj> actually does something cleverer than using the
canonical type as a default.  Doing that, and opening the resulting
pathname, would look only for the preferred mapping of the canonical
type.  <obj>compile-file</obj> actually tries to open <arg>each</arg> possible mapping,
trying the preferred mapping first.  Here is how it does so:
</p>
<definition><define key="pathname-open-canonical-default-type-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>canonical-type <standard>&amp;rest</standard> options</args>
</define>

<description>If this pathname's type component is non-<obj>nil</obj>, the pathname is simply
opened, passing the <arg>options</arg> to the <obj>:open</obj> operation.  If the type
component is <obj>nil</obj>, each mapping of <arg>canonical-type</arg> is tried as a
type component, in the order the mappings appear in the canonical type
definition.  If an open succeeds, a stream is returned.  The
possibilities continue to be tried as long as <obj>fs:file-not-found</obj>
errors happen; other errors are not handled.  If all the possibilities fail,
a <obj>fs:file-not-found</obj> error is signaled for the caller, with a pathname
that contains the preferred mapping as its type component.
</description></definition></subsection></section><a name="Defaults and Merging"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="Defaults and Merging" number="3" title="Defaults and Merging"><index-entry index="concepts" title="default (pathname)"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="merge (pathname)"></index-entry>

<p>When the user is asked to type in a pathname, it is of course unreasonable
to require the user to type a complete pathname, containing all components.
Instead there are defaults, so that components not specified by the user can
be supplied automatically by the system.  Each program that deals with pathnames
typically has its own set of defaults.
</p>

<p>The system defines an object called a <arg>defaults alist</arg>.  Functions are
provided to create one, get the default pathname out of one, merge a pathname
with one, and store a pathname back into one.  A defaults alist can remember
more than one default pathname if defaults are being kept separately for
each host; this is controlled by the variable <obj>fs:*defaults-are-per-host*</obj>.
The main primitive for using defaults is the function
<obj>fs:merge-pathname-defaults</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="fs:merge-pathname-defaults-fun" title="Function fs:merge-pathname-defaults" type="fun"></ref>).
</p>

<p>In place of a defaults alist, you may use just a pathname.  Defaulting one
pathname from another is useful for cases such as a program that has an input
file and an output file, and asks the user for the name of both, letting
the unsupplied components of one name default from the other.  Unspecified
components of the output pathname come from the input pathname, except
that the type should default not to the type of the input but to the appropriate
default type for output from this program.
</p>

<p>The implementation of a defaults alist is an association list of host names
and default pathnames.  The host name <obj>nil</obj> is special and holds the
defaults for all hosts, when defaults are not per-host.
</p>

<p>The <arg>merging</arg> operation takes as input a pathname, a defaults alist
(or another pathname), a default type, and a default version, and returns a
pathname.  Basically, the missing components in the pathname are filled
in from the defaults alist.  However, if a name is specified but the
type or version is not, then the type or version is treated specially.
</p>

<p>Here are the merging rules in full detail.
</p>

<p>If no host is specified, the host is taken from the defaults.  If the
pathname explicitly specifies a host and does not supply a device, then
the the default file device for that host is used.
</p>

<p>If the pathname specifies a device named <obj>DSK</obj>, that is replaced with the
<arg>working device</arg> for the pathname's host, and the directory defaults to
the <arg>working directory</arg> for the host if it is not specified.  See
<obj>fs:set-host-working-directory</obj>, below.
</p>

<p>Next, if the pathname does not specify a host, device, directory, or name,
that component comes from the defaults.
</p>

<p>If the value of <obj>fs:*always-merge-type-and-version*</obj> is non-<obj>nil</obj>,
the type and version are merged just like the other components.
</p>

<p>If <obj>fs:*always-merge-type-and-version*</obj> is <obj>nil</obj>, as it normally
is, the merging rules for the type and version are more complicated
and depend on whether the pathname specifies a name.  If the pathname
doesn't specify a name, then the type and version, if not provided,
come from the defaults, just like the other components.  However,
if the pathname does specify a name, then the type and version come
from the <arg>default-type</arg> and <arg>default-version</arg> arguments to
<obj>merge-pathname-defaults</obj>.  If those arguments were omitted, the
value of <obj>fs:*name-specified-default-type*</obj> (initially, <obj>:lisp</obj>)
is used as the default type, and <obj>:newest</obj> is used as the default
version.
</p>

<p>The reason for this is that the type and version
``belong to'' some other filename, and are thought to be unlikely to have
anything to do
with the new filename you are typing in.
</p>
<definition><define key="fs:set-host-working-directory-fun" name="fs:set-host-working-directory" type="fun"><args>host pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Sets the <arg>working device</arg> and <arg>working directory</arg> for <arg>host</arg> to
those specified in <arg>pathname</arg>.  <arg>host</arg> should be a host object or the
name of a host.  <arg>pathname</arg> may be a string or a pathname.
The working device and working directory are used for defaulting pathnames
in which the device is specified as <obj>DSK</obj>.

The editor command <obj>Meta-X Set Working Directory</obj> provides a convenient
interface to this function.
</description></definition>
<p>The following special variables are parts of the pathname interface
that are relevant to defaults.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="fs:*defaults-are-per-host*-var" name="fs:*defaults-are-per-host*" type="var"></define>

<description>This is a user customization option intended to be set by a user's
<obj>LISPM INIT</obj> file (see <ref chapter="36" definition-in-file="fd-hac" key="lispm-init-file" section="8" title="Logging In" type="section"></ref>).  The default value is
<obj>nil</obj>, which means that each program's set of defaults contains only
one default pathname.  If you type in just a host name and a colon, the
other components of the name default from the previous host, with
appropriate translation to the new host's pathname syntax.  If
<obj>fs:*defaults-are-per-host*</obj> is set to <obj>t</obj>, each program's set of
defaults maintains a separate default pathname for each host.  If
you type in just a host name and a colon, the last file that was
referenced on that host is used. 
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="fs:*always-merge-type-and-version*-var" name="fs:*always-merge-type-and-version*" type="var"></define>

<description>If this variable is non-<obj>nil</obj>, then the type and version are defaulted
only from the pathname defaults just like the other components.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="fs:*name-specified-default-type*-var" name="fs:*name-specified-default-type*" type="var"></define>

<description>If <obj>fs:*always-merge-type-and-version*</obj> is <obj>nil</obj>, then when a name is
specified but not a type, the type defaults from an argument to the
merging function.  If that argument is not specified, this variable's
value is used.  It may be a string or a canonical type keyword.  The
value is initially <obj>:lisp</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="*default-pathname-defaults*-var" name="*default-pathname-defaults*" type="var"></define>

<description>This is the default defaults alist; if the pathname primitives that need
a set of defaults are not given one, they use this one.  Most programs, however,
should have their own defaults rather than using these.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="cli:*default-pathname-defaults*-var" name="cli:*default-pathname-defaults*" type="var"></define>

<description>The Common Lisp version of the default pathname defaults.  The value of
this variable is a pathname rather than an alist.  This variable is
magically (with a forwarding pointer) identified with a cell in the
defaults-alist which the system really uses, so that setting this
variable modifies the contents of the alist.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="fs:last-file-opened-var" name="fs:last-file-opened" type="var"></define>

<description>This is the pathname of the last file that was opened.  Occasionally
this is useful as a default.  Since some programs deal with files
without notifying the user, you must not expect the user to know what
the value of this symbol is.  Using this symbol as a default may cause
unfortunate surprises if you don't announce it first, and so such use is
discouraged.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>These functions are used to manipulate defaults alists directly.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="fs:make-pathname-defaults-fun" name="fs:make-pathname-defaults" type="fun"></define>

<description>Creates a defaults alist initially containing no defaults.  If you ask
this empty set of defaults for its default pathname before anything has
been stored into it you get the file <obj>FOO</obj> on the user's home
directory on the host he logged in to.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:copy-pathname-defaults-fun" name="fs:copy-pathname-defaults" type="fun"><args>defaults</args>
</define>

<description>Creates a defaults alist, initially a copy of <arg>defaults</arg>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:default-pathname-fun" name="fs:default-pathname" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;optional</standard> defaults host default-type default-version</args>
</define>

<description>This is the primitive function for getting a default pathname out of a defaults alist.
Specifying the optional arguments <arg>host</arg>, <arg>default-type</arg>, and <arg>default-version</arg>
to be non-<obj>nil</obj> forces those fields of the returned pathname to contain those values.

If <obj>fs:*defaults-are-per-host*</obj> is <obj>nil</obj> (its default value), this gets the
one relevant default from the alist.  If it is <obj>t</obj>, this gets the default for
<arg>host</arg> if one is specified, otherwise for the host most recently used.

If <arg>defaults</arg> is not specified, the default defaults are used.

This function also has an additional optional argument <arg>internal-p</arg>, which is obsolete.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:default-host-fun" name="fs:default-host" type="fun"><args>defaults</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the default host object specified by the defaults-alist <arg>defaults</arg>.
This is the host used by pathname defaulting with the given defaults
if no host is specified.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:set-default-pathname-fun" name="fs:set-default-pathname" type="fun"><args>pathname <standard>&amp;optional</standard> defaults</args>
</define>

<description>This is the primitive function for updating a set of defaults.  It
stores <arg>pathname</arg> into <arg>defaults</arg>.
If <arg>defaults</arg> is not specified, the default defaults are used.
</description></definition></section><a name="Pathname Functions"></a>

<section chapter-number="25" name="Pathname Functions" number="4" title="Pathname Functions"><nopara></nopara>
<p>This function obtains a pathname from an object if that is possible.
</p>
<definition><define key="pathname-fun" name="pathname" type="fun"><args>object</args>
</define>

<description>Converts <arg>object</arg> to a pathname and returns that, if possible.  If
<arg>object</arg> is a string or symbol, it is parsed.  If <arg>object</arg> is a
plausible stream, it is asked for its pathname with the <obj>:pathname</obj>
operation.  If <arg>object</arg> is a pathname, it is simply returned.
Any other kind of <arg>object</arg> causes an error.
</description></definition><nopara></nopara>
<p>These functions are what programs use to parse and default file names
that have been typed in or otherwise supplied by the user.
</p>
<definition><define key="parse-namestring-fun" name="parse-namestring" type="fun"><args>thing <standard>&amp;optional</standard> host defaults <standard>&amp;key</standard> (start <obj>0</obj>) end junk-allowed</args>
</define>

<description>Is the Common Lisp function for parsing file names.  It is equivalent to
<obj>fs:parse-pathname</obj> except in that it takes some keyword arguments where
the other function takes all positional arguments.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:parse-pathname-fun" name="fs:parse-pathname" type="fun"><args>thing <standard>&amp;optional</standard> host defaults (start <obj>0</obj>) end junk-allowed</args>
</define>

<description>This turns <arg>thing</arg>, which can be a pathname, a string, a symbol, or a
Maclisp-style name list, into a pathname.  Most functions that are advertised
to take a pathname argument call <obj>fs:parse-pathname</obj> on it so that they can
accept anything that can be turned into a pathname.  If <obj>thing</obj> is itself
a pathname, it is returned unchanged.

If <arg>thing</arg> is a string, <arg>start</arg> and <arg>end</arg> are interpreted as
indices specifying a substring to parse.  They are just like
the second and third arguments to <obj>substring</obj>.  The rest of <arg>thing</arg> is
ignored.  <arg>start</arg> and <arg>end</arg> are ignored if <arg>thing</arg> is not a string.

If <arg>junk-allowed</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, parsing stops without error if the
syntax is invalid, and this function returns <obj>nil</obj>.  The second value
is then the index of the invalid character.  If parsing is successful,
the second value is the index of the place at which parsing was supposed
to stop (<arg>end</arg>, or the end of <arg>thing</arg>).  If <arg>junk-allowed</arg> is
<obj>nil</obj>, invalid syntax signals an error.

This function does <arg>not</arg> do defaulting, even though it has an argument
named <arg>defaults</arg>; it only does parsing.  The <arg>host</arg> and <arg>defaults</arg>
arguments are there because in order to parse a string into a pathname,
it is necessary to know what host it is for so that it can be parsed with
the file name syntax peculiar to that host.  If <arg>thing</arg> does not contain
a manifest host name, then if <arg>host</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, it is the host name
to use, as a string.  If <arg>thing</arg> is a string, a manifest host name may be
at the beginning or the end, and consists of the name of a host followed by a colon.
If <arg>host</arg> is <obj>nil</obj> then the host name is obtained
from the default pathname in <arg>defaults</arg>.  If <arg>defaults</arg> is not supplied,
the default defaults (<obj>*default-pathname-defaults*</obj>) are used.

Note that if <arg>host</arg> is specified, and <arg>thing</arg> contains a host name, an
error is signaled if they are not the same host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:pathname-parse-error-condition" name="fs:pathname-parse-error" type="condition"><args>(<obj>fs:pathname-error</obj> <obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This condition is signaled when <obj>fs:parse-pathname</obj> finds a syntax
error in the string it is given.

<obj>fs:parse-pathname</obj> sets up a nonlocal proceed type <obj>:new-pathname</obj>
for this condition.  The proceed type expects one argument, a pathname,
which is returned from <obj>fs:parse-pathname</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:merge-pathname-defaults-fun" name="fs:merge-pathname-defaults" type="fun"><args>pathname <standard>&amp;optional</standard> defaults default-type default-version</args>
</define>

<description>Fills in unspecified components of <arg>pathname</arg> from the defaults and returns
a new pathname.  This is the function that most programs should call to
process a file name supplied by the user.  <arg>pathname</arg> can be a pathname,
a string, a symbol, or a Maclisp namelist.  The returned value is always
a pathname.  The merging rules are documented on <ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="pathname-merging-rules" type="page"></ref>.

If <arg>defaults</arg> is a pathname, rather than a defaults alist, then the defaults
are taken from its components.  This is how you merge two pathnames.  (In Maclisp
that operation is called <obj>mergef</obj>.)

<arg>defaults</arg> defaults to the value of <obj>*default-pathname-defaults*</obj>
if unsupplied.  <arg>default-type</arg> defaults to the value of
<obj>fs:*name-specified-default-type*</obj>.  <arg>default-version</arg> defaults to <obj>:newest</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="merge-pathnames-fun" name="merge-pathnames" type="fun"><args>pathname <standard>&amp;optional</standard> defaults (default-version <obj>:newest</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>Is the Common Lisp function for pathname defaulting.  It does only some
of the things that <obj>fs:merge-pathname-defaults</obj> does.  It merges
defaults from <arg>defaults</arg> (which defaults to the value of
<obj>*default-pathname-defaults*</obj>) into <arg>pathname</arg> to get a new
pathname, which is returned.  <arg>pathname</arg> can be a string (or symbol);
then it is parsed and the result is defaulted.  <arg>default-version</arg> is
used as the version when pathname has a name but no version.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:merge-and-set-pathname-defaults-fun" name="fs:merge-and-set-pathname-defaults" type="fun"><args>pathname <standard>&amp;optional</standard> defaults default-type default-version</args>
</define>

<description>This is the same as <obj>fs:merge-pathname-defaults</obj> except that after it
is done the defaults-list <arg>defaults</arg> is modified so that the merged
pathname is the new default.  This is handy for programs that have
sticky defaults, which means that the default for each command
is the last filename used.  (If <arg>defaults</arg> is a pathname rather than a
defaults alist, then no storing back is done.)  The optional arguments
default the same way as in <obj>fs:merge-pathname-defaults</obj>.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>These functions convert a pathname into a namestring for all or some
of the pathname's components.
</p>
<definition><define key="namestring-fun" name="namestring" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a string containing the printed form of <arg>pathname</arg>, as you would type it in.
This uses the <obj>:string-for-printing</obj> operation.
</description></definition><definition><define key="file-namestring-fun" name="file-namestring" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a string showing just the name, type and version of <arg>pathname</arg>.
This uses the <obj>:string-for-dired</obj> operation.
</description></definition><definition><define key="directory-namestring-fun" name="directory-namestring" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a string showing just the device and directory of <arg>pathname</arg>.
This uses the <obj>:string-for-directory</obj> operation.
</description></definition><definition><define key="enough-namestring-fun" name="enough-namestring" type="fun"><args>pathname <standard>&amp;optional</standard> defaults</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a string showing just the components of <arg>pathname</arg> which would
not be obtained by defaulting from <arg>defaults</arg>.  This is the shortest
string that would suffice to specify pathname, given those defaults.  It
is made by using the <obj>:string-for-printing</obj>  operation on a modified
pathname.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>This function yields a pathname given its components.
</p>
<definition><define key="make-pathname-fun" name="make-pathname" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;key</standard> (defaults <obj>t</obj>) host device raw-device directory raw-directory name raw-name type raw-type version canonical-type original-type</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a pathname whose components are as specified.

If <arg>defaults</arg> is a pathname or a defaults-alist, any components not
explicitly specified default from it.  If <arg>defaults</arg> is <obj>t</obj> (which
is the default), then unspecified components default to <obj>nil</obj>, except
for the host (since every pathname must have a specific host), which
defaults based on <obj>*default-pathname-defaults*</obj>.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>These functions give the components of a pathname.
</p>
<definition><define key="pathname-host-fun" name="pathname-host" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the host component of <arg>pathname</arg>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-device-fun" name="pathname-device" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define><define key="pathname-directory-fun" name="pathname-directory" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define><define key="pathname-name-fun" name="pathname-name" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define><define key="pathname-type-fun" name="pathname-type" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define><define key="pathname-version-fun" name="pathname-version" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Likewise, for the other components
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>These functions return useful information.
</p>
<definition><define key="fs:user-homedir-fun" name="fs:user-homedir" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;optional</standard> host reset-p (user <obj>user-id</obj>) force-p</args>
</define><define key="user-homedir-pathname-fun" name="user-homedir-pathname" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;optional</standard> host reset-p (user <obj>user-id</obj>) force-p</args>
</define>


<description><index-entry index="concepts" title="home directory"></index-entry>
Returns the pathname of the <arg>user</arg> 's home directory on <arg>host</arg>.
These default to the logged in user and the host logged in to.  Home
directory is a somewhat system-dependent concept, but from the point of
view of the Lisp Machine it is the directory where the user keeps
personal files such as init files and mail.

This function returns a pathname without any name, type, or version
component (those components are all <obj>nil</obj>).

If <arg>reset-p</arg> is specified non-<obj>nil</obj>, the machine the user is logged
in to is changed to be <arg>host</arg>.

The synonym <obj>user-homedir-pathname</obj> is from Common Lisp.
</description></definition><definition><define key="init-file-pathname-fun" name="init-file-pathname" type="fun"><args>program-name <standard>&amp;optional</standard> host</args>
</define>


<description><index-entry index="concepts" title="init file"></index-entry>
Returns the pathname of the logged-in user's init file for the program <arg>program-name</arg>,
on the <arg>host</arg>, which defaults to the host the user logged in to.  Programs that load
init files containing user customizations call this function to find where to look
for the file, so that they need not know the separate init file name conventions of
each host operating system.  The <arg>program-name</arg> <obj>&quot;LISPM&quot;</obj> is used by the <obj>login</obj>
function.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>These functions are useful for poking around.
</p>
<definition><define key="fs:describe-pathname-fun" name="fs:describe-pathname" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>If <arg>pathname</arg> is a pathname object, this describes it, showing you its properties
(if any) and information about files with that name that have been loaded into the
machine.  If <arg>pathname</arg> is a string, this describes all interned pathnames that
match that string, ignoring components not specified in the string.
One thing this is useful for is finding the directory of a file
whose name you remember.  Giving <obj>describe</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-hac" key="describe-fun" title="Function describe" type="fun"></ref>) a pathname
object invokes this function.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:pathname-plist-fun" name="fs:pathname-plist" type="fun"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Parses and defaults <arg>pathname</arg>, then returns the list of properties of that pathname.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="fs:*pathname-hash-table*-var" name="fs:*pathname-hash-table*" type="var"></define>

<description>This is the hash table in which pathname objects are interned.  You can
find all pathnames ever constructed by applying the function <obj>maphash</obj>
to this hash table.
</description></definition></section><a name="generic-pathname"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="generic-pathname" number="5" title="Generic Pathnames"><index-entry index="concepts" title="generic pathname"></index-entry>

<p>A generic pathname stands for a whole family of files.  The property
list of a generic pathname is used to remember information about the
family, some of which (such as the package) comes from the <example>-*-</example> line
(see <ref chapter="26" definition-in-file="files" key="file-attribute-list" section="5" title="File Attribute Lists" type="section"></ref>)
of a source file in the family.  Several types of files with that name, in
that directory, belong together.  They are different members of the same
family; for example, they may be source code and compiled code.
However, there may be several other types
of files that form a logically distinct group even though they have
this same name; <obj>TEXT</obj> and <obj>PRESS</obj> for example.  The exact mapping is
done on a per host basis since it can sometimes be affected by host naming
conventions.
</p>

<p>The generic pathname of pathname <arg>p</arg> usually has the same host,
device, directory, and name as <arg>p</arg> does.  However, it has a version of
<obj>:unspecific</obj>.  The type of the generic pathname is obtained by
sending a <obj>:generic-base-type</obj> <arg>type-of-p</arg> message to the host of
<arg>p</arg>.  The default response to this message is to return the associated
type from <obj>fs:*generic-base-type-alist*</obj> if there is one, else
<arg>type-of-p</arg>.  Both the argument and the value are either strings, in
interchange form, or canonical type symbols.
</p>

<p>However, the ITS file system presents special problems.  One cannot
distinguish multiple generic base types in this same way since the type
component does not exist as such; it is derived from the second
filename, which unfortunately is also sometimes used as a version
number.  Thus, on ITS, the type of a generic pathname is always
<obj>:unspecific</obj> if there is any association for the type of the pathname
on <obj>fs:*generic-base-type-alist*</obj>. 
</p>

<p>  Since generic pathnames are primarily useful for storing properties,
it is important that they be as standardized and conceptualized as possible.
For this reason, generic pathnames are defined to be backtranslated, i.e.
the generic pathname of a pathname that is (or could be) the result of a logical host
translation has the host and directory of the logical pathname.  For
example, the generic pathname of <obj>OZ:&lt;L.WINDOW&gt;;STREAM LISP</obj> would be
<obj>SYS:WINDOW;STREAM⋃⋃</obj> if <obj>OZ</obj> is the system host.
</p>

<p>  All version numbers of a particular pathname share the
same identical generic pathname.  If the values of particular properties have
changed between versions, it is possible for confusion to result.
One way to deal with this problem is to have the property be a list associating
version number with the actual desired property.  Then it is relatively
easy to determine which versions have which values for the property in question
and select one appropriately.  But in the applications for which
generic pathnames are typically used, this is not necessary.
</p>

<p>The <obj>:generic-pathname</obj> operation on a pathname returns its
corresponding generic pathname.  See
<ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="pathname-generic-pathname-method" title="Method pathname :generic-pathname" type="method"></ref>.  The <obj>:source-pathname</obj> operation
on a pathname returns the actual or probable pathname of the
corresponding source file (with <obj>:newest</obj> as the version).  See
<ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="pathname-source-pathname-method" title="Method pathname :source-pathname" type="method"></ref>.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="fs:*generic-base-type-alist*-var" name="fs:*generic-base-type-alist*" type="var"></define>

<description>This is an association list of the file types and the type of the generic pathname
used for the group of which that file type is a part.  Constructing a generic
pathname replaces the file type with the association from this list, if there
is one (except that ITS hosts always replace with <obj>:unspecific</obj>).
File types not in this list are really part of the name in some sense.
The initial list is

<lisp> ((:text . :text) (&quot;DOC&quot; . :text)
  (:press . :text) (&quot;XGP&quot; . :text)
  (:lisp . :unspecific) (:qfasl . :unspecific)
  (nil . :unspecific))
</lisp>The association of <obj>:lisp</obj> and <obj>:unspecific</obj> is unfortunately made
necessary by the problems of ITS mentioned previously.  This way makes
the generic pathnames of logically mapped <obj>LISP</obj> files identical no
matter whether the logical host is mapped to an ITS host or not.

The first entry in the list with a particular cdr is the entry for
the type that source files have.  Note how the first element whose
cdr is <obj>:unspecific</obj> is the one for <obj>:lisp</obj>.  This is how the
<obj>:source-pathname</obj> operation knows what to do, by default.

Some users may need to add to this list.
</description></definition>
<p>The system records certain properties on generic pathnames
automatically.
</p>

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:warnings</obj></td><td>This property is used to record compilation and other warnings for the
file.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:definitions</obj></td><td>This property records all the functions and other things defined in the
file.  The value has one element for each
package into which the file has been loaded; the element's car is the
package itself and the cdr is a list of definitions made.

Each definition is a cons whose car is the symbol or function spec
defined and whose cdr is the type of definition (usually one of the
symbols <obj>defun</obj>, <obj>defvar</obj>, <obj>defflavor</obj> and <obj>defstruct</obj>).

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:systems</obj></td><td>This property's value is a list of the names of all the systems (defined
with <obj>defsystem</obj>, see <ref definition-in-file="maksys" key="defsystem-fun" title="Macro defsystem" type="mac"></ref>) of which this is a source file.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:file-id-package-alist</obj></td><td>This property records what version of the file was most recently loaded.
In case the file has been loaded into more than one package, as is
sometimes necessary, the loaded version is remembered for each package
separately.  This is how <obj>make-system</obj> tells whether a file needs to
be reloaded.  The value is a list with an element for each package that
the file has been loaded into; the elements look like

<lisp>(package file-information)
</lisp><arg>package</arg> is the package object itself; <arg>file-information</arg>
is the value returned by the <obj>:info</obj> operation on a file stream, and
is usually a cons whose car is the truename (a pathname) and whose cdr
is the file creation date (a universal time number).
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Some additional properties are put on the generic pathname by reading
the attribute list of the file (see <ref definition-in-file="files" key="fs:read-attribute-list-fun" title="Function fs:read-attribute-list" type="fun"></ref>).  It
is not completely clear that this is the right place to store these
properties, so it may change in the future.  Any property name can
appear in the attributes list and get onto the generic pathname; the
standard ones are described in <ref chapter="26" definition-in-file="files" key="file-attribute-list" section="5" title="File Attribute Lists" type="section"></ref>.
</p>
</section><a name="Pathname Operations"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="Pathname Operations" number="6" title="Pathname Operations"><p>This section documents the operations a user may send to a pathname
object.  Pathnames handle some additional operations that are only
intended to be sent by the file system itself, and therefore are not
documented here.  Someone who wants to add a new host to the system
would need to understand those internal operations.
</p>

<p>The operations on pathnames that actually operate on files are
documented in <ref chapter="26" definition-in-file="files" key="pathname-file-operations" section="4" title="Pathname Operations That Access Files" type="section"></ref>.  Certain pathname flavors,
for specific kinds of hosts, allow additional special purpose
operations.  These are documented in <ref chapter="25" definition-in-file="pathnm" key="specific-host-syntax" section="7" title="Host File Systems Supported" type="section"></ref> in the
section on the specific host type.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="pathname-generic-pathname-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns the generic pathname for the family of files of which this pathname is a member.
See <ref chapter="25" definition-in-file="pathnm" key="generic-pathname" section="5" title="Generic Pathnames" type="section"></ref> for documentation on generic pathnames.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-source-pathname-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns the pathname for the source file in the family of files to which
this pathname belongs.  The returned pathname has <obj>:newest</obj>
as its version.  If the file has been loaded in some fashion into the
Lisp environment, then the pathname type is that which the user actually
used.  Otherwise, the conventional file type for source files is determined
from the generic pathname.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-primary-device-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns the default device name for the pathname's host.  This is used
in generating the initial default pathname for a host.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>Operations dealing with wildcards.

<index-entry index="concepts" title="wildcards (in pathnames)"></index-entry>
</p>

<p>The character <example>*</example> in a namestring is a <arg>wildcard</arg>.
It means that the pathname is a really a pattern which
specifies a set of possible filenames rather than a single
filename.  The <example></example> matches any sequence of characters
within a single component of the name.  Thus, the component
<obj>FOO*</obj> would match <obj>FOO</obj>, <obj>FOOBAR</obj>, <obj>FOOT</obj>,
or any other component starting with <obj>FOO</obj>.
</p>

<p>Any component of a pathname can contain wildcards except the
host; wild hosts are not allowed because a known host is required
in order to know what flavor the pathname should be.
If a pathname component is written in the namestring as just <example>*</example>,
the actual component of the pathname instance is the keyword
<obj>:wild</obj>.  Components which contain wildcards but are not
simply a single wildcard are represented in ways subject to change.
</p>

<p>Pathnames whose components contain wildcards are called
<arg>wild</arg> pathnames.  Wild pathnames useful in functions such as
<obj>delete-file</obj> for requesting the deletion of many files at once.
Less obviously but more fundamentally, wild pathnames are
required for most use of the function <obj>fs:directory-list</obj>;
an entire directory's contents are obtained by specifying a
pathname whose name, type and version components are <obj>:wild</obj>.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="pathname-wild-p-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns non-<obj>nil</obj> if this pathname contains any sort of wildcards.
If the value is not <obj>nil</obj>, it is a keyword, one of
<obj>device</obj>, <obj>:directory</obj>, <obj>:name</obj>, <obj>:type</obj> and
<obj>:version</obj>, and it identifies the `first' component
which is wild.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-device-wild-p-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description><obj>t</obj> if this pathname's device contains any sort of wildcards.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-directory-wild-p-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-name-wild-p-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-type-wild-p-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>
<define key="pathname-version-wild-p-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Similar, for the other components that can be wild.  (The host cannot
ever be wild.)
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-pathname-match-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>candidate-pathname <standard>&amp;optional</standard> (match-host-p <obj>t</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>Returns <obj>t</obj> if <obj>candidate-pathname</obj> matches the pathname
on which the operation is invoked (called, in this context, the
<arg>pattern pathname</arg>).  If the pattern pathname contains
no wildcards, the pathnames match only if they are identical.
This operation is intended in cases where wildcards are expected.

Wildcard matching is done individually by component; the operation
returns <obj>t</obj> only if each component matches.  Within each component,
an occurrencs of <example>*</example> in pattern pathname's component can match
any sequence of characters in <arg>candidate-pathname</arg>'s component.
Other characters, except for host-specific wildcards, must match exactly.
<obj>:wild</obj> as a component of the pattern pathname matches any component
that <arg>candidate-pathname</arg> may have.

Note that if a component of the pattern pathname is <obj>nil</obj>,
<arg>candidate-pathname</arg>'s component must be <obj>nil</obj> also to match it.
Most user programs that read pathnames and use them as patterns
default unspecified components to <obj>:wild</obj> first.

Examples:

<lisp>(defvar pattern)
(defun test (str)
  (send pattern
        :pathname-match
        (parse-namestring str)))

(setq pattern
      (parse-namestring &quot;OZ:*:&lt;F*O&gt;*.TEXT.*&quot;))

(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FOO&gt;A.TEXT&quot;) =&gt; t
(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FO&gt;HAHA.TEXT.3&quot;) =&gt; t
(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FPPO&gt;HAHA.TEXT.*&quot;) =&gt; t
(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FOX&gt;LOSE.TEXT&quot;) =&gt; nil

(setq pattern
      (parse-namestring &quot;OZ:*:&lt;*&gt;A.TEXT*.5&quot;))

(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FOO&gt;A.TEXT.5&quot;) =&gt; t
(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FOO&gt;A.TEXTTTT.5&quot;) =&gt; t
(test &quot;OZ:&lt;FOO&gt;A.TEXT&quot;) =&gt; nil
</lisp>
If <arg>match-host-p</arg> is <obj>nil</obj>, then the host components of
the two pathnames are not tested.  The result then depends only
on the other components.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-translate-wild-pathname-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>target-pattern starting-data <standard>&amp;optional</standard> reversible</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a pathname corresponding to <arg>starting-data</arg> under the mapping
defined by the wild pathnames <arg>source-pattern</arg>, which is the
pathname this operation is invoked on, and <arg>target-pattern</arg>, the argument.
It is expected that <arg>starting-data</arg> would match
the source pattern under the <obj>:pathname-match</obj> operation.

<obj>:translate-wild-pathname</obj> is used by functions such as
<obj>copy-file</obj> which use one wild pathname to
specify a set of files and a second wild pathname to specify
a corresponding filename for each file in the set.
The first wild pathname would be used as the source-pattern
and the second, specifying the name to copy each file to,
would be passed as the <arg>target-pattern</arg> pathname.

Each component of the result is computed individually from the corresponding
components of <arg>starting-data</arg> and the pattern pathnames, using the
following rules:

<table><tbody><tr><td><standard>1)</standard></td><td>If <arg>target-pattern</arg>'s component is <obj>;wild</obj>,
then the result component is taken from <arg>starting-data</arg>.

</td></tr><tr><td><standard>2)</standard></td><td>Otherwise, each non-wild character in <arg>target-pattern</arg>'s component
is taken literally into the result.  Each wild character in
<arg>target-pattern</arg>'s component is paired with a wild character in
<arg>source-pattern</arg>'s component, and thereby with the portion of
<arg>starting-data</arg>'s component which that matched.  This portion
of <arg>starting-data</arg> appears in the result in place of the wild
target character.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
Example:

<lisp>(setq source (fs:parse-pathname &quot;OZ:PS:&lt;FOO&gt;A*B*.*.*&quot;))
(setq target (fs:parse-pathname &quot;OZ:SS:&lt;*&gt;*LOSE*.*B.*&quot;))

(send source :translate-wild-pathname target
      (fs:parse-pathname &quot;OZ:PS:&lt;FOO&gt;ALIBI.LISP.3&quot;))
 =&gt; <arg>the pathname </arg>OZ:SS:&lt;FOO&gt;LILOSEI.LISPB.3
</lisp>
It is easiest to understand the mapping as being done
in interchange case: the interchange components of the
arguments are used and the results specify the interchange
components of the value.

The type component is slightly special; if the <arg>target-pattern</arg> type
is <obj>:wild</obj>, the canonical type of <arg>starting-data</arg> is taken
and then interpreted according to the mappings of the target host.
Example:

<lisp>(setq source (fs:parse-pathname &quot;OZ:PS:&lt;FOO&gt;A*.*.*&quot;))
(setq target (fs:parse-pathname &quot;U://usr//foo//b*.*&quot;))

(send source :translate-wild-pathname target
      (fs:parse-pathname &quot;OZ:PS:&lt;FOO&gt;ALL.LISP&quot;))
 =&gt; <arg>the pathname </arg>U:/usr/foo/bll.l
</lisp>
If <arg>reversible</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, rule 1 is not used;
rule 2 controls all mapping.  This mode is used by logical
pathname translation.  It makes a difference when
the target pattern component is <obj>:wild</obj> and the source
pattern component contains wildcards but is not simply
<obj>:wild</obj>.  For example, with source and target pattern
components <obj>BIG<example>*</example></obj> and <example>*</example>, and starting data
<obj>BIGGER</obj>, the result is ordinarily <obj>BIGGER</obj> by rule 1,
but with reversible translation the result is <obj>GER</obj>.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>Operations to get a path name string out of a pathname object:
</p>
<definition>
<define key="pathname-string-for-printing-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns a string that is the printed representation of the path name.  This is
the same as what you get if you <obj>princ</obj> the pathname or take <obj>string</obj> of it.
</description></definition><definition><define key="pathname-string-for-wholine-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>length</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a string like the <obj>:string-for-printing</obj>, but designed to fit
in <arg>length</arg> characters.  <arg>length</arg> is a suggestion; the actual
returned string may be shorter or longer than that.  However, the
who-line updater truncates the value to that length if it is longer.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-string-for-editor-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns a string that is the pathname with its components rearranged so
that the name is first.  The editor uses this form to name its buffers.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-string-for-dired-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns a string to be used by the directory editor.  The string contains only
the name, type, and version.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-string-for-directory-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns a string that contains only the device and directory of
the pathname.  It identifies one directory among all directories on the host.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-string-for-host-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Returns a string that is the pathname the way the host file system likes to see it.
</description></definition><need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>Operations to move around through a hierarchy of directories:
</p>
<definition>
<define key="pathname-pathname-as-directory-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Assuming that the file described by the pathname is a directory,
return another pathname specifying that <arg>as</arg> a directory.
Thus, if sent to a pathname <obj>OZ:&lt;RMS&gt;FOO.DIRECTORY</obj>, it would return the
pathname <obj>OZ:&lt;RMS.FOO&gt;</obj>.  The name, type and version of the returned
pathname are <obj>:unspecific</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-directory-pathname-as-file-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>This is the inverse of the preceding operation.  It returns a pathname
specifying as a file the directory of the original pathname.  The name,
type and version of the original pathname are ignored.
</description></definition>
<p>The special symbol <obj>:root</obj> can be used as the directory component of a
pathname on file systems that have a root directory.
</p>
<need amount="1500"></need><nopara></nopara>
<p>Operations to manipulate the property list of a pathname:
</p>
<definition><define key="pathname-get-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>property-name <standard>&amp;optional</standard> default-value</args>
</define><define key="pathname-getl-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>list-of-property-names</args>
</define><define key="pathname-putprop-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>value property-name</args>
</define><define key="pathname-remprop-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>property-name</args>
</define>
<define key="pathname-plist-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>These manipulate the pathname's property list, and are used if you call
the property list functions of the same names (see <ref definition-in-file="fd-con" key="get-fun" title="Function get" type="fun"></ref>) giving
the pathname as the first argument.  Please read the paragraph on
<ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="pathname-plist-warning" type="page"></ref> explaining the care you must take in using
property lists of pathnames.
</description></definition></section><a name="zwei-hosts"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="zwei-hosts" number="7" title="Host File Systems Supported"><p>This section lists the host file systems supported, gives an example
of the pathname syntax for each system, and discusses any special idiosyncracies.
More host types may be added in the future.
</p>



<subsection name="NIL" title="ITS"><index-entry index="concepts" title="ITS pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>An ITS pathname looks like <obj>&quot;<arg>host</arg>: <arg>device</arg>: <arg>dir</arg>; <arg>name</arg> <arg>type-or-version</arg>&quot;</obj>.
The primary device is <obj>DSK:</obj> but other devices such as <obj>ML:</obj>, <obj>ARC:</obj>,
<obj>DVR:</obj>, or <obj>PTR:</obj> may be used.
</p>

<p>ITS does not exactly fit the virtual file system model, in that a file
name has two components (FN1 and FN2) rather than three (name, type, and
version).  Consequently to map any virtual pathname into an ITS
filename, it is necessary to decide whether the FN2 is the type or
the version.  The rule is that usually the type goes in the FN2 and the
version is ignored; however, certain types (<obj>LISP</obj> and <obj>TEXT</obj>) are
ignored and instead the version goes in the FN2.  Also if the type is <obj>:unspecific</obj>
the FN2 is the version.
</p>

<p>Given an ITS filename, it is converted into a pathname by making the FN2
the version if it is `&lt;', `&gt;', or a number.  Otherwise the FN2 becomes
the type.  ITS pathnames allow the special version symbols <obj>:oldest</obj>
and <obj>:newest</obj>, which correspond to `&lt;' and `&gt;' respectively.
</p>

<p>In every ITS pathname either the version or the type is <obj>:unspecific</obj>
or <obj>nil</obj>; sometimes both are.  When you create a new ITS pathname, if
you specify only the version or only the type, the one not specified
becomes <obj>:unspecific</obj>.  If both are specified, the version is
<obj>:unspecific</obj> unless the type is a normally-ignored type (such as
<obj>LISP</obj>) in which case the version is <obj>:newest</obj> and the type is
<obj>:unspecific</obj> so that numeric FN2's are found.
</p>

<p>Each component of an ITS pathname is mapped to upper case and truncated to
six characters.
</p>

<p>Special characters (space, colon, and semicolon) in a component of an ITS pathname
can be quoted by prefixing them with right horseshoe (<example>⊃</example>)
or equivalence sign (<example>≡</example>).  Right horseshoe is the same character code in the
Lisp Machine character set as control-Q in the ITS character set.
</p>

<p>An ITS pathname can have a structured name, which is a list of two strings,
the FN1 and the FN2.  In this case there is neither a type nor a version.
</p>

<p>An ITS pathname with an FN2 but no FN1 (i.e. a type and/or version but no name)
is represented with the placeholder FN1 `<example>↔</example>', because ITS pathname syntax
provides no way to write an FN2 without an FN1 before it.
</p>

<p>The ITS init file naming convention is <obj>&quot;<arg>homedir</arg>; <arg>user</arg> <arg>program</arg>&quot;</obj>.
</p>
<definition>
<define key="fs:*its-uninteresting-types*-var" name="fs:*its-uninteresting-types*" type="var"></define>

<description>The ITS file system does not have separate file types and version numbers;
both components are stored in the ``FN2''.  This variable is a list of the file
types that are ``not important''; files with these types use the FN2 for a version
number.  Files with other types use the FN2 for the type and do not have a version
number.  The initial list is

<lisp>(&quot;LISP&quot; &quot;TEXT&quot; nil :unspecific)
</lisp>Some users may need to add to this list.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="its-pathname-fn1-method" name="its-pathname" type="method"></define>
<define key="its-pathname-fn2-method" name="its-pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>These two operations return a string that is the FN1 or FN2 host-dependent
component of the pathname.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="pathname-type-and-version-method" name="pathname" type="method"></define><define key="pathname-new-type-and-version-method" name="pathname" type="method"><args>new-type new-version</args>
</define>

<description>These two operations provide a way of pretending that ITS pathnames can
have both a type and a version.  They use the first three characters of
the FN2 to store a type and the last three to store a version number.

On an ITS-pathname,
<obj>:type-and-version</obj> returns the type and version thus extracted (not
the same as the type and version of the pathname).
<obj>:new-type-and-version</obj> returns a new pathname constructed from the
specified new type and new version.

On any other type of pathname, these operations simply return or set
both the type component and the version component.
</description></definition></subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="TOPS-20 (Twenex), Tenex, and VMS."><index-entry index="concepts" title="TOPS-20 pathnames"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="Twenex pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>A pathname on TOPS-20 (better known as Twenex) looks like

<lisp><arg>host</arg>:<arg>device</arg>:&lt;<arg>directory</arg>&gt;<arg>name</arg>.<arg>type</arg>.<arg>version</arg>
</lisp>The primary device is <obj>PS:</obj>.
</p>

<p>TOPS-20 pathnames are mapped to upper case.  Special characters (including
lower-case letters) are quoted with the circle-cross (<example>⊗</example>) character, which
has the same character code in the Lisp Machine character set as Control-V,
the standard Twenex quoting character, in the ASCII character set.
</p>

<p>If you specify a period after the name, but nothing after that,
then the type is <obj>:unspecific</obj>, which translates into an empty
extension on the TOPS-20 system.  If you omit the period, you have
allowed the type to be defaulted.
</p>

<p>TOPS-20 pathnames allow the special version symbols <obj>:oldest</obj> and
<obj>:newest</obj>.  In the string form of a pathname, these are expressed as
`<obj>.-2</obj>', and as an omitted version.
</p>

<p>The directory component of a TOPS-20 pathname may be structured.  The
directory <obj>&lt;FOO.BAR&gt;</obj> is represented as the list <obj>(&quot;FOO&quot; &quot;BAR&quot;)</obj>.
</p>

<p>The characters <obj>*</obj> and <obj>%</obj> are wildcards that match any sequence of
characters and any single character (within one pathname component),
respectively.  To specify a filename that actually contains a <obj>*</obj> or
<obj>%</obj> character, quote the character with <obj>⊗</obj>.  When a component is
specified with just a single <obj>*</obj>, the symbol <obj>:wild</obj> appears in the
pathname object.
</p>

<p>The TOPS-20 init file naming convention is <obj>&quot;&lt;<arg>user</arg>&gt;<arg>program</arg>.INIT&quot;</obj>.
</p>

<p>When there is an attempt to display a TOPS-20 file name in the who-line and
there isn't enough room to show the entire name, the name is truncated
and followed by a center-dot character to indicate that there is more to
the name than can be displayed.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="Tenex pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>Tenex pathnames are almost the same as TOPS-20 pathnames, except that
the version is preceeded by a semi-colon instead of a period, the
default device is <obj>DSK</obj> instead of <obj>PS</obj>, and the quoting
requirements are slightly different.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="VMS pathnames"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="very mangled software"></index-entry>

<p>VMS pathnames are basically like TOPS-20 pathnames, with a few
complexities.  The primary device is <obj>USRD$</obj>.
</p>

<p>First of all, only alphanumeric characters are allowed in filenames
(though <obj>$</obj> and underscore can appear in device names).
</p>

<p>Secondly, a version number is preceded by `<obj>;</obj>' rather than by `<obj>.</obj>'.
</p>

<p>Thirdly, file types (called ``extensions'' in VMS terminology) are
limited to three characters.  Each of the system's canonical types has a
special mapping for VMS pathnames, which is three characters long:

<lisp>:lisp → LSP     :text → TXT     :qfasl → QFS    :midas → MID
:press → PRS    :widths → WID   :patch-directory → PDR
:qwabl → QWB    :babyl → BAB    :mail → MAI     :xmail → XML
:init → INI     :unfasl → UNF   :output → OUT
</lisp></p>
</subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Unix and Multics Pathnames"><index-entry index="concepts" title="Unix pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>A Unix pathname is a sequence of directory or file names separated by
slashes.  The last name is the filename; preceding ones are directory
names (but directories are files anyway).  There are no devices or
versions.  Alphabetic case is significant in Unix pathnames, no case
conversion is normally done, and lower case is the default.  Therefore,
components of solid upper or lower case are inverted in case when going
between interchange form and raw form.  (What the user types in a
pathname string is the raw form.)
</p>

<p>Unix allows you to specify a pathname relative to your default directory
by using just a filename, or starting with the first subdirectory name;
you can specify it starting from the root directory by starting with
a slash.  In addition, you can start with `<obj>..</obj>' as a directory name one
or more times, to refer upward in the hierarchy from the default
directory.
</p>

<p>Unix pathnames on the Lisp Machine provide all these features too, but
the canonicalization to a simple descending list of directory names
starting from the root is done on the Lisp Machine itself when you merge
the specified pathname with the defaults.
</p>

<p>If a pathname string starts with a slash, the pathname object that
results from parsing it is called ``absolute''.  Otherwise the pathname
object is called ``relative''.
</p>

<p>In an absolute pathname object, the directory component is either a
symbol (<obj>nil</obj>, <obj>:unspecific</obj> or <obj>:root</obj>), a string, or a list of
strings.  A single string is used when there is only one level of
directory in the pathname.
</p>

<p>A relative pathname has a directory that is a list of the symbol
<obj>:relative</obj> followed by some strings.  When the pathname is merged
with defaults, the strings in the list are appended to the strings
in the default directory.  The result of merging is always an absolute
pathname.
</p>

<p>In a relative pathname's string form, the string ``<obj>..</obj>'' can be used as a
directory name.  It is translated to the symbol <obj>:up</obj> when the string
is parsed.  That symbol is processed when the relative pathname is
merged with the defaults.
</p>

<p>Restrictions on the length of Unix pathnames require abbreviations for
the standard Zetalisp pathname types, just as for VMS.  On Unix the
preferred mappings of all canonical types are one or two characters
long.  We give here the mappings in raw form; they are actually
specified in interchange form.

<lisp>:lisp → l       :text → tx      :qfasl → qf     :midas → md
:press → pr     :widths → wd    :patch-directory → pd
:qwabl → qw     :babyl → bb     :mail → ma      :xmail → xm
:init → in      :unfasl → uf    :output → ot
</lisp></p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="Multics pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>The Multics file system is much like the Unix one; there are absolute
and relative pathnames, absolute ones start with a directory delimiter,
and there are no devices or versions.  Alphabetic case is significant.
</p>

<p>There are differences in details.  Directory names are terminated, and
absolute pathnames begun, with the character `<obj>&gt;</obj>'.  The containing
directory is referred to by the character `<obj>&lt;</obj>', which is complete in
itself.  It does not require a delimiter.  Thus, <obj>&lt;&lt;FOO&gt;BAR</obj> refers to
subdirectory <obj>FOO</obj>, file <obj>BAR</obj> in the superdirectory of the superdirectory
of the default directory.
</p>

<p>The limits on filename sizes are very large, so the system canonical
types all use their standard mappings.  Since the mappings are specified
as upper case, and then interpreted as being in interchange form, the
actual file names on Multics contain lower case.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Lisp Machine File Systems"><index-entry index="concepts" title="Lisp machine pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>There are two file systems that run in the MIT Lisp Machine system.
They have different pathname syntax.  Both can be accessed either
remotely like any other file server, or locally.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="Local-File pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>The Local-File system uses host name <obj>LM</obj> for the machine you are on.
A Local-File system on another machine can be accessed using the name of
that machine as a host name, provided that machine is known as a file
server.
</p>

<p>The remainder of the pathname for the Local-File system looks like
<obj>&quot;<arg>directory</arg>; <arg>name</arg>.<arg>type</arg>#<arg>version</arg>&quot;</obj>.  There is no restriction on the length
of names; letters are converted to upper case.  Subdirectories are
allowed and are specified by putting periods between the directory
components, as in <obj>RMS.SUBDIR;</obj>.
</p>

<p>The TOPS-20 pathname syntax is also accepted.  In addition, if the flag
<obj>fs:*lmfs-use-twenex-syntax*</obj> is non-<obj>nil</obj>, Local-File pathnames
print out using TOPS-20 syntax.  Note that since the printed representation
of a pathname is cached, changing this flag's value does not change the
printing of pathnames with existing representations.
</p>

<p>The Local-File system on the filecomputer at MIT has the host name <obj>FS</obj>.
</p>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="LMFILE pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>The LMFILE system is primarily for use as a file server, unless you have
512k of memory.  At MIT it runs on the filecomputer and is accessed
remotely with host name <obj>FC</obj>.
</p>

<p>The remainder of an LMFILE pathname looks like <obj>&quot;<arg>directory</arg>;
<arg>name</arg> <arg>type</arg>#<arg>version</arg>&quot;</obj>.  However, the directory and name can
be composed of any number of subnames, separated by backslashes.  This
is how subdirectories are specified.  <obj>FOO;BAR\X</obj> refers to the same
file as <obj>FOO\BAR;X</obj>, but the two ways of specifying the file have
different consequences in defaulting, getting directory listings, etc.
</p>

<p>Case is significant in LMFILE pathnames; however, when you open a file,
the LMFILE system ignores the case when it matches your pathname against
the existing files.  As a result, the case you use matters when you
create or rename a file, and appears in directory listings, but it is
ignored when you refer to an existing file, and you cannot have two
files whose names differ only in case.  When components are accessed in
interchange form, they are always converted to upper case.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Logical Pathnames"><index-entry index="concepts" title="logical pathnames"></index-entry>

<p>There is another kind of pathname that doesn't correspond to any
particular file server.  It is called a <arg>logical</arg> pathname, and its host
is called a logical host.  Every logical pathname can be translated
into a corresponding <arg>physical</arg> pathname because each logical host
records a corresponding actual (``physical'') host and rules for translating
the other components of the pathname.
</p>

<p>The reason for having logical pathnames is to make it easy to keep
bodies of software on more than one file system.  An important example
is the body of software that constitutes the Lisp Machine system.  Every
site has a copy of all of the sources of the programs that are loaded
into the initial Lisp environment.  Some sites may store the sources on
an ITS file system, while others may store them on a TOPS-20.  However,
system software (including <obj>make-system</obj>) wishes to be able to find a
particular file independent of the name of the host a particular site
stores it on, or even the kind of host it is.  This is done by means of
the logical host <obj>SYS</obj>; all pathnames for system files are actually
logical pathnames with host <obj>SYS</obj>.  At each site, <obj>SYS</obj> is defined
as a logical host, but translations are different at each site.  For
example, at MIT the source files are stored on the TOPS-20 system named
OZ, so MIT's site file says that <obj>SYS</obj> should translate to the host
<obj>OZ</obj>.
</p>

<p>Each logical host, such as <obj>SYS</obj>, has a list of translations, each of
which says how to map certain pathnames for that host into pathnames for
the corresponding physical host.  To translate a logical pathname, the
system tests each of the logical host's translations, in sequence, to see if it is applicable.
(If none is applicable, an error is signaled.)  A translation
consists of a pair of pathnames or namestrings, typically containing
wildcards.  Unspecified components in them default to <obj>:wild</obj>.  The
<arg>from</arg>-pathname of the translation is used to match against the
pathname to be translated; if it matches, the corresponding
<arg>to</arg>-pathname is used to construct the translation, filling in its
wild fields from the pathname being translated as in the
<obj>:translate-wild-pathname</obj> operation
(<ref definition-in-file="pathnm" key="pathname-translate-wild-pathname-method" title="Method pathname :translate-wild-pathname" type="method"></ref>).
</p>

<p>Most commonly the translations contain pathnames that have only
directories specified, everything else wild.  Then the other components
are unchanged by translation.
</p>

<p>If the files accessed through the logical host are moved, the translations
can be changed so that the same logical pathnames refer to the same files
on their new physical host via physical pathnames changed to fit
the restrictions and the conventions of the new physical host.
</p>

<p>Each translation is specified as a list of two strings.  The strings
are parsed into pathnames and any unspecified components are defaulted
to <obj>:wild</obj>.  The first string of the pair is the source pattern;
it is parsed with logical pathname syntax.  The second string is the
target pattern, and it is parsed with the pathname syntax for the
specified physical host.
</p>

<p>For example, suppose that logical host <obj>FOO</obj> maps to physical host
<obj>BAR</obj>, a Tops-20, and has the following list of translations:

<lisp>((&quot;BACK;&quot; &quot;PS:&lt;FOO.BACK&gt;&quot;)
 (&quot;FRONT;* QFASL&quot; &quot;SS:&lt;FOO.QFASL&gt;*.QFASL&quot;)
 (&quot;FRONT;&quot; &quot;PS:&lt;FOO.FRONT&gt;&quot;))
</lisp>Then all pathnames with host <obj>FOO</obj> and directory <obj>BACK</obj>
translate to host <obj>BAR</obj>, device <obj>PS</obj> and directory <obj>&lt;FOO.BACK&gt;</obj>
with name, type and version unchanged.
All pathnames with host <obj>FOO</obj>, directory <obj>FRONT</obj> and
type <obj>QFASL</obj> translate to host <obj>BAR</obj>, device <obj>SS</obj>,
directory <obj>&lt;FOO.QFASL&gt;</obj> and type <obj>QFASL</obj>, with name
and version unchanged.  All other pathnames with host <obj>FOO</obj>
and directory <obj>FRONT</obj> map to host <obj>BAR</obj>, device <obj>PS</obj>
and directory <obj>&lt;FOO.FRONT&gt;</obj>, with name, type and version
unchanged.  Note that the first translation whose pattern
matches a given pathname is the one that is used.
</p>

<p>Another site might define <obj>FOO</obj>'s to map to a Unix host
<obj>QUUX</obj>, with the following translation list:

<lisp>((&quot;BACK;&quot; &quot;//nd//foo//back//&quot;)
 (&quot;FRONT;&quot; &quot;//nd//foo//front//&quot;))
</lisp>This site apparently does not see a need to store the <obj>QFASL</obj>
files in a separate directory.  Note that the slashes are duplicated
to quote them for Lisp; the actual namestrings contain single slashes
as is usual with Unix.
</p>

<p>If the last translation's source pattern is entirely wild, it applies
to any pathname not so far handled.  Example:

<lisp>((&quot;BACK;&quot; &quot;//nd//foo//back//&quot;)
 (&quot;&quot; &quot;//nd//foo1//*//&quot;))
</lisp></p>

<p>Physical pathnames can also be <arg>back-translated</arg> into the
corresponding logical pathname.  This is the inverse transformation
of ordinary translation.  It is necessary to specify which logical
host to back translate for, as it may be that the same physical
pathname could be the translation of different logical pathnames
on different hosts.  Use the <obj>:back-translated-pathname</obj> operation,
below.
</p>
<definition><define key="fs:add-logical-pathname-host-fun" name="fs:add-logical-pathname-host" type="fun"><args>logical-host physical-host translations</args>
</define><define key="fs:set-logical-pathname-host-fun" name="fs:set-logical-pathname-host" type="fun"><args>logical-host <standard>&amp;key</standard> physical-host translations</args>
</define>

<description>Both create a new logical host named <arg>logical-host</arg>.  Its
corresponding physical host (that is, the host to which it should
forward most operations) is <arg>physical-host</arg>.  <arg>logical-host</arg> and
<arg>physical-host</arg> should both be strings.  <arg>translations</arg> should be a
list of translation specifications, as described above.
The two functions differ only in that one accepts positional
arguments and the other accepts keyword arguments.
Example:

<lisp>(add-logical-pathname-host &quot;MUSIC&quot; &quot;MUSIC-10-A&quot;
      '((&quot;MELODY;&quot; &quot;SS:&lt;MELODY&gt;&quot;)
        (&quot;DOC;&quot; &quot;PS:&lt;MUSIC-DOCUMENTATION&gt;&quot;)))
</lisp>
This creates a new logical host called <obj>MUSIC</obj>.  An attempt to open the
file <obj>MUSIC:DOC;MANUAL  TEXT  2</obj> will be re-directed to the file
<obj>MUSIC-10-A:PS:&lt;MUSIC-DOCUMENTATION&gt;MANUAL.TEXT.2</obj> (assuming that the
host <obj>MUSIC-10-A</obj> is a TOPS-20 system).
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:make-logical-pathname-host-fun" name="fs:make-logical-pathname-host" type="fun"><args>name</args>
</define>

<description>Requests that the definition of logical host <arg>name</arg> be
loaded from a standard place in the file system: namely,
the file <obj>SYS: SITE; <arg>name</arg> TRANSLATIONS</obj>.
This file is loaded immediately with <obj>load</obj>, in
the <obj>fs</obj> package.
It should contain code to create the logical host;
normally, a call to <obj>fs:set-logical-pathname-host</obj> or
<obj>fs:add-logical-pathname-host</obj>, above.

The same file is automatically reloaded, if it has been changed,
at appropriate times: by <obj>load-patches</obj>, and whenever
site information is updated.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="fs:logical-pathname-translated-pathname-method" name="fs:logical-pathname" type="method"></define>

<description>Converts a logical pathname to a physical pathname.  It returns the
translated pathname of this instance, a pathname whose host
component is the physical host that corresponds to this instance's
logical host.

If this operation is applied to a physical pathname, it simply returns
that pathname unchanged.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:logical-pathname-back-translated-pathname-method" name="fs:logical-pathname" type="method"><args>pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Converts a physical pathname to a logical pathname.
<arg>pathname</arg> should be a pathname whose host is the physical host
corresponding to this instance's logical host.  This returns
a pathname whose host is the logical host and whose translation
is <arg>pathname</arg>.  If <arg>pathname</arg> is not the translation
of any logical pathname on this instance's host, <obj>nil</obj> is returned.

Here is an example of how this would be used in connection with truenames.
Given a stream that was obtained by opening a logical pathname,

<lisp>(send stream :pathname)
</lisp>returns the logical pathname that was opened.

<lisp>(send stream :truename)
</lisp>returns the true name of the file that is open, which of course is
a pathname on the physical host.  To get this in the form of a logical
pathname, one would do

<lisp>(send (send stream :pathname)
      :back-translated-pathname
      (send stream :truename))
</lisp>
If this operation is applied to a physical pathname, it simply returns its
argument.  Thus the above example works no matter what kind of
pathname was opened to create the stream.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:unknown-logical-pathname-translation-condition" name="fs:unknown-logical-pathname-translation" type="condition"><args>(<obj>fs:pathname-error</obj> <obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This is signaled when a logical pathname has no translation.
The condition instance supports the <obj>:logical-pathname</obj> operation,
which returns the pathname that was untranslatable.

The proceed type <obj>:define-directory</obj> is supported.
It expects a single argument, a pathname or a string to be parsed into one.
This defines the target pattern for a translation whose source pattern
is the directory from the untranslatable pathname (and all else wild).
Such a translation is added to the logical host, making it possible
to translate the pathname.
</description></definition>
<p>A logical pathname looks like <obj>&quot;<arg>host</arg>: <arg>directory</arg>; <arg>name</arg> <arg>type</arg> <arg>version</arg>&quot;</obj>.
There is no way to specify a device; parsing a logical pathname
always returns a pathname whose device component is <obj>:unspecific</obj>.
This is because devices don't have any meaning in logical pathnames.
</p>

<p>The equivalence-sign character (<obj>≡</obj>) can be used for quoting special
characters such as spaces and semicolons.  The double-arrow character
(`<obj>↔</obj>') can be used as a place-holder for components that are <obj>nil</obj>,
and the up-horseshoe (`<obj>⋃</obj>') indicates <obj>:unspecific</obj> (generic pathnames
typically have <obj>:unspecific</obj> as the type and the version).
All letters are mapped to upper case unless quoted.  The <obj>:newest</obj>, <obj>:oldest</obj>,
and <obj>:wild</obj> values for versions are written as
`<obj>&gt;</obj>', `<obj>&lt;</obj>', and `<obj>*</obj>' respectively.
</p>

<p>There isn't any init file naming convention for logical hosts; you
can't log into them.  The <obj>:string-for-host</obj>,
<obj>:string-for-wholine</obj>, <obj>:string-for-dired</obj>, and <obj>:string-for-editor</obj> messages are all
passed on to the translated pathname, but the <obj>:string-for-printing</obj>
is handled by the <obj>fs:logical-pathname</obj> flavor itself and shows
the logical name.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Editor Buffer Pathnames"><p>The hosts <obj>ED</obj>, <obj>ED-BUFFER</obj> and <obj>ED-FILE</obj> are used in pathnames
which refer to buffers in the editor.  If you open such a pathname, you
get a stream that reads or writes the contents of an editor buffer.  The
three host names differ only in the syntax of the pathname, and in how
it is interpreted.
</p>

<p>The host <obj>ED</obj> is followed by an abbreviation that should complete to
the name of an existing editor buffer.  For example, the pathname
<obj>ED:FOO</obj> could refer to the buffer <obj>FOO.LISP PS:&lt;ME&gt; OZ:</obj>.
</p>

<p>The host <obj>ED-BUFFER</obj> is followed by an exact buffer name.  If there is
no buffer with that name, one is created.  This is most useful for
creating a buffer.
</p>

<p>The host <obj>ED-FILE</obj> is followed by an arbitrary pathname, including a
host name.  An <obj>ED-FILE</obj> pathname refers to a buffer visiting that
file.  If necessary, the file is read into the editor.  For example,
<obj>ED-FILE: OZ: PS:&lt;ME&gt;FOO.LISP</obj> would refer to the same buffer as
<obj>ED: FOO</obj>.  The current default defaults are used in processing the
pathname that follows <obj>ED-FILE</obj>, when the pathname is parsed.
</p>
</subsection></section><a name="file-stream"></a>


<section chapter-number="25" name="file-stream" number="8" title="Hosts"><index-entry index="concepts" title="host objects"></index-entry>

<p>Each host known to the Lisp Machine is represented by a flavor instance
known as a host object.  The host object records such things as the name(s)
of the host, its operating system type, and its network address(es).
Host objects print like <obj>#⊂FS:TOPS20-CHAOS-HOST &quot;MIT-OZ&quot;⊃</obj>, so they
can be read back in.
</p>

<p>Not all hosts support file access.  Those that do support it appear on the list
<obj>fs:*pathname-host-list*</obj> and can be the host component of pathnames.
A host object is also used as an argument when you make a Chaosnet
connection for any purpose.
</p>

<p>The hosts that you can use for making network connections appear in the
value of <obj>si:host-alist</obj>.  Most of the hosts you can use for pathnames
are among these; but some, such as logical hosts, are not.
</p>


<subsection name="NIL" title="Parsing Hostnames"><definition><define key="si:parse-host-fun" name="si:parse-host" type="fun"><args>namestring <standard>&amp;optional</standard> no-error-p (unknown-ok <obj>t</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a host object that recognizes the specified name.
If the name is not recognized, it is an error, unless <arg>no-error-p</arg> is
non-<obj>nil</obj>; in that case, <obj>nil</obj> is returned.

If <arg>unknown-ok</arg> is non-<obj>nil</obj> (the default), a host table server on the
local network is contacted, to see if perhaps it can find the name there.  If
it can't, an error is signalled or <obj>nil</obj> is returned, according to
<arg>no-error-p</arg>.  The host instance created in this manner contains all the kinds
of information that a host defined from the host table file has.

If a string of the form <obj>CHAOS|</obj><arg>nnn</arg> is used, a host object is
created and given <arg>nnn</arg> (interpreted as octal) as its Chaosnet
address.  This can be done regardless of the <arg>unknown-ok</arg> argument.

The first argument is allowed to be a host object instead of a string.
In this case, that argument is simply returned.
</description></definition><definition><define key="sys:unknown-host-name-condition" name="sys:unknown-host-name" type="condition"><args>(<obj>sys:local-network-error</obj> <obj>sys:network-error</obj> <obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This condition is signaled by <obj>si:parse-host</obj> when the
host is not recognized, if that is an error.

The <obj>:name</obj> operation on the condition instance returns the string
given to <obj>si:parse-host</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="si:get-host-from-address-fun" name="si:get-host-from-address" type="fun"><args>address network</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a host object given an address and the name of the network which
that address is for.  Usually the symbol <obj>:chaos</obj> is used as the
network name.

<obj>nil</obj> is returned if there is no known host with that address.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:get-pathname-host-fun" name="fs:get-pathname-host" type="fun"><args>name <standard>&amp;optional</standard> no-error-p</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a host object that can be used in pathnames.
If the name is not recognized, it is an error, unless <arg>no-error-p</arg> is
non-<obj>nil</obj>; in that case, <obj>nil</obj> is returned.

The first argument is allowed to be a host object instead of a string.
In this case, that argument is simply returned.

<obj>si:parse-host</obj> and <obj>fs:get-pathname-host</obj> differ in the set of
hosts searched.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fs:unknown-pathname-host-condition" name="fs:unknown-pathname-host" type="condition"><args>(<obj>fs:pathname-error</obj> <obj>error</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This condition is signaled by <obj>fs:get-pathname-host</obj> when the
host is not recognized, if that is an error.

The <obj>:name</obj> operation on the condition instance returns the string
given to <obj>fs:get-pathname-host</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="fs:*pathname-host-list*-var" name="fs:*pathname-host-list*" type="var"></define>

<description>This is a list of all the host objects that support file access.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="si:host-alist-var" name="si:host-alist" type="var"></define>

<description>This variable is a list of one element for each known network host.
The element looks like this:

<lisp>(<arg>full-name</arg> <arg>host-object</arg> (<arg>nickname</arg> <arg>nickname2</arg> ... <arg>full-name</arg>)
 <arg>system-type</arg> <arg>machine-type</arg> <arg>site</arg>
 <arg>network</arg> <arg>list-of-addresses</arg> <arg>network2</arg> <arg>list-of-addresses2</arg> ...)
</lisp>The <arg>full-name</arg> is the host's official name.  The <obj>:name</obj> operation on
the host object returns this.

The <arg>host-object</arg> is a flavor instance that represents this host.
It may be <obj>nil</obj> if none has been created yet; <obj>si:parse-host</obj>
creates them when they are referred to.

The <arg>nickname</arg>s are alternate names that <obj>si:parse-host</obj> should
recognize for this host, but which are not its official name.

The <arg>system-type</arg> is a symbol that tells what software the
host runs.  This is used to decide what flavor of host object to
construct.  Symbols now used include <obj>:lispm</obj>, <obj>:its</obj>, <obj>:tops-20</obj>,
<obj>:tenex</obj>, <obj>:vms</obj>, <obj>:unix</obj>, <obj>:multics</obj>, <obj>:minits</obj>, <obj>:waits</obj>,
<obj>:chaos-gateway</obj>, <obj>:dos</obj>, <obj>:rsx</obj>, <obj>:magicsix</obj>, <obj>:msdos</obj>, and others.
Not all of these are specifically understood in any way by the Lisp Machine.
If none of these applies to a host you wish to add, use a new symbol.

The <arg>machine-type</arg> is a symbol that describes the hardware of the
host.  Symbols in use include <obj>:lispm</obj>, <obj>:pdp10</obj>, <obj>:pdp11</obj>,
<obj>:vax</obj>, <obj>:nu</obj>, <obj>:pe3230</obj>, and <obj>:ibmpc</obj>.
<obj>(nil)</obj> has also been observed to appear here.
Note that these machine types attempt to have wide meanings, lumping
together various brands, models, etc.

The <arg>site</arg> does not describe anything about the host.  Instead it
serves to say what the Lisp Machine's site name was when the host was
defined.  This is so that, when a Lisp Machine system is moved to a
different institution that has a disjoint set of hosts, all the old
site's hosts can be deleted from the host alist by site
reinitialization.

The <arg>network</arg>s and lists of addresses describe how to reach the host.
Usually there is only one network and only one address in the list.
The generality is so that hosts with multiple addresses on multiple
networks can be recorded.  Networks include <obj>:chaos</obj> and <obj>:arpa</obj>.
The address is meaningful only to code for a specific network.
</description></definition></subsection>

<subsection name="NIL" title="Host Object Operations"><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :name</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the full, official name of the host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :name-as-file-computer</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the name to print in pathnames on this host (assuming it
supports files).  This is likely to be a short nickname of the host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :short-name</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the shortest known nickname for this host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :pathname-host-namep string</args>
</define>

<description>Returns <obj>t</obj> if <arg>string</arg> is recognized as a name for this host for
purposes of pathname parsing.  The local host will recognise <obj>LM</obj>
as a pathname host name.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :system-type</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the operating system type symbol for this host.
See <ref definition-in-file="fd-hac" key="host-table" type="page"></ref>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :network-type</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the symbol for one network that this host is connected to,
or <obj>nil</obj> if it is not connected to any.  <obj>:chaos</obj> is preferred if it
is one of the possible values.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :network-typep network</args>
</define>

<description>Returns <obj>t</obj> if the host is connected to the specified network.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :network-addresses</args>
</define>

<description>Returns an alternating list of network names and lists of addresses, such as

<lisp>(:chaos (3104) :arpa (106357002))
</lisp>You can therefore find out all networks a host is known to be on, and
its addresses on any network.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :sample-pathname</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a pathname for this host, whose device, directory, name, type
and version components are all <obj>nil</obj>.  Sample pathnames are often
useful because many file-system-dependent pathname operations depend
only on the pathname's host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :open-streams</args>
</define>

<description>Returns a list of all the open file streams for files on this host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :close-all-files</args>
</define>

<description>Closes all file streams open for files on this host.
</description></definition><definition><define key="&quot;host-method" name="&quot;host" type="metamethod"><args>objects&quot; :generic-base-type type-component</args>
</define>

<description>Returns the type component for a generic pathname assuming it is being
made from a pathname whose type component is the one specified.
</description></definition></subsection></section></chapter>
</document-part>
