<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><a name="query-chapter"></a>
<chapter name="query-chapter" number="33" title="Querying the User"><index-entry index="concepts" title="querying the user"></index-entry>

<index-entry index="concepts" title="yes-or-no"></index-entry>

<p>The following functions provide a convenient and consistent interface for
asking questions of the user.  Questions are printed and the answers are
read on the stream <obj>*query-io*</obj>, which normally is synonymous with
<obj>*terminal-io*</obj> but can be rebound to another stream for special applications.
</p>

<p>The macro <obj>with-timeout</obj> (see <ref definition-in-file="proces" key="with-timeout-fun" title="Macro with-timeout" type="mac"></ref>) can be used with
the functions in this chapter to assume an answer if the user does
not respond in a fixed period of time.
</p>

<p>We first describe two simple functions for yes-or-no questions, then
the more general function on which all querying is built.
</p>
<definition><define key="y-or-n-p-fun" name="y-or-n-p" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;optional</standard> format-string <standard>&amp;rest</standard> format-args</args>
</define>

<description>This is used for asking the user a question whose answer is either `y' for `yes'
or `n' for `no'.  It prints a message by passing <arg>format-string</arg> and
<arg>format-args</arg> to <obj>format</obj>, reads a one-character
answer, echoes it as `<obj>Yes</obj>' or `<obj>No</obj>', and returns <obj>t</obj> if the
answer is `yes' or <obj>nil</obj> if the answer is `no'.  The characters which
mean `yes' are `Y', `T', <obj>Space</obj>, and <obj>Hand-up</obj>.  The characters
which mean &quot;no&quot; are `N', <obj>Rubout</obj>, and <obj>Hand-down</obj>.  If any other
character is typed, the function beeps and demands a `Y or N' answer.

You should include a question mark and a space at the end of the message.
<obj>y-or-n-p</obj> does type `(Y or N)' for you.

<obj>*query-io*</obj> is used for all input and output.

<obj>y-or-n-p</obj> should be used only for questions that the user knows are
coming.  If the user is not going to be anticipating the question (e.g.
if the question is ``Do you really want to delete all of your files?'' out
of the blue) then <obj>y-or-n-p</obj> should not be used, because the user
might type ahead a `T', `Y', `N', <obj>Space</obj>, or <obj>Rubout</obj>, and
therefore accidentally answer the question.  In such cases, use
<obj>yes-or-no-p</obj>.
</description></definition><definition><define key="yes-or-no-p-fun" name="yes-or-no-p" type="fun"><args><standard>&amp;optional</standard> format-string <standard>&amp;rest</standard> format-args</args>
</define>

<description>This is used for asking the user a question whose answer is either
`yes' or `no'.  It prints a message by passing <arg>format-string</arg> and
<arg>format-args</arg> to <obj>format</obj>, beeps, and reads in a line
from <obj>*query-io*</obj>.  If the line is `yes', it returns <obj>t</obj>.
If the line is `no', it returns <obj>nil</obj>.  (Case is ignored, as are
leading and trailing spaces and tabs.)  If the input line is anything else,
<obj>yes-or-no-p</obj> beeps and demands a `yes or no' answer.

You should include a question mark and a space at the end of the message.
<obj>yes-or-no-p</obj> does type `(Yes or No)' for you.

<obj>*query-io*</obj> is used for all input and output.

To allow the user to answer a yes-or-no question with a single
character, use <obj>y-or-n-p</obj>.  <obj>yes-or-no-p</obj> should be
used for unanticipated or momentous questions; this is why it beeps
and why it requires several keystrokes to answer it.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fquery-fun" name="fquery" type="fun"><args>options format-string <standard>&amp;rest</standard> format-args</args>
</define>

<description>Asks a question, printed by <obj>(format *query-io* <arg>format-string</arg> <arg>format-args</arg>...)</obj>,
and returns the answer.  <obj>fquery</obj> takes care of checking for valid answers,
reprinting the question when the user clears the screen, giving help, and so
forth.

<arg>options</arg> is a list of alternating keywords and values, used to select among a variety
of features.  Most callers pass a constant list as the <arg>options</arg>
(rather than consing up a list whose contents varies).
The keywords allowed are:

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:type</obj></td><td>What type of answer is expected.  The currently-defined types are
<obj>:tyi</obj> (a single character), <obj>:readline</obj> or
<obj>:mini-buffer-or-readline</obj> (a line terminated by a carriage return).
<obj>:tyi</obj> is the default.  <obj>:mini-buffer-or-readline</obj> is nearly
the same as <obj>:readline</obj>, the only difference being that the former
uses a minibuffer if used inside the editor. 

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:choices</obj></td><td>Defines the allowed answers.  The allowed forms of choices are complicated and
explained below.  The default is the same set of choices as the <obj>y-or-n-p</obj>
function (see above).  Note that the <obj>:type</obj> and <obj>:choices</obj> options should
be consistent with each other.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:list-choices</obj></td><td>If <obj>t</obj>, the allowed choices are listed (in parentheses) after the question.
The default is <obj>t</obj>; supplying <obj>nil</obj> causes the choices not to be listed unless
the user tries to give an answer which is not one of the allowed choices.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:help-function</obj></td><td>Specifies a function to be called if the user hits the <obj>Help</obj> key.
The default help-function simply lists the available choices.
Specifying <obj>nil</obj> disables special treatment of <obj>Help</obj>.
Specifying a function of three arguments--the stream, the list of choices,
and the type-function--allows smarter help processing.  The type-function
is the internal form of the <obj>:type</obj> option and can usually be ignored.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:condition</obj></td><td>If non-<obj>nil</obj>, a signal name (see <ref definition-in-file="errors" key="signal-name" type="page"></ref>) to be signaled
before asking the question.  A condition handler may handle the
condition, specifying an answer for <obj>fquery</obj> to return, in which case
the user is not asked.  The details are given below.  The default
signal name is <obj>:fquery</obj>, which signals condition name <obj>:fquery</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:fresh-line</obj></td><td>If <obj>t</obj>, <obj>*query-io*</obj> is advanced to a fresh line before asking the question.
If <obj>nil</obj>, the question is printed wherever the cursor was left by previous typeout.
The default is <obj>t</obj>.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:beep</obj></td><td>If <obj>t</obj>, <obj>fquery</obj> beeps to attract the user's attention to the question.
The default is <obj>nil</obj>, which means not to beep unless the user tries to
give an answer which is not one of the allowed choices.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:stream</obj></td><td>The value should be either an I/O stream or a symbol or expression
that will evaluate to one.  <obj>fquery</obj> uses the specified stream
instead of <obj>*query-io*</obj> for all its input and output.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:clear-input</obj></td><td>If <obj>t</obj>, <obj>fquery</obj> throws away type-ahead before reading the user's response
to the question.  Use this for unexpected questions.  The default is <obj>nil</obj>,
which means not to throw away type-ahead unless the user tries to
give an answer which is not one of the allowed choices.  In that case, type-ahead
is discarded since the user probably wasn't expecting the question.

</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:make-complete</obj></td><td>If <obj>t</obj> and <obj>*query-io*</obj> is a typeout-window, the window is ``made complete''
after the question has been answered.  This tells the system that the contents
of the window are no longer useful.  Refer to the window system documentation
for further explanation.  The default is <obj>t</obj>.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
The argument to the <obj>:choices</obj> option is a list each of whose elements is
a <arg>choice</arg>.  The cdr of a choice is a list of the user inputs which correspond
to that choice.  These should be characters for <obj>:type :tyi</obj> or strings
for <obj>:type :readline</obj>.  The car of a choice is either a symbol which <obj>fquery</obj>
should return if the user answers with that choice, or a list whose first element
is such a symbol and whose second element is the string to be echoed when the
user selects the choice.  In the former case nothing is echoed.
In most cases <obj>:type :readline</obj> would use the first
format, since the user's input has already been echoed, and <obj>:type :tyi</obj> would
use the second format, since the input has not been echoed and furthermore is
a single character, which would not be mnemonic to see on the display.

A choice can also be the symbol <obj>:any</obj>.  If used, it must be the
last choice.  It means that any input is allowed, and should simply be
returned as a string or character if it does not match any of the
other choices.

Perhaps this can be clarified by example.  The <obj>yes-or-no-p</obj> function uses
this list of choices:

<lisp>((t &quot;Yes&quot;) (nil &quot;No&quot;))
</lisp>and the <obj>y-or-n-p</obj> function uses this list:

<lisp>(((t &quot;Yes.&quot;) #\y #\t #\space #\hand-up)
 ((nil &quot;No.&quot;) #\n #\rubout #\hand-down))
</lisp>
If a signal name is specified (or allowed to default to <obj>:fquery</obj>),
before asking the question <obj>fquery</obj> will signal it.  (See <ref chapter="31" definition-in-file="errors" key="condition" section="1" title="Conditions" type="section"></ref>
for information about conditions.)  <obj>make-condition</obj> will receive, in
addition to the signal name, all the arguments given to <obj>fquery</obj>,
including the list of options, the format string, and all the format
arguments.  <obj>fquery</obj> provides one proceed type, <obj>:new-value</obj>, and if
a condition handler proceeds, the argument it proceeds with is returned
by <obj>fquery</obj>.

If you want to use the formatted output functions instead of <obj>format</obj> to produce the
promting message, write

<lisp>(fquery <arg>options</arg> (format:outfmt <arg>exp-or-string</arg> <arg>exp-or-string</arg> ...))
</lisp><obj>format:outfmt</obj> puts the output into a list of a string, which makes <obj>format</obj>
print it exactly as is.  There is no need to supply additional arguments to the
<obj>fquery</obj> unless it signals a condition.  In that case the arguments might be passed so
that the condition handler can see them.  The condition handler will receive a list
containing one string, the message, as its third argument instead of just a string.  If
this argument is passed along to <obj>format</obj>, all the right things happen.
</description></definition><definition><define key="fquery-condition" name="fquery" type="condition"><args>(<obj>condition</obj>)</args>
</define>

<description>This condition is signaled, by default, by <obj>fquery</obj>.
The condition instance supports these operations:

<table><tbody><tr><td><obj>:options</obj></td><td>Returns the list of options given to <obj>fquery</obj>.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:format-string</obj></td><td>Returns the format string given to <obj>fquery</obj>.
</td></tr><tr><td><obj>:format-args</obj></td><td>Returns the list of additional args for format, given to <obj>fquery</obj>.
</td></tr></tbody></table>
One proceed type is provided, <obj>:new-value</obj>.  It should be used with a
single argument, which will be returned by <obj>fquery</obj> in lieue of asking
the user.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="format:y-or-n-p-options-var" name="format:y-or-n-p-options" type="const"></define>

<description>A suitable list to pass as the first argument to <obj>fquery</obj> to make
it behave like <obj>y-or-n-p</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="format:yes-or-no-p-options-var" name="format:yes-or-no-p-options" type="const"></define>

<description>A suitable list to pass as the first argument to <obj>fquery</obj> to make
it behave like <obj>yes-or-no-p</obj>.
</description></definition><definition>
<define key="format:y-or-n-p-choices-var" name="format:y-or-n-p-choices" type="const"></define>

<description>A list which <obj>y-or-n-p</obj> uses as the value of the <obj>:choices</obj> option.
</description></definition></chapter>
</document-part>