<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lmman.xsl"?>
<document-part><center><heading>Lisp Machine Manual</heading></center><center>Sixth Edition, System Version 99</center><center>June 1984</center><center>Richard Stallman</center><center>Daniel Weinreb</center><center>David Moon</center><nopara></nopara>
<p>This report describes research done at the Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.  Support for the
laboratory's artificial intelligence research is provided in part by the
Advanced Research Projects Agency of the Department of Defense under Office
of Naval Research Contract number N00014-80-C-0505.
<page></page><center><sub-heading>Preface</sub-heading></center></p>

<p>The Lisp Machine manual describes both the language and the operating system
of the Lisp Machine.  The language, a dialect of Lisp called Zetalisp,
is completely documented
by this manual.  The software environment and operating-system-like parts of
the system contain many things which are still in a state of flux.
This manual confines itself primarily to the stabler parts of the
system.  It describes how to program, but not for the most part how to
operate the machine.  The window system is documented separately in
the Lisp Machine Window System manual.
</p>

<p>Any comments, suggestions, or criticisms will be welcomed.  Please send
Arpa network mail to BUG-LMMAN@MIT-MC.
</p>

<p>Those not on the Arpanet may send U.S. mail to

<lisp><standard>Richard M. Stallman
Artificial Intelligence Lab
545 Technology Square
Cambridge, Mass. 02139</standard>
</lisp></p>

<p>Portions of this manual were written by Mike McMahon and Alan Bawden.
The chapter on the LOOP iteration macro is mostly a reprint of
Laboratory for Computer Science memo TM-169, by Glenn Burke.  Sarah
Smith, Meryl Cohen and Richard Ingria of LMI, and Richard Mlynarik of
MIT, helped to correct the manual.
</p>
<nopara></nopara><center><sub-heading>Personal Note from Richard Stallman</sub-heading></center>
<p>The Lisp Machine is a product of the efforts of many people too
numerous to list here and of the former unique unbureaucratic,
free-wheeling and cooperative environment of the M.I.T. Artificial
Intelligence Laboratory.  I believe that the commercialization of
computer software has harmed the spirit which enabled such systems to
be developed.  Now I am attempting to build a software-sharing movement to
revive that spirit from near oblivion.
</p>

<p>Since January 1984 I have been working primarily on the development of
GNU, a complete Unix-compatible software system for standard hardware
architectures, to be shared freely with everyone just like EMACS.
This will enable people to use computers and be good neighbors legally
(a good neighbor allows his neighbors to copy any generally useful
software he has a copy of).  This project has inspired a growing
movement of enthusiastic supporters.  Just recently the first free
portable C compiler compiled itself.  If you would like to contribute
to GNU, write to me at the address above.  Restrain social decay--help
get programmers sharing again.
</p>
<page></page>
</document-part>